<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A conference desired by the Lords and had by a committee of both houses, concerning the rights and privileges of the subjects discoursed by Sir Dudley Digges, Sir Edward Littleton Knight, now Lord Keeper, Master Selden, Sir Edward Cooke ; with the objections by Sir Robert Heath, Knight, then Attorney Generall, and the answers, 3 ̊Apr. 4. Car. 1628.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 228 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 47 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A69923</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E1284C</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8061</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12143595</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12143595</idno>
            <idno type="VID">54884</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A69923)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 54884)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 528:20 or 761:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A conference desired by the Lords and had by a committee of both houses, concerning the rights and privileges of the subjects discoursed by Sir Dudley Digges, Sir Edward Littleton Knight, now Lord Keeper, Master Selden, Sir Edward Cooke ; with the objections by Sir Robert Heath, Knight, then Attorney Generall, and the answers, 3 ̊Apr. 4. Car. 1628.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 91 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A.N. for Mathew Walbancke and Richard Best ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>This item is identified as Wing D1457 at reel 528:21 and as Wing E2793 at reel 761:15. Both numbers cancelled in Wing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of originals in Cambridge University Library and Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1603-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:54884:1"/>
            <p>A CONFERENCE DESIRED BY THE LORDS AND HAD by a Committee of both Houſes, CONCERNING THE <hi>RIGHTS</hi> AND <hi>PRIVILEGES</hi> of the <hi>Subjects.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Diſcourſed by
<list>
                  <item>Sir DUDLEY DIGGES.</item>
                  <item>Sir EDWARD LITTLETON Knight, now Lord Keeper.</item>
                  <item>Maſter SELDEN.</item>
                  <item>Sir EDWARD COOKE.</item>
               </list> With the <hi>Objections</hi> by Sir <hi>Robert Heath</hi> Knight then Attorney Generall, and the <hi>Anſwers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. Apr. 4. Car. 1628.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>A. N.</hi> for <hi>Mathew Walbancke,</hi> and <hi>Richard Beſt,</hi> and are to be ſold at their ſhops at Graies-Inne Gate. 1642.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb facs="tcp:54884:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:54884:2"/>
            <div n="Digges" type="introduction">
               <head>THE INTRODVCTION.</head>
               <byline>Sir <hi>Dudley Diggs.</hi>
               </byline>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MY LORDS,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Shall I hope auſpiciouſly begin this Conference this day, with an obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion out of the holy Story, <note place="margin">2. Chro. Cha. 34.</note> in the dayes of good King <hi>Ioſiah,</hi> when the Land was purged of Idolatrie, and the great men went about to repaire the houſe of God, while money was ſought for, there was found a Booke of the Law which had beene neglected, <note place="margin">2 Kings Cha. 22.</note> and afterwards being preſented to the good King, procured the bleſſing which your Lordſhips may reade in the Scriptures.</p>
               <p>My good Lords, I am confident your Lordſhips will as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheerefully joyne with the Commons, in acknowledgement of Gods great bleſſing in our good King <hi>Ioſiah,</hi> as the Knights, Citizens, and Burgeſſes, of the Houſe of Commons, by mee their unworthieſt ſervant, doe thankfully remember your moſt religiouſly and truly honourable invitation of them to the late Petition, for cleanſing this Land from Popiſh abominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which I may truly call a neceſſary and a happy repairing of the houſe of God, and to goe on with the parallel, whilſt we the Commons out of our good affections were ſeeking for money, we found I cannot ſay a booke of the Law, but many and fundamentall points thereof neglected and broken, which hath occaſioned our deſire of this conference, wherein I am firſt commanded to ſhew unto your Lordſhips in generall, that the Lawes of <hi>England</hi> are grounded on reaſon more ancient
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:54884:3"/> then bookes, conſiſting much in unwritten cuſtomes, yet ſo full of Juſtice and true equitie, that your moſt Honourable Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors, and Anceſtours propugned them with a <hi>nolumus mutari,</hi> and ſo ancient, that from the Saxon dayes, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Injuries and ruines of time, they have continued in moſt parts the ſame, as may appeare in old remaining Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Lawes of <hi>Ethelbert,</hi> the firſt Chriſtian King of Kent, <hi>Jna</hi> the King of the Weſt Saxons, <hi>Offer</hi> of the Mertians, and of <hi>Alfred</hi> the great Monarch who united the <hi>Saxon</hi> Hep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarchie, whoſe lawes are yet to bee ſeene publiſhed, as ſome thinke by Parliament, as he ſayes to that end, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t qui ſub uno rege, ſub una lege rege<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>entur.</hi> And though the Booke of <hi>Litch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field</hi> ſpeaking of the times of the <hi>Danes,</hi> ſayes that then <hi>Ius ſopitum erat in regno, leges &amp; conſuetudines ſopitae ſunt,</hi> and <hi>pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va voluntas, vis, &amp; violentia magis regnabant quam judicia vel juſtitia;</hi> yet by the bleſſing of God a good King, <hi>Edward,</hi> commonly called St. <hi>Edward,</hi> did awaken thoſe lawes, and as the old words are, <hi>Excitatas reparavit, reparatas decoravit, deco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratas confirmavit;</hi> Which <hi>confirmavit,</hi> ſhewes that good King <hi>Edward</hi> did not give thoſe Lawes which <hi>William</hi> the Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour and all his Succeſſours ſince that time have ſworne unto.</p>
               <p>And here my Lords, by many Caſes frequent in our mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derne Lawes ſtrongly concurring with thoſe of the ancient <hi>Saxon</hi> Kings, I might, if time were not more pretious, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate that our Lawes and Cuſtomes were the ſame.</p>
               <p>I will only intreat your Lordſhips leave to tell you, that as we have now, even in thoſe <hi>Saxon</hi> times they had their Court Barons, and Court Leets, and Sheriffs Courts, by which, as <hi>Tacitus</hi> ſayes of the <hi>Germanes,</hi> their Anceſtours <hi>Jura redde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant per pagos &amp; vicos;</hi> and I doe beleeve, as wee have now, they had their Parliaments, where new lawes were made <hi>cum conſenſu Praelatorum magnatum &amp; totius communitatis;</hi> or as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother writes, <hi>cum conſilio praelatorum, nobilium, &amp; ſapientium laicorum.</hi> I will adde nothing out of <hi>Glanvile</hi> that wrote in the time of <hi>H.</hi> 2. or <hi>Bracton</hi> that writ in the dayes of <hi>H.</hi> 3. only give me leave to cyte that of <hi>Forteſcue,</hi> the learned Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour to <hi>H.</hi> 6. who writing of this Kingdome, ſayes, <hi>Regnum
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:54884:3"/> iſtud moribus nationum, &amp; Regum temporibus, eiſdem quibus nunc Regitur legibus &amp; conſuetudinibus regebatur.</hi> But my good Lords, as the Poet ſaid of Fame, I may ſay of our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law;
<q>Ingreditur<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſolo caput inter nubila condit.</q> Wherefore the cloudy part being mine, I will make haſt to open way for your Lordſhips to heare more certaine Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and ſuch as goe on more ſure grounds.</p>
               <p>Be pleaſed then to know, that it is an undoubted and fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentall point of this ſo antient common law of <hi>England,</hi> that the Subject hath a true property in his goods and poffeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which doth preſerve as ſacred that <hi>Meum &amp; tuum,</hi> that is the nurſe of Induſtry, and mother of Courage, and without which there can be no Juſtice, of which <hi>Meum &amp; tuum</hi> is the proper object. But the undoubted birth-right of Free Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, hath lately not a little beene invaded and preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diced by preſſures, the more grievous, becauſe they have beene purſued by impriſonment contrary to the Franchiſes of this Land, and when according to the Lawes and Statutes of this Realme, redreſſe hath beene ſought for in a legall way by demanding <hi>Habeas Corpus</hi> from the Judges, and a diſcharge or triall according to the law of the Land, ſucceſſe hath failed, that now inforceth the Commons in this preſent Parliament aſſembled, to examine by Acts of Parliament, preſidents and reaſons, the truth of the Engliſh Subjects libertie, which I ſhall leave to learned Gentlemen, whoſe learned Arguments I hope will leave no place in your Lordſhips memories, for the errours and infirmities of your humbleſt ſervant, that doth thankfully acknowledge the great favour of your Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and patient Attention.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="Littleton" type="part">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:54884:4"/>
               <head>Sir <hi>Edward Littletons</hi> Argument.</head>
               <head>The Argument made by the Command of the houſe of Commons out of Acts of Parliament, and authorities of Law, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding the ſame, at the firſt Conference with the Lords concerning the libertie of the perſon of every Free-man.</head>
               <byline>Mr. <hi>Littleton.</hi>
               </byline>
               <div type="argument">
                  <opener>
                     <salute>MY LORDS,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Pon the occaſions delivered by the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, your Lordſhips have heard the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons have taken into their ſerious conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration the matter of perſonall libertie, and after long debate thereof on divers dayes, as well by ſolemne Arguments, as ſingle propoſitions of doubts and anſwers, to the end no ſcruple might remaine in any mans breſt unſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, they have upon a full Search, and cleare underſtanding of all things pertinent to the queſtion, unanimouſly declared; That no Free-man ought to bee committed or reſtrained in priſon by the command of the King or Privie Counſell, or any other, unleſſe ſome cauſe of the commitment, detainer, or reſtraint bee expreſſed, for which by law hee ought to bee committed, detained, or reſtrained. And they have ſent mee with other of their members, to repreſent unto your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips the true grounds of their reſolution, and have charged me particularly, leaving the reaſons of law, and preſidents, for others, to give your Lordſhips ſatisfaction, that this libertie is eſtabliſhed and confirmed by the whole State, the King, the Lords ſpirituall and temporall, and Commons, by ſeverall Acts of Parliament, the authoritie whereof is ſo great, that it can receive no anſwer ſave by interpretation or repeale by fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Statutes. And thoſe that I ſhall mind your Lordſhips of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:54884:4"/> are ſo direct in point, that they can beare no other expoſition at all, and ſure I am they are ſtill in force; The firſt of them is the grand Charter of the Liberties of <hi>England,</hi> firſt granted in the ſeventeenth yeare of King <hi>John,</hi> and renewed in the ninth yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the third, and ſince confirmed in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment above 30. times, the words there are Chap. 29. <hi>Nullus liber homo capiatur, vel impriſonetur, aut diſſeiſietur de libero tento ſuo vel liberis conſuetudinibus ſu is, aut utlageretur, aut exu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>letur, aut aliquo modo deſtruatur, nec ſuper eum ibimus, nec ſuper eum mittemus, niſi per legale judicium parium ſuorum vel per legem terrae.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Theſe words <hi>nullus liber homo,</hi> &amp;c. are expreſſe enough, yet it is remarkable, that <hi>Mathew Paris,</hi> an Authour of ſpeciall credit, doth obſerve, fol. 432. that the Charter of 9. <hi>H.</hi> 3. was the very ſame as that of 17. King <hi>John, in nullo diſſimilis</hi> are his words, and that of King <hi>Iohn</hi> he ſetteth downe <hi>verbatim,</hi> Fo. 342. and there the words are directly, <hi>Nec eum in Carce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem mittemus,</hi> and ſuch a corruption as is now in the print might eaſily happen 'twixt 9. <hi>H.</hi> 3. and 28. of <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. when this Charter was firſt exemplified, but certainly there is ſufficient left in that which is extant to decide this queſtion, for the words are, that no Free-man ſhall be taken or impriſoned, but by the lawfull judgement of his Peeres, which is by a Iurie of Peeres, ordinary Iurors for others, who are their Peeres, or by the law of the Land; Which words, Law of the Land, muſt of neceſſity be underſtood in this notion, to be by due Proces of the Law, and not the law of the Land generally, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe it would comprehend Bond-men (whom wee call Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laines) who are excluded by the word <hi>liber;</hi> For the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall law of the Land doth allow their Lords to impriſon them at their pleaſure without cauſe, wherein they only differ from the Free-men in reſpect of their perſons, who cannot be impriſoned without a cauſe. And that this is the true under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of theſe words <hi>per legem terrae,</hi> will more plainly appeareby divers other Statutes that I ſhall uſe, which doe expound the Law according. And though the words of this grand Charter be ſpoken in the third perſon, yet they are not to be underſtood of ſuites betwixt party and party, at leaſt
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:54884:5"/> not of them alone, but even of the Kings ſuites againſt his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, as will appeare by the occaſion of getting of that Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which was by reaſon of the differences betwixt thoſe Kings and their people, and therefore properly to bee applied unto their power over them, and not to ordinary queſtions betwixt Subject and Subject. Secondly, the words <hi>per legale judicium parium ſuorum,</hi> immediatly preceding the other of <hi>per legem terrae,</hi> are meant of trials at the Kings ſuit, and not at the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution of a Subject. And therefore if a Peere of the Realme be arraigned, at the Suit of the King, upon an Indictement of murther, he ſhall be tried by his Peeres; but if he be appealed of murther by a Subject, his triall ſhall be by an ordinary Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of 12. Freeholders, as appeareth in 10. <hi>Ed.</hi> 4. 6. 33. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>Brooke</hi> title trials 142. <hi>Stan. Cor. li.</hi> 3. <hi>ca.</hi> 1. <hi>fol.</hi> 152. and in 10. <hi>Ed.</hi> 4. 6. it is ſaid, ſuch is the meaning of <hi>Magna Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta,</hi> for the ſame reaſon; <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Sinor indite ferra trie per pares auter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſi ſoit ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale, Br. tit Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rone</hi> 153. <hi>nota bien.</hi>
                     </note> Therefore as <hi>per judicium parium ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orum,</hi> extends to the Kings Suit, ſo ſhall theſe words <hi>per le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem terrae;</hi> And in 8. <hi>Ed.</hi> 2. <hi>rot. parliament. membrana</hi> 7. there is a Petition that a Writ under the privie Seale went to the Guardians of the great Seale, to cauſe lands to bee ſeized into the Kings hands, by force of which there went a Writ out of the Chancery to the Eſchetor, to ſeize againſt the forme of the grand Charter, that the King nor his miniſters ſhall out no man of his Freehold-without reaſonable judgement, and the party was reſtored to his land, which ſheweth the Statute did extend to the King. There was no invaſion upon this perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall libertie, till the time of King <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. which was eftſoone reſented by the Subject, for in 5. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>ca.</hi> 9. it is ordained in theſe words; <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Sta.</hi> 5. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. 9.</note> It is enacted that no man from henceforth ſhal be attached by any occaſion, nor fore-judged of life or limbe, nor his lands, tenements, goods nor chattels ſeized into the Kings hands, againſt the forme of the great Charter, and the law of the Land. 25. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Sta.</hi> 15. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. 4.</note> It is more full, and doth expound the words of the grand Charter, and is thus; Whereas it is conteined in the grand Charter of the franchiſes of <hi>England,</hi> that none ſhall be impriſoned, nor put out of his freehold, nor free cuſtome, unleſſe it be by the law of the Land, It is awar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, aſſented, and eſtabliſhed, that from hence none ſhall bee
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:54884:5"/> taken by Petition or Suggeſtion, made to our Lord the King, or to his Counſell, unleſſe it be by Inditement, or preſentment of his good and lawfull people of the ſame neighbourhood, which ſuch Deeds ſhall be done in due manner, or by Proces made by Writ originall at the Common law, nor that none be Out of his Franchiſes, nor of his Freehold, unleſſe he be du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly brought in anſwer, and fore-judged of the ſame by the courſe of the law, and if any thing be done againſt the ſame, it ſhall be redreſſed and holden for none.</p>
                  <p>Out of this Statute I obſerve, <note place="margin">Lex terre ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound ꝑ pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces dée faict ꝑ bre original al co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon ley.</note> that what in <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and the preamble of the Statute is tearmed by the law of the Land, is in the body of this Act expounded to bee by Proces made by Writ originall at the Common law, which is a plain interpretation of the words (Law of the Land) in the grand Charter. And I note that the Law was made upon the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitment of divers to the Tower, no man yet knoweth for what.</p>
                  <p>28. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Sta.</hi> 28. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>ca.</hi> 3.</note> It is more direct, this libertie being follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with freſh Suit by the Subject, where the words are not many, but very full and ſignificant; That no man of what ſtate or condition he be, ſhall be put out of his lands nor tenements, nor taken, nor impriſoned, nor diſ-inherited, nor put to death, without he be brought in anſwer by due Proces of law.</p>
                  <p>Here your Lordſhips ſee the uſuall words of The law of the Land, are rendred by Due Proces of the law.</p>
                  <p>36. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>Rot. parliament. numero</hi> 9. <note place="margin">36. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>Rot. Parliam. nu.</hi> 9. Peticion del Commons.</note> Amongſt the Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Commons, one of them being tranſlated into Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh out of French, is thus; Firſt, that the great Charter, and the Charter of the Forreſt, and other Statutes made in the time of his Progenitors, for the profit of him, and his Como<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naltie, be well and firmly kept, and put in due execution, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out putting diſturbance, or making arreſt contrary to them by ſpeciall command, or in other manner.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <abbr>Rns</abbr> al petici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> The Anſwer to the Petition, which makes an Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Our Lord the King, by the Aſſent of the Prelates, Dukes, Earles, Barons, and the Commonaltie, hath ordained or eſtabliſhed, that the ſaid Charters and Statutes bee held and put in execution, according to the ſaid Petition. It is obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:54884:6"/> that the Statutes were to be put in execution according to the ſaid Petition, which is, that no arreſt ſhould bee made contrary to the Statutes, by ſpeciall command. This concludes the queſtion, and is of as great force, as if it were printed, for the Parliament roll is the true warrant of an Act, and many are omitted out of the bookes, that are extant in the Roll.</p>
                  <p>36. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>Rot. Parliamenti num.</hi> 22. <note place="margin">36. <hi>Ed</hi> 3. <hi>Rot. parl num.</hi> 22. Peticion d' Commons.</note> explaineth it further, for there the Petition is, <hi>Item,</hi> as it is contained in the grand Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and other Statutes, that no man be taken or impriſoned by ſpeciall command without Inditement, or other due Proces to be made by the law, and oftentimes it hath beene, and yet is, many are hindred, taken, and impriſoned without Inditement, or other Proces made by the Law upon them, as well of things done out of the Forreſt of the King, as for other things, that it would pleaſe our ſaid Lord to command thoſe to bee delivered, which are ſo taken by ſpeciall command, againſt the forme of the Charter and Statutes as aforeſaid.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <abbr>Rns</abbr> al Petici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> 
                     <hi>The anſwer is,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>St.</hi> 27. <hi>Ed</hi> 3. <hi>ca.</hi> 18.</note> The King is pleaſed, that if any man find himſelfe grieved, that he come and make his complaint, and right ſhall be done unto him. 37 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 8. agreeth in ſubſtance with them, it ſaieth, Though it be contained in the great Charter, that no man be taken nor impriſoned, nor put out of his Freehold without Proces of the law; Nevertheleſſe divers people make falſe ſuggeſtions to the King himſelfe, as well for malice as other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, whereof the King is often grieved, and divers of the Realme put in dammage againſt the forme of the ſame Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; Wherefore it is ordained, that all they which make Sug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtions, ſhall be ſent with the ſame Suggeſtions to the Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellour, Treaſurer, and his grand Counſell, and that they there find ſuretie to purſue their Suggeſtions, and incurre the ſame paine that the other ſhould have had, if he were attainted, in caſe that the Suggeſtion be found evill, and that then Proces of law be made againſt them without being taken or impriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, againſt the forme of the ſaid Charter, and other Statutes; here the law of the Land in the grand Charter is explained to be without Proces of law.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Sta.</hi> 42. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>ca.</hi> 13.</note> 42. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 13. At the requeſt of the Commons by their
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:54884:6"/> Petition put forth in this Parliament, to eſchew miſchiefe and dammage done to divers of his Commons by falſe accuſers, which oftentimes have made their accuſaſions, more for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge and ſingular profit, then for the profit of the King, or of his people, which accuſed perſons, Some have beene taken and cauſed to come before the Kings Counſell by Writ, and otherwiſe upon grievous paines againſt the Law, It is aſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and accorded for the good governance of the Commons, that no man be put to anſwer without preſentment or matter of record, or by due Proces and Writ originall according to the old law of the Land, And if any thing from hence bee done to the contrary, it ſhall be void in the Law, and holden for Error.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Sta.</hi> 42. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>Rot. Parliam. num.</hi> 12.</note> But this is better in the Parliament roll, where the Petition and anſwer, which make the Act, are ſet downe at large. 42. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>Rot. Parliamenti, numero</hi> 12.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Peticion des Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons.</note> 
                     <hi>The Petition.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Item,</hi> Becauſe that many of your Commons are hurt and deſtroyed by falſe accuſers, who make their accuſations more for their revenge and particular gaine, then for the profit of the King, or of his people. And thoſe that are accuſed by them, ſome are taken, and others are made to come before the Kings Counſell by Writ, or other commandement of the King, upon grievous paines contrary to the Law. That it would pleaſe our Lord the King, and his good Counſell, for the juſt government of his people, to ordaine, that if hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter any accuſer purpoſe any matter for the profit of the King, that the ſame matter be ſent to the Iuſtices of the one bench or of the other, or the Aſſiſes, to be inquired and determined ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Law; and if it concerne the Accuſer or party, that he take his Suit at the common law, and that no man bee put to anſwer without preſentment before Iuſtices or matter of Record, and by due Proces and originall Writ, according to the ancient law of the Land. And if any thing henceforward bee done to the contrary, that it bee void in law, and held for error.</p>
                  <p>Here by due Proces and originall Writ, according to the ancient Law of the Land, is meant the ſame thing, as <hi>per legem
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:54884:7"/> terrae, in Magna Charta,</hi> and the abuſe was, they were put to anſwer to the commandement of the King.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <abbr>Rns</abbr> al petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> 
                     <hi>The Kings Anſwer is thus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Becauſe that this Article is an Article of the grand Charter, the King willeth that this bee done, as the Petition doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand. By this appeareth that <hi>per legem terrae, in Magna Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta,</hi> is meant by due Proces of the Law.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Obi. hors d' l' Sta. de Weſtm. 1. cap. 15.</note> Thus your Lordſhips have heard act of Parliament in the point. But the Statute of <hi>Weſtminſt,</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 15. is urged to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove this opinion, where it is expreſly ſaid, <note place="margin">Que ne ſont repleviſeable <expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ſont com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit per le com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand le Roy.</note> that a man is not repleviſeable, who is committed by the command of the King, therefore the Command of the King, without any cauſe ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, is ſufficient to commit a man to priſon. And becauſe the ſtrength of the Argument may appeare, and the Anſwer bee better underſtood, I will reade the words of the Statute, which are thus. <note place="margin">Les parols d' Sta.</note> And foraſmuch as Sheriff, and others, which have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and kept in priſon perſons detected for Felonie, and often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times have let out by Replevin, ſuch as were not repleviable, and have kept in priſon ſuch as were repleviable, becauſe they would gaine of the one party, and grieve the other, And for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as before this time it was not certainly determined what perſons were repleviable, and what not, but only thoſe that were taken for the death of a man, or by the command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the King, or of his Iuſtices, or for the Forreſt, It is provided, and by the King commanded, that ſuch priſoners as were before outlawed, and they which have abjured the Realme, provers, and ſuch as be taken with the manner, and thoſe which have broken the Kings priſon, Theeves openly defamed and knowne, and ſuch as be appealed by approvers, ſo long as the approvers are living, if they be not of good name, and ſuch as be taken for burning of houſes feloniouſly done, or for falſe money, or for counterfeiting the Kings Seale, or perſons Excommunicate taken at the requeſt of the Biſhop, or for manifeſt offences, or for treaſon touching the King himſelfe, ſhall be in no wiſe repleviable by the common Writ, or without Writ; But ſuch as be indicted of Larceny by inqueſts taken before Sheriffs or Bayliffs by their office, or of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:54884:7"/> light ſuſpition, or of petit Larceny, that amounteth not above the value of twelve pence, if they were not guiltie of ſome other Larceny afore-time, or guilty of receipt of Felons, or of commandment, or of force, or of ayde of felony done, or guilty to ſome other treſpaſſe, for which one ought not to loſe either life or member, and a man appealed by an approver, after the death of the approver, if he be no common theefe or defamed, ſhall from henceforth be lett out by ſufficient ſuretie, whereof the Sheriff will be anſwerable, and that without gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ought of their goods; and if the Sheriffe, or any other, let any goe at large, by ſurety, that are not repleviable, if hee be Sheriffe, or Conſtable, or any other Bailiffe, or ſuch as hath a Fee, which hath keeping of priſons, and thereof be Attainted, he ſhall loſe his Office and Fee for ever. And if the under She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rife, Conſtable or Bailiffe, or ſuch as hath Fee for keeping of Priſons, doe it contrary to the will of his Lord, or any other Bailiffe being not of Fee, they ſhall have three yeares impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment, and make a Fine at the Kings pleaſure; And if any man with-hold Priſoners repleviſeable, after that they have offered ſufficient Suretie, he ſhall pay a grievous amercement to the King, and if he take any reward for the deliverance of ſuch, he ſhall pay double to the Priſoner, and alſo ſhall be in the great mercy of the King.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Anſwer.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It muſt be acknowledged, that a man taken by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement of the King is not repleviſeable, for ſo are the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe words of this Statute, but this maketh nothing againſt the Declaration of the Commons; For they ſay not the She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rife may replevy ſuch a one by ſureties, <hi>ſilicet manucaptores,</hi> but he is bayleable by the Kings Courts of Juſtice; for the better apprehending whereof, it is to be knowne, that there is a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betweene repleviſeable, <note place="margin">Diverſitie en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Bayleable &amp; repleviſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</note> which is alwayes by the She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rife upon pledges or Sureties given, and baileable, which is by a Court of Record, where the Priſoner is delivered to bayle, and they are his Gaolers, and may impriſon him, and ſhall ſuffer for him body for body, as appeareth 33. <hi>&amp;</hi> 36. <hi>Ed</hi> 3. <hi>titulo mainpriſe</hi> 12. <hi>&amp;.</hi> 13. where the difference betwixt Bayle and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:54884:8"/> Mainpriſe is expreſly, <hi>take,</hi> and if the words of the Statute themſelves be obſerved, it will appeare plainly that it extends to the Sherife and other inferiour Officers, and doth not bind the hands of the Judges. The preamble which is the key that openeth the Entrance into the meaning of the makers of the Law is; Foraſmuch as Sherifes and others have taken and kept in priſon perſons detected of felonie. Out of theſe words I obſerve that it nominateth Sherifes, and then if the Judges ſhould be included, they muſt be comprehended under that generall word, <hi>other,</hi> which doth not extend to thoſe of an higher ranke, but to inferiours, for the beſt by all courſes is firſt to be named. And therefore if a man bring a Writ of Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes and ſervices, and name rents and other things, the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſhall not include homage, which is a perſonall ſervice; and of an higher nature, but it ſhall extend to ordinary annuall ſervice, 31. <hi>E.</hi> 1. <hi>Droit.</hi> 67. So the Statute of 13. <hi>El. cap.</hi> 10. which beginneth with Colledges, Deanes and Chapters, Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, Vicars, and concludes with theſe words, and others ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſpirituall promotions, ſhall not comprehend Biſhops that are of an higher degree, as appeareth in the Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterburies</hi> Caſe, 2. Reports, <hi>fol.</hi> 46. <hi>B.</hi> And thus much is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained in the very Statute towards the end; when it doth enumerate thoſe were meant by the word, <hi>other,</hi> namely un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Sherifes, Conſtables, Bailiffs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Againe, the words are Sherifes, and others which have taken and kept in priſon; Now every man knoweth, Judges doe neither arreſt, nor keep men in priſon, that is the office of Sherifes and other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour Miniſters. Therefore this Statute meant ſuch only and not Judges. The words are further, that they let out by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plevin ſuch as are not repleviable, that is the proper language for a Sherife; Nay, more expreſſe afterward in the body of the Statute, that ſuch as are there mentioned, ſhall be in no wiſe repleviſeable by the common Writ, which is <hi>de Homine replegiando,</hi> and is directed to the Sherife, nor without Writ which is by the Sherife <hi>Ex officio.</hi> But that which receives no anſwer is this, that the command of the Juſtices, who derive their authoritie from the Crowne is the equalled and to this purpoſe with the command of the King. And therefore by all
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:54884:8"/> reaſonable conſtruction, it muſt needs relate to Officers that are ſubordinate to both, as Sherifes, under-Sherifes, Bailiffes, Conſtables, and the like. And it were a harſh expoſition to ſay that the Juſtices might not diſcharge their owne com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and yet that reaſon would conclude as much; And that this was meant of the Sherife and other miniſters of Juſtice by the recitall 27. <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. and likewiſe by <hi>Fleta</hi> a manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript ſo called, becauſe the Author lay in the Fleet when he made the booke, for he <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 52. in his Chapter of turnes, and the viewes of the hundred Court in the Countrey ſetteth downe the Articles of the Charges that are there to be inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of, amongſt which, one of them is <hi>De Replegibilibus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſte detentis &amp; irreplegiabilibus dimiſſis;</hi> which cannot be meant of not bayling by the Juſtices, for what hath the inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Courts in the Countrey to doe with the acts of the Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces? and to make that more plaine, he ſetteth downe in that chapter, that concerneth Sherifes only, the very Statute of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> 1. which he tranſlates <hi>verbatim</hi> out of the French into the Latine, ſave that he renders, taken by the command of of the Juſtices, thus, <hi>per judicium Juſticiariorum,</hi> and his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face to the Statute plainly ſheweth, that he underſtood it of replevine by Sherifs, for he ſaith, <hi>Qui debent per plegios hoc di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitti, qui non declarat hoc Statutum,</hi> and <hi>per plegios</hi> is before the Sherife. But for direct authority, <note place="margin">22. <hi>H.</hi> 6. 46. ꝑ <hi>Newton</hi> Chiefe Iuſtice.</note> it is the opinion of <hi>Newton,</hi> Chiefe Juſtice, 22. <hi>H.</hi> 6 46. where his words are theſe; It cannot be intended that the Sherife did ſuffer him to goe at large by Mainpriſe, for where one is taken by the Writ of the King, or the Commandement of the King, he is irrepleviſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, but in ſuch caſe his friends may come to the Juſtices from him if he be arreſted, and purchaſe a <hi>Superſedeas;</hi> This Judge concludes that the Sherife cannot deliver him that is taken by the command of the King, for that he is irrepleviſeable, which is the very word of the Satute: but, ſaith he, his friends may come to the Juſtices and purchaſe a <hi>Superſedeas;</hi> So he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares the very queſtion, that the Sherife had no power, but the Juſtices had power to deliver him that is committed by the Kings command; and both the ancient and moderne pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe manifeſt as much, for he that is taken for the death of a
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:54884:9"/> man, or for the Forreſt, is not repleviable by the Sherife, yet they are ordinarily bayled by the Juſtice, and were by the Kings Writs directed to the Sherifs in the times of <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. and 2. as appeares in the cloſe rolls, which could not be done if they were not baylable. And it is every dayes experience, that the Juſtices of the Kings Bench doe bayle for Murther, and for offences done in the Forreſt, which they could not doe, if they were irrepleviſeable, if <hi>Weſtminſt.</hi> 1. were meant of the Juſtices, aſwell as of the Sherifs. For authorities that have beene offered to prove the contrary, are in number three, the firſt is 21. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>Rot.</hi> 2. which alſo is in the Booke of Pleas in Parliament at the Tower, upon an action there brought, <hi>fol.</hi> 44. It is not an Act of Parliament, but a reſolution in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament upon an action there brought, which was uſuall in thoſe times. And the caſe is, that <hi>Stephen Rabaz,</hi> the Sherife of the Counties of <hi>Leiceſter</hi> and <hi>Warwicke,</hi> was queſtioned, for that he had let at large by Surety, amongſt others, one <hi>William,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Walter le Peſons,</hi> againſt the will and command of the King, whereas the King had commanded him by Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters under the Privie Seale, that he ſhould doe no favour to any man that was committed by the Earle of <hi>Warwicke,</hi> as that man was, whereunto the Sherife anſwered, that he did it at the requeſt of ſome of the Kings houſhold upon their Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and becauſe the Sherife did acknowledge the receipt of the Kings Letters, thereupon he was committed to priſon ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the forme of the Statute. To this I anſwer, the Sherife was juſtly puniſhed, for that he is expreſly bound by the Statute of <hi>Weſtminſt.</hi> 1. which was agreed from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, but this is no proofe, that the Iudges had no power to bayle this man.</p>
                  <p>The next Authority is 33. <hi>H.</hi> 6. in the Court of Common Pleas, <hi>fo.</hi> 28. <hi>b.</hi> 29. where <hi>Sobert Poyning</hi> Eſquire, was brought to the Barre upon a <hi>Capias,</hi> and was returned, that he was committed <hi>Per Duos de Conſilio,</hi> (which is ſtrongeſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt what I maintaine) <hi>pro diverſis cauſis regem tangent.</hi> and he made an Attorney there in an action, whence it's infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that the returne was good, and the party could not be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered. To this the anſwer is plaine.</p>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:54884:9"/>
                  <p>Firſt, no opinion is delivered in that booke, one way or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, upon the returne, neither is there any teſtimony whether he were delivered, or bayled, or not. 2. It appeares expreſly, that he was brought thither, to be charged in an action of debt, at another mans ſuit, and no deſire of his owne to bee delivered, or bayled, and then if hee were reman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, it is in no way materiall to the queſtion in hand. But that which is moſt relied upon, is the opinion of <hi>Stan.</hi> in his Booke of Pleas of the Crowne <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 18. <hi>fol.</hi> 72. 73. in his Chapter of Mainpriſe, where hee reciteth the Statute of <hi>Weſtminst.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 15. and then ſaith thus; <note place="margin">
                        <abbr>Rns</abbr> al Obi. hors de Stan. pl. Cor' 72.</note> By this Statute it appeares, that in foure caſes at the Common law a man was not repleaviable, to wit, thoſe that were taken for the death of a man, by the command of the King, or his Juſtices, or for the Forreſt, thus farre he is moſt right, then hee goeth on, and ſaith, as to the command of the King, that is underſtood by the command of his owne mouth, or his counſell, which is incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porated unto him, and speake with his mouth, or otherwiſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Writ or Capias to take a man, which is the Kings com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, would be as much; and as to the command of the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that is meant their abſolute commandment, for if it bee by their ordinary commandment, he is repleviable by the Sherife, if it be not in ſome of the caſes prohibited by the Statute.</p>
                  <p>The anſwer that I give unto this is, that <hi>Stanford</hi> had ſaid nothing whether a man may be committed without cauſe by the Kings command, or whether the Judges ought not to bayle him in ſuch Caſe, only that ſuch a one is not repleviſeable, which is agreed, for that belongs to the Sherife. And becauſe no man ſhould thinke he meant any ſuch thing, hee concludes the whole Sentence touching the Command of the King and the Juſtices, that one committed by the ordinary command of the Juſtice, is repleviſeable by the Sherife, or at leaſt it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares not that he meant, that a man committed by the King, or by the Privie Counſell without cauſe, ſhould not be bayleable by the Juſtices, and he hath given no opinion in this caſe; what he would have ſaid, if he had beene asked the queſtion cannot be knowne, neither doth it appeare, that by any thing that hee hath ſaid, hee meant any ſuch thing as would bee inferred
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:54884:10"/> out of him. And now my Lords I have performed the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of the Commons, and as I conceive ſhall cleare the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of perſonall libertie, an antient and undoubted truth, fortified with ſeven Acts of Parliament, and not oppoſed by any Statute or authoritie of law whatſoever.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="objections">
                  <head>The objections of the Kings Counſell, with like anſwers made thereunto, at the two other Conferences touching the ſame matter.</head>
                  <p>IT was agreed by the Attorney generall, that the 7. Statutes urged by the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons were in force, and that <hi>magna Charta</hi> did extend moſt properly to the King, but he ſaid, <note place="margin">1. <hi>Object.</hi>
                     </note> 1. That ſome of them are in generall words, and therefore conclude nothing, but are to be expounded by the Preſidents, and others that bee more particular, are applied to the Suggeſtions of Subjects, and not to the Kings command ſimply of it ſelfe; <note place="margin">Le <abbr>Rns</abbr>.</note> Hereunto it was anſwered, that the Statutes were as direct as could bee, which appeareth by the reading of them, and that though ſome of them ſpeak of Suggeſtions of the Subjects, yet others do not, and they that doe are as effectuall, for that they are in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall reaſon, a commitment by the command of the King, being of as great force, when it moveth from a Suggeſtion from a Subject, as when the King taketh notice of it himſelfe, the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for that Kings ſeldome intermeddle with matters of this nature, but by information from ſome of their people.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">2. <hi>Object.</hi>
                     </note> 2. Maſter Attorney objected that <hi>per legem terrae in Magna Charta</hi> (which is the foundation of this queſtion) cannot be underſtood for Proces of the Law and originall Writs, for that in criminall proceedings no originall Writ is uſed at all, But every Conſtable either for Felonie or breach of the Peace, or to prevent the breach of the Peace, may commit without Proces or originall Writ, and it were hard the King ſhould not have the power of a Conſtable. And the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute cyted by the Commons, make Proces of the Law, and Writ originall, to be all one.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Le <abbr>Rns</abbr>.</note> The anſwer of the Commons to this Objection was, that they doe not intend originall Writs only by the Law
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:54884:10"/> of the Land, but all other legall Proces, which comprehends the whole proceedings of Law upon cauſe, other then triall by Jury, <hi>Judicium parium,</hi> unto which it is oppoſed, thus much is imported <hi>ex vi termini</hi> out of the word Proces, and by the true acceptation thereof in the Statutes which have beene uſed by the Commons to maintaine their Declaration, and moſt eſpecially the Statutes of 25. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. where it appeareth that a man ought to be brought in to anſwer by the courſe of the Law, having former mention of Proces made by originall Writ. And in 28. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. by the courſe of the Law is rendred by the due Proces of the Law. And 36. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>Rot. Parliamenti numero</hi> 20. The Petition of the Commons ſaith, that no man ought to bee impriſoned by ſpeciall command without Inditement or other due Proces to bee made by the Law. 37. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 18. calleth the ſame thing Proces of the Law, and 42. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. ſtileth it by due Proces and Writ originall, where the conjunctive muſt be taken for a diſ-junctive, which charge is ordinary to an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of Statutes and Deeds to avoid inconveniences, to make it ſtand with the reſt, and with reaſon, as it may be col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected by the law of the Land in <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> by the courſe of the Law in 25. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. by the due Proces of Law in 28. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. other due Proces to bee made by the Law in 36. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. Proces of the Law in 37. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. and by due Proces and Writ originall in 42. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. are one and the ſame thing, the later of theſe Statutes referring alwayes to the former, and that all of them import any due and regular proceedings of law upon a cauſe other then the triall by Jurie. And this appeareth 10. <hi>Rep.</hi> 74. in the Caſe of the Marſhalſea, and 11. <hi>Rep.</hi> 99. <hi>James Baggs</hi> Caſe, where it is underſtood of giving Juriſdiction by Charter or preſcription which is the ground of a proceeding by courſe of law. And in <hi>Seldens</hi> Notes on <hi>Forteſcue, fol.</hi> 29. where it is expounded for Law wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, which is likewiſe a tryall by law by the oath of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, differing from that by Jurie. And it doth truly compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend theſe and all other regular proceedings in law upon cauſe, which gives authoritie to the Conſtable to arreſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on cauſe. And if this be not the true expoſition of theſe words
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:54884:11"/> 
                     <hi>per legem terrae,</hi> the Kings Counſell were deſired to declare their meaning, which they never offered to doe, and yet cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly theſe words were not put into the Statute without ſome intention of conſequence. <note place="margin">3. <hi>Objection.</hi>
                     </note> And thereupon Mr. Serjant <hi>Aſhley</hi> offered an interpretation of them thus, namely; that there were divers Lawes of this Realme, as the Common law, the law of the Chancery, the Eccleſiaſticall law, the law of the Admiral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, or Marine law, the law of Merchants, the Marſhall law, and the law of State, and that theſe words <hi>per legem terrae</hi> doe extend to all theſe Lawes. <note place="margin">
                        <abbr>Rns</abbr> a ceo.</note> To this it was anſwered, that wee read of no law of State, and that none of theſe Lawes can bee meant there ſave the Common law, which is the principall and generall Law, and is alwayes underſtood by the way of Excellencie, when mention is of the law of the Land gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, and that though each of the other Lawes, which are ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted into this Kingdome by Cuſtome or Act of Parliament, may juſtly be called a law of the Land, yet none of them can have the preheminence to be ſtiled the Law of the Land. And no Statute, Law booke, or other authority, printed or unprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, could be ſhewen, to prove that the Law of the Land, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing generally mentioned, was ever intended of any other then the Common Law, and yet even by theſe other Lawes a man may not be committed without a cauſe expreſſed. But it ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth with the rule of other legall expoſitions, that <hi>per legem terrae</hi> muſt be meant the Common Law, which is the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and univerſall Law, by which men hold their Inheritan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and therefore if a man ſpeake of Eſcuage generally, it is underſtood as <hi>Littleton</hi> obſerveth, <hi>Sect.</hi> 99. of the incertaine Eſcuage, which is a Knights ſervice tenure, for the defence of the Realme, by the body of the tenant in time of warres, and not of a certaine Eſcuage which giveth only a contribution in money, and no perſonall ſervice. And if a Statute ſpeak of the Kings Courts of Record, it is meant only of the 4. at <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minster</hi> by way of excellencie, 6. <hi>Rep.</hi> 20. <hi>Gregories</hi> Caſe; So the Canoniſts by the Excommunication ſimply ſpoken, doe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the greater excommunication. And the Emperour in his Inſtitutions ſaith, that the Civill Law being ſpoken gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally is meant of the Civill law of <hi>Rome,</hi> though the Law of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:54884:11"/> every City is a Civill Law; as when a man names the Poet, the Graecians underſtand <hi>Homer,</hi> the Latiniſts <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgil.</hi> 2. Admit <hi>per legem terrae</hi> extend to all the Lawes of the Land, yet a man muſt not be committed by any of them, but by the due pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings that are executed by thoſe Lawes, and upon a cauſe declared. <note place="margin">4. <hi>Object.</hi>
                     </note> Againe, it was urged that the King was not bound to expreſſe a cauſe of impriſonment, becauſe there may be in it matter of State, not fit to be revealed for a time, leſt the confederates thereupon make meanes to eſcape the hands of Juſtice. And therfore the Statute cannot be intended to reſtrain all commitments unleſſe a cauſe be expreſſed, for that it would be very inconvenient and dangerous to the State, to publiſh the Cauſe at the very firſt. <note place="margin">Le <abbr>Rns</abbr>.</note> Hereunto it was replied by the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons, that all danger and inconvenience may be avoided by declaring a generall Cauſe, as for Treaſon, ſuſpition of Treaſon, miſpriſion of Treaſon or felonie, without ſpecifying the particular, which can give no greater light to a confederate, then will bee conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctured by the very apprehenſion upon the impriſonment, if nothing at all were expreſſed. <note place="margin">5. <hi>Object.</hi>
                     </note> It was further alledged that there was a kind of contradiction in the poſition of the Houſe of Commons, when they ſay a party committed without a cauſe ſhewed, ought to be delivered or bayled, Bayling being a kind of impriſonment, deliverie a totall freeing. <note place="margin">Le <abbr>Rns</abbr>.</note> To this it hath beene anſwered, that it hath alwayes beene the diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Judges, to give ſo much reſpect to a commitment by the Command of the King, or the Privie Councell, which are ever intended to be don in juſt and weighty cauſes, that they will not preſently let them free, but bayle them to anſwer what ſhall be objected againſt them on his Majeſties behalfe; but if any other inferiour Officer doe commit a man without ſhewing cauſe, they doe inſtantly deliver him, as having no cauſe to expect their leaſure. So the delivery is applied to an impriſonment by the command of ſome meane miniſter of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, Bayling when it is done by the command of the King or his Counſell.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">6. <hi>Object.</hi>
                     </note> It was urged by Mr. Attorney, that Bayling is a grace and favour of a Court of Juſtice, and that they may refuſe to doe it. <note place="margin">Le <abbr>Rns</abbr>.</note> This was agreed to be true in divers caſes, as where the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:54884:12"/> cauſe appears to be for felony or other crimes expreſſed, for that there is another way to diſcharge them in convenient time by their triall, and yet in theſe caſes the conſtant practiſe hath beene anciently and modernly to bayle men, but where no cauſe of the impriſonment is returned, but the Command of the King, there is no way to deliver ſuch perſons by triall or otherwiſe, but that of the <hi>Habeas Corpus.</hi> And if they ſhould be then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, they might be perpetually impriſoned without any remedy at all, and conſequently a man that had committed no offence might be in worſe caſe then a great offender, for the later ſhould have an ordinary tryall to diſcharge him, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhould never be delivered. <note place="margin">7. <hi>Objection.</hi>
                     </note> It was further ſaid, that though the Statute of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 15. be a Statute which by way of proviſion did extend only to the Sherife, yet the recitall of that touching the foure cauſes wherein a man was not reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſeable at the common law, namely thoſe that were commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for the death of a man, by the command of the King, or of his Juſtices, or for the Forreſt, did declare that the Juſtices could not bayle ſuch a one, and that repleviſeable and bayleable were <hi>Synomina</hi> all one, and that <hi>Stanford</hi> a Judge of great autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie doth expound it accordingly, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Stan. pl. Cor.</hi> 72.</note> and that neither the Statute nor he ſay repleviſeable by the Sherife, but generally without reſtraint; And that if the chiefe Juſtice committed a man, hee is not to be inlarged by any other Court, as appeareth in the Regiſter. <note place="margin">Le <abbr>Rns</abbr>.</note> To this it was anſwered, That the recitall of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the Statute, relateth only to the Sherife only, as appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth by the very words. 2. That Repleviſeable is to the Sherife, for that the word imports no more, but a man committed by the chiefe Juſtice, is bayleable by the Court of Kings Bench. 3. That <hi>Stanford</hi> meaneth all of the Sherife, or at leaſt hee hath not ſufficiently expreſſed that he intended the Juſtices. 4. It was denied that Repleviſeable and bayleable was the ſame, for they differ in reſpect of the place where they are uſed, bayle being in the Kings Court of record, Repleviſeable before the Sherife, and they are of ſeverall natures, repleviable being a letting at large upon ſuretie, bayling being when one <hi>traditur in Balliv.</hi> the bayle are his Iaylors and may impriſon him, and ſhall ſuffer body for body, which is not of replevying by Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:54884:12"/> and differeth from Mainpriſe in this, <note place="margin">Diverſitie en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter bayle &amp; mainpriſe.</note> Mainpriſe is an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking in a ſome certaine, Bayling to anſwer the condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation in Civill cauſes, and for criminall, body for body. And the reaſons and authorities in the firſt Conference were then renewed, and no exceptions taken to any ſave that in 22. <hi>H.</hi> 6. it doth not appeare that the command of the King was by his mouth, which muſt be intended, or by his Counſell, which is all one, as is obſerved by <hi>Stanford,</hi> for the words are that a man is not repleviſeable by the Sherife, who is committed by the Writ or the commandment of the King, 21. <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. <hi>Rot.</hi> 2. <hi>Dorſ.</hi> was Cyted by the Kings Counſell, that it was anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that it concerned the Sherife of <hi>Leiceſter</hi> ſhire only, and not the power of the Iudges, 33. <hi>H.</hi> 6. the Kings Attorney con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed was nothing to the purpoſe, and yet that Booke hath beene uſually cited by thoſe that maintaine the contrary to the Declaration of the Commons. And therefore ſuch ſudden opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions as have been given thereupon are not to be regarded the foundation failing. And where it was ſaid that the French of 36. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>Rot. parliamenti numero</hi> 9. which can receive no an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer did not warrant what was inferred thence, but that theſe words <hi>Sauns diſturbance mettre, ou arreſt fair, &amp; le contre per ſpecial mandement ou autre mannere</hi> muſt bee underſtood, that the Statute ſhould be put in execution without putting diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance, or making arreſt to the contrary by ſpeciall command or in other manner, The Commons did utterly denie the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation given by the Kings Counſell, and to juſtifie their owne, did appeale to all men that underſtood the French, and upon the 7. Statutes did conclude, that their Declaration remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned an undoubted truth, not controlled by any thing ſaid to the contrary.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="precedents">
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:54884:13"/>
                  <head>Sir <hi>Edward Littletons</hi> Preſidents. The true Copies of the Records not printed, which were uſed on either ſide of that part of the Debate.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>Inter Record. Domini Regis Caroli in Theſaurario Recept. Scaca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rij ſui ſub custodia Theſaurar. &amp; Camerar ibidem rema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent. viz. pl. Coram ipſo Domino Rege, &amp; conſilio ſuo, ad Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liamentum ſuum poſt Paſch. apud London in Maner' Arch-Epiſcopi Ebor', Anno Regni Domini Regis Ed. 3. 21. inter alia ſic continetur ut ſequitur, Rot. 2. indorſo.</p>
                  </argument>
                  <div xml:lang="lat" type="record">
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Tephanus Rabaz Vicecomes Leic. &amp; Warw. co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram ipſo Domino Rege &amp; ejus Concilio arena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus &amp; ad Rudom poſitus de hac quod cum I. B. E. H. &amp; W. H. nuper balliv' ipſius Vicecomitis per Dom. Regem fuiſſent aſſign' ad Gaolas Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini Regis deliberand. eidem vic' quendam W. P. per quendam appellatorem ante adventum eorum Juſticiariorum ibidem appellat. &amp; capt. vivente ipſo appellatore uſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> diem delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rationis coram eis fact. demiſſat. per pleviam contra formam Statuti, &amp;c. Et etiam quendam R. de C. qui de morte hominis ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicatus fuit, &amp; per eundem Vicecomit' captus, Jdem Vic' per pleviam demiſit contra formam Stat. &amp; etiam idem R. ſine fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris coram eiſdem Iuſticiar' ad deliberationem praed' produxit contra conſuetudinem Regni, &amp; ſimiliter quendam Walterum fili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um Walteri le Perſone qui per praeceptum Comitis Warwici cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus fuit dimiſit per pleviam contra vocem &amp; preceptu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Domini Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis Cum idem Dominus Rex ſub literas ſuas ſub privato Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gillo ſuo eidem Vicecomit precipiet quod nulli per preceptum praed. Com. Warwici capt. aliquam gratiam vel favorem fac. &amp;c. Et ſuper hoc praefat. I. B. qui preſens eſt, &amp; qui fuit primus Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciar.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:54884:13"/> pred. premiſſ. recordatur &amp; pred. vicecomes dicit quoad. pred. W. P. ipſe nunquam a tempore captionis ipſius W. per pred appella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torem demiſſ. fuit per pleviam aliquam ante advent. pred. Juſticiar. Imo dicit quod per dimid. Anni ante Adventum eorum Justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciar. captus fuit. Et quoad pred. R. bene cognoſcit quod ipſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſit eum per pleviam, &amp; hoc bene facere poterat ratione ac au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritate officij, ſui, eo quod captus fuit pro quadam ſimplici tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſione, &amp; non pro aliqua felonia, pro qua replegiare non potuit. Et quoad 3. vizt. W. filium Perſone bene cognoſcit quod ipſe captus fuit per preceptum pred. Com. Warwici &amp; quod dimiſit eum per ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viam. Sed dicit quod hoc fecit ad rogatum quorundam de Hoſpitio &amp; Curia Dom. Regis qui eum ſimiliter inde rogaverint per lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras ſuas. Et ſuper hoc idem vicecom queſivit per Dom. Regem quis eum rogavit, &amp; literas ſuas ei direxit, &amp; ubi literae illae ſunt, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit quod Walterus de Langton eum per literas ſuas inde rogavit, ſed dicit quod literae illae ſunt in partibus ſuis Leic. Et ſuper hoc idem Vicecomes profert bre. Dom. Regis de privato ſigillo eidem vic. direct. quod teſtatnr quod Dominus Rex eidem Vic. precipit, quod omnes illos tranſ. contra pacem, &amp; de quibus Comes Warwici ei Scire fecit, caperet, &amp; Salvo Cuſtodiret abſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> aliqua gracia eis facienda. Et quia pred. Juſticiar' expreſſe recordata, quod ipſe &amp; ſocij ſui per bonum &amp; legalem inquiſitionem de militibus &amp; aliis communibus coram eis fact. invenerunt quod pred. W. de Petling dimiſſus fuit per pleviam per magnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tempus ante adventum eorun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem Juſtic. uſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> adventu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eorundem &amp; per vic. pred. Et etiam quia pred. vic. cognoſcit quod pred. R. dimiſſus fuit per pleviam per ipſum vic. &amp; hoc dic. quod bene facere potuit, eo quod captus fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it pro levi tranſgreſsion. &amp; per record. ejuſdem Iuſticiar. compert. est quod captus fuit pro morte hominis quod eſt contrar. dict. pred. vicecom. &amp; ſimiliter quod idem Vicecom. cognovit, quod rece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit literam Dom. Regis por quam Rex ei precepit, quod nullam gratiam fecerit illis qui capt. fuer. per precept. pred. Com. &amp; idem vicecomes contra preceptum illud dimiſit pred. Willielmum filium Walteri per pleviam qui captus fuit per pretextum pred. Comitis pro ut idem Vicecomes fatetur. Et ſic tam ratione ipſius tranſgr. quam aliorum pred. incidit in pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>am Stat. Conceſt. quod pred. Vicecomes comittatur priſonae juxta formam Statuti, &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div xml:lang="fre" type="record">
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:54884:14"/>
                     <head>Ex Rot. Parliamenti de Anno 36. Regis Ed. 3. Numero 9.</head>
                     <p>Primerment &amp; la grand Chartre, &amp; le Chartre de Forreſt, &amp; les autres Statuts fait en ſon temps de ſes Progenitores per profits de luy, &amp; de la Commenalty ſoient bien &amp; ferment garder, &amp; miſe en due execution ſauns disturbance mettre ou arreſt faire le contre per ſpecial mandement, ou en autre manere. <note place="margin">Le <abbr>Rns</abbr>.</note> Noſtre Seig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior le Roy per aſſent Prelates, Dukes, Comites, Barons, &amp; la Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menaltie ad ordeine &amp; eſtabliſh <expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> les dits Chartres &amp; Statuts ſoient tenus &amp; miſe en execution ſo lon le dit Petition.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div xml:lang="fre" type="record">
                     <head>Numero 12.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Sta.</hi> 36. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>num.</hi> 22.</note> 
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Petition.</hi>
                        </note> Item, comme il ſoit conteine en le grand Chartre &amp; autre Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tut <expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> nul home ſerra priſe ne impriſon per ſpecial mandement ſauns Indictment, ou autre Proces a faire per le ley &amp; ſovent foits ad eſtre, &amp; uncore eſt <expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> pleſures gents ſont emperches priſe, &amp; impriſon ſauns indictement ou autre Proces fait per le ley ſur eux, cibien del choſe fait hors de le forreſt Dom. Regis cum per autre Cauſe <expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> pleaſe avaut dit par le command. &amp; deliv. ceux <expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ſont auxi priſe per tiel ſpecial mandement contre le forme de Chartres &amp; Statuts avaut dits.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Le <abbr>Rns</abbr>.</note> Item, pleſt ou Roy &amp; ſi nul de ſent greine veigne, &amp; fait le plaurt &amp; droit ſerra fait a luy.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div xml:lang="fre" type="record">
                     <head>Parliament. Anno 42. Ed. 3. Numero 12.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Sta.</hi> 42. <hi>Ed</hi> 3. <hi>numero</hi> 12.</note> 
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Peticion.</hi>
                        </note> Item, pur ceo <expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> pluſors de voſtre common ſont diſworts pur faux accuſance queux ſont lour accuſants plus pur lour vengen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces &amp; ſingles profits <expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> pur le profit del Roy ou de ſon people, &amp; la accuſoits pur eux aſcuns ou en priſon, &amp; aſcuns fait venire de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant le conſual le Roy per brief ex autre mandement de Roy al greife Relme du contre government de ſon people ordeine <expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ſi de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lores purpoſe aſcun mattre pur profit del Roy <expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> cil matire ſoit mando a les Iuſtices del un Banckes, ou del autre, ou del Aſſizes deut inquire ou terminere ſolon la ley. Et ſi touch la accuſer ou parte dit ſont ſcient al Common ley, &amp; nul home ſoit miſe a reſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere ſans preſentment devant Iuſtices en choſe de records, &amp; per due Proces &amp; breif original ſolon la auncient ley de la tere &amp; ſi rien de ſore avaunt. ou ſoit fait e' le contre ſoit void en ley &amp;
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:54884:14"/> deeme pur error. <note place="margin">Le <abbr>Rns</abbr>.</note> Pur ceo <expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ceſt Article eſt Article de le grand Chartre le Roy voit ceo ley ſoit fait en la Petition de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div xml:lang="lat" type="record">
                     <head>Ex Rot. clauſ. de Anno Regni Regis Ed. 1. primo numero, Membrano 10.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Anno</hi> 1. <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. <hi>Pro tranſgr. Forr.</hi>
                        </note> Thomas de Clere de Beckwith, captus &amp; detent. in priſona de Northamton pro tranſgreſſione forreſt. habet literas Rogero de Clifford Iuſticiar' citra Trent quod ponatur per Bali' Dat. apud Sanct. Martin. Magn. London 20. die Octobr.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="record">
                     <head>Membrano 7.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pro tranſgr. Forreſt.</hi>
                        </note> Stephanus de Lindſey capt. &amp; detent. in priſona pro tranſgreſ. per ipſum fact. in Forreſt. Regis de Lindley habet literas Regis Galfrido de Nevill Iuſticiar. ultra Trent. quod ponatur per ballium.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div xml:lang="lat" type="record">
                     <head>Membrano 8.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pro morte ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis.</hi>
                        </note> Tho. Spademan capt. &amp; detent. in priſona de Oxon. pro morte Willielmi Winne unde rectat. eſt habet literas Regis Vicec. Oxon. quod ponatur per ball'.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div xml:lang="lat" type="record">
                     <head>Membr. 9.</head>
                     <p>Willielmus de Deane, Matheus Cruſt, Roger de Bedell, W. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>alfefrench, Robertus Wyat, Alexander Harcing, Harry de Shorne, Nicolas de Sindilonde, Turgeſius de Hertfield, Robertus de Pole, &amp; Richardus Galias, capti &amp; dent in priſona de Cant. pro morte Galfridi de Cottiller unde appellati ſunt habent literas Regis Vic' Kan. quod ponantur per Ball' Dat. 23. Martij.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div xml:lang="lat" type="record">
                     <head>Clauſ. Anno 2. Ed. 1. Membr. 12.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Anno</hi> 2. <hi>Ed.</hi> 1.</note> 
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pro tranſgr. Forreſt.</hi>
                        </note> Rex Roger de Clifford, Iuſticiar. Forreſt. citra Trent manda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus nobis quod ſi Robertus <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nwin, Capt. &amp; detent. in priſona noſtra de Aylesbury pro tranſgr. Forreſt. noſtri invenerit nobis 12. probos &amp; legales homines de Ball. vera qui manucapiant cum habere corum Iuſticiar. noſtr. ad placita Forreſt. cum in partes, &amp;c. ad Stand. inde rectat. hunc ipſum Robertum ſi ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam Aſſiſam Forreſt. fuer. repleg per dictos disodecim interim tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditur in Ball ſicut praed. eſt &amp; habeatis nomina illornm 12. homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num. Et hoc bre. &amp;c. Dat. 27. Februar.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div xml:lang="lat" type="record">
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:54884:15"/>
                     <head>Clauſ. Anno 12. Ed. 1. nu. 14.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>De ponend. in Ball'.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pro tranſgr. Forr.</hi>
                        </note> Winimus de Brirot, Galfridus de Wickeram, &amp; Hugo de Stone, detent. in priſona Regis de Ailesbury pro tranſgr. venationis ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buit bre. direct. Rogero de Clifford Iuſticiar. Forreſt. quod ſi ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum Aſſiſſ. Foriſtacerunt repleg. uſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> advent. Iuſticiar. Regis ad plita Forrest. cum in partes illas venerunt. dat. apud Coddington 28. die Decembr.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div xml:lang="lat" type="record">
                     <head>Nu. 15.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pro morte ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis.</hi>
                        </note> Guilbert Courvey de Keddington, &amp; Hugo le Taylor de Ked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dington Capt. &amp; detent. in priſon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> ſancti Edmundi pro morte Bunting unde rectati ſunt habuerint literas Regis Vic' Suff. quod ponantur per Ball'.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div xml:lang="lat" type="record">
                     <head>Clauſ. Anno 3. Ed. 1. num 11.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Anno</hi> 3. <hi>Ed.</hi> 1.</note> 
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pro morte ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis.</hi>
                        </note> Galfridus de Hairton captus &amp; detentus in priſona Regis Ebor' pro morte Adel' Clerke unde rectatus eſt habet literas Regis vic' Ebor. quod ponatur per Ball' Dat apud Weſtminſt. 14. Junij.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div xml:lang="lat" type="record">
                     <head>Num. 20.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pro morte ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis.</hi>
                        </note> Robertus Belbarbe captus et detentus in priſona de Newgate pro morte Thomae Pollard unde rectatus eſt habet literas Regis Vic. Midd. quod ponatur per Ball' Dat. 28. Februar.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div xml:lang="lat" type="record">
                     <head>Clauſ. nu. 4. Ed. 1. Membr. 5.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pro tranſgr. Forreſt.</hi>
                        </note> Mandatum eſt Rado de Sandwico quod ſi W. de Pattare, &amp; Iohannes filius ejus, Walterus Home, Walterus Corwen, Henricus Path, &amp; W. Cadegan, capt. &amp; detent. in priſona Regis de Sct. Brionell pro tranſgr. Forr. unde rectati ſunt invenerint ſibi 12. probos &amp; legales homines de Ballia ſua, vizt. quilibet eorum 12. qui eos manuc ap' habere coram Iuſticiar. Regis ad plita Forreſt. cum in partes illas venerint ad ſtand. inde rectat. tunc ipſos Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lielm. Iohannem, Walterum, Walterum, Henricum, &amp; Willielm. pred. 12. ſi ſecundum Aſsiſſ. fuer. repleg. tradantur in Ball' ut pred. eſt ſi habent ibi nomina illorum 12. hominum &amp; hoc bre. Teſt. Rege apud Bell' locum Regis 29. die Auguſti.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div xml:lang="lat" type="record">
                     <head>Clauſ. Anno 4. Ed. 1. membr. 16.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pro morte ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis.</hi>
                        </note> Henricus filius Rogeri de Kemi &amp; Cottesbrooke capt. &amp; detent.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:54884:15"/> in priſona noſtra Northampton promorte Symonis de Charrettell unde appellatus eſt habet literas Regis <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ic' Northampton quod ponatur per ballium.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div xml:lang="lat" type="record">
                     <head>Clauſ. Anno 5. Ed. 1. membr. 1.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pro tranſgr. Forreſt.</hi>
                        </note> Mandatnm eſt Galfrid. de Nevil Iuſticiar. Forreſt. ultr. Trent. quod S. Walterus de le Greene Captus &amp; detentus in priſona de Nottingham pro tranſgr. For' invenerit ſibi 12. probos &amp; legales homines qui eum manucapiant, &amp;c. ad ſtand' inde rectat. ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum aſſiſſ. Forr' Regis tunc ibidem Walter. pred. 12. traditur in Ballium ſicut praed. eſt. Dat. 16. Novemb.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div xml:lang="lat" type="record">
                     <head>Membrano 2.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pro morte ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis.</hi>
                        </note> Thomas de <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pwell, &amp; Iuliana uxor ejus Capt. &amp; detent. in priſona de Wynboteſham pro morte Stephani Southet unde re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctat. ſunt habent literas Vic' Norff. quod ponantur per Ballium. Dat. apud Rothelm 28. die Septembr.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div xml:lang="lat" type="record">
                     <head>Clauſ. Anno 6. Ed. 1 nu. 2.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pro morte uxor.</hi>
                        </note> Bitherus Pestle captus &amp; detentus fuit in priſona Rs de Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wici pro morte Iulianae quondam uxor' ſuae unde rectatus eſt &amp; habet literas Vic' Norff. quod ponatur per Ball' Teſte Rege apud Weſtminſt. 12. Novemb.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div xml:lang="lat" type="record">
                     <head>Membr. 4.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pro tranſg. Forr.</hi>
                        </note> Mandatum eſt Vic' Nottingham quod ſi Tho. de Cudart rectat. de tranſgr. Forreſt. quod feciſſe dicebatur in Forreſt. de Sherwood invenerit ſibi ſex probos &amp; legales homines de Ballia ſua qui eum Manucap' habere coram rege ad mandatum regis ad Stand. rect. coram rege cum Rex inde cum eo loqui voluerit tunc praed. Tho. praed. 6. hominibus trad. in Ball' juxta manucapt. praed. Dat. 12. die Decembr.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div xml:lang="lat" type="record">
                     <head>Membr. 4.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pro morte homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis.</hi>
                        </note> Tho. Burrell captus &amp; detent. in priſona Regis Oxon. pro morte Galfrid. Geffard unde rectat. est habet literas Dom. Regis Vic' Devon. quod ponatur per Ball'.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div xml:lang="lat" type="record">
                     <head>Clauſ. Anno 1. Ed. 2. Membr. 1.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pro morte ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis.</hi>
                        </note> Iohannes Brynn de Rollin Writh capt. &amp; detent. in priſona
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:54884:16"/> Regis Oxon. pro morte Johannis de Sutton unde rectat. eſt habet li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teras Regis Vic. Oxon. quod ponatur per Ball. uſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> prim. Aſsiſſ. ſi ea occaſione, &amp;c. Teſte Rege apud Briſtoll 28. Iunij.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div xml:lang="lat" type="record">
                     <head>Membr. 2.</head>
                     <p>W. Spore Capell. capt. &amp; detent. in priſona Regis Oxon. pro morte Johannis Spore unde Jndictatus eſt, &amp; habet literas Regis Vic D'evon. quod ponatur per Ballium uſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ad prox. Aſſiſ. ſi ea occaſione, &amp;c. Teſte rege apud Windſor 28. die Maij.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div xml:lang="lat" type="record">
                     <head>Numero 10.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pro morte homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis.</hi>
                        </note> Guilbertus Fairchild capt. &amp; dotent. in Gaole Regis Dorce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter pro morte Heneri de Langton unde indictat. eſt habet literas quod ponatur per Ballium uſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ad prim' aſſiſſ. Teſte Rege apua Westminſt. 28. Februar'.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div xml:lang="lat" type="record">
                     <head>Clauſ. Anno 2. Ed. 2. Membr. 1.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pro morte ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis.</hi>
                        </note> Willielmus Sandie de Cobham Capt. &amp; detent. in priſona Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis Cant. pro morte Iohannis de Sprink, Iohannis Ermond de Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berke unde rectatus eſt habet literas Regis Vic' Kanc' quod pona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur per Ball' uſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ad primam Aſſiſſ. Si ea occaſione, &amp;c. Teſte rege apud Ceſtre. 29. Iunij.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pro morte ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis.</hi>
                        </note> Radu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s Corynn capt. &amp; detentus in Gaole Regis de Lincolne pro morte Willielmi Filij Symonis Porter unde rectat. eſt &amp; habet li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teras Regis Vic' Lincolne quod ponatur per Ball' uſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ad primum Aſſiſſ. Si ea occaſione, &amp;c. Teſte rege apud Sheene 3. die Iunij.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div xml:lang="lat" type="record">
                     <head>Membrana 7.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pro morte ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis.</hi>
                        </note> Iohannes de Githerd Capt' &amp; detent. in priſona Regis Ebor' pro morte Mathei Sampſon de Ebor' unde rectatus est habet lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras Regis Vic' Ebor' quod ponatur per Ball' uſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ad prim' Aſſiſſ. Dat. apud Langele 50. die Aprilis.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div xml:lang="lat" type="record">
                     <head>Clauſ. 3. Ed. 2. Membr. 3.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pro morte ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis.</hi>
                        </note> Adam de Pepper captus &amp; detent. in Gaole Regis Ebor' pro morte Henrici de Syner' de Eaſtrick unde rectatus eſt habet literas Regis Vic' Ebor' quod ponat' per Ball' uſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ad primum Aſſiſſ. Teſte rege apud Weſtminſt. 7. die Febr.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div xml:lang="lat" type="record">
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:54884:16"/>
                     <head>Numero 14.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pro morte</hi> 2. <hi>femes.</hi>
                        </note> Margareta uxor Willielmi Colbot capta &amp; detenta in Gaol Regis Norwici pro morte Agnetis filiae Willielmi Colbot, &amp; Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tildae ſororis ejuſdem Agnetis unde rectata eſt habet literas Regis Vic' Norff. quod ponatur per Ball' Teſte rege apud Sheene 22. Ianuar.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div xml:lang="lat" type="record">
                     <head>Numero 16.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pro morte ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis.</hi>
                        </note> Iohannes Frere Captus &amp; detent. in Gaole Regis Oxon. pro morte Adae de Egeleigh unde rectata eſt habet literas Regis Vic' Devon. quod ponatur per Ball' Teſte rege apud Weſtminſt. 8. Decembr.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div xml:lang="lat" type="record">
                     <head>Clauſ. Anno 4. Ed. 2. Membr. 7.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pro morte hom.</hi>
                        </note> Robertus Shrene Capt. &amp; detent. in Gaole Regis de Colcheſter pro morte Roberti le Maigme unde rectat. eſt habet literas Regis Vic' Eſſex quod ponatur per Ball' uſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ad prim' Aſſiſſ. Dat. 22. die Maij.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div xml:lang="lat" type="record">
                     <head>Numero 8.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pro morte hom.</hi>
                        </note> W. Filius Robertile Fiſhere de Shirborne capt. &amp; detent. in Gaole Regis Ebor' pro morte Roberti le Monus de Norton unde rectatus est habet literas Regis Vic. Ebor. quod ponatur per Ball. uſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ad primam Aſſiſſ. Dat. 25. April.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div xml:lang="lat" type="record">
                     <head>Clauſ. Anno 4. Ed. 2. Numero. 22.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pro morte hom.</hi>
                        </note> Thomas Ellis de Stanford capt. &amp; detent. in priſona Regis Lincolne pro morte Michaelis filii Willielmi de Fodering unde rectat. eſt habet literas Regis Vic. Lincolne quod ponatur per Ball' uſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ad prim. Aſſiſſ. Teſte Rege apud novum monaſterium 8. die Septembr.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="Selden" type="part">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:54884:17"/>
               <head>Mr. <hi>Seldens</hi> Argument.</head>
               <head>The Argument which by the Command of the Houſe of Commons was made at their firſt conference with the Lords, touching the perſonall libertie of the perſon of every Free-man, out of Preſidents of Record, and reſolutions of Judges in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times.</head>
               <div type="argument">
                  <opener>
                     <salute>MY LORDS,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Our Lordſhips have heard from the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that laſt ſpake a great part of the grounds upon which the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons upon mature deliberation proceeded to that cleere reſolution touching the right of the libertie of their perſons. The many Acts of Parliament, which are the written lawes of the Land, and are expreſly in the point, have beene read and opened, and ſuch Objections as have beene by ſome made to them, and ſome Objections alſo made out of another Act of Parliament, have beene cleered and anſwered. It may ſeeme now perhaps (my Lords) that little remaines needfull to bee further added, for the inforcement and maintenance of ſo fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentall and eſtabliſhed a right and libertie belonging to every Free-man of the Kingdome. But in the examination of queſtions of Law of right, beſides the Lawes or Acts of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, that ought chiefly to direct and regulate every mans judgement, whatſoever hath beene put in practiſe to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, there are commonly uſed alſo former Judgements or Preſidents, and indeed have beene ſo uſed ſometimes, that the weight of reaſon, of law, and of Acts of Parliament, hath been laid by, and reſolutions have beene made, and that in this very point, only upon the interpretation and apprehenſion of Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents.
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:54884:17"/> Preſidents my Lords are good <hi>media</hi> or proofes of illuſtration or confirmation where they agree with the expreſſe Law, but they can never bee proofe enough to overthrow any one law much leſſe ſeven ſeverall Acts of Parliament as the number of them is for the point. The houſe of Commons therefore taking into conſideration that in this queſtion being of ſo high a nature that never any exceeding it in any Court of Juſtice whatſoever all the ſeverall wayes of juſt examination of the truth ſhould be uſed, have alſo moſt carefully informed themſelves of all for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer judgements or preſidents concerning this great point ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way, and have beene no leſſe carefull of the due preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Majeſties juſt prerogative then of their owne rights. The Preſidents here are of two kinds, either meerely matter of record, or elſe the former reſolutions of the Judges after ſolemne debate in the point.</p>
                  <p>This point that concernes preſidents the Houſe of Commons have commanded me to preſent to your Lordſhips, which I ſhall as briefly as I may, ſo I doe it faithfully and perſpicuouſly. To that end my Lords, before I come to the particulars of any of thoſe Preſidents, I ſhall firſt remember to your Lordſhips, that which will ſeeme as a generall key for the opening and true apprehenſion of all them of Record, without which key no man unleſſe he be verſt in the entries and courſe of the Kings Bench can poſſibly underſtand them.</p>
                  <p>In all caſes my Lords where any right or libertie belongs to the Subjects by any poſitive law written or unwritten, if there were not alſo a remedie by Law for the enjoying or regaining this right or libertie when it is violated or taken from him, the poſitive law were moſt vaine and to no purpoſe, and it were to no purpoſe, for any man to have any right in any land or other inheritance, if there were not a knowne remedie, that is an action or writ, by which in ſome Court of ordinary Juſtice he might recover it. And in this caſe of right of libertie of perſon, if there were not a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie in the Law for regaining it when it is reſtrained, it were of no purpoſe to ſpeak of lawes that ordain it ſhould not be reſtrained. Therefore in this caſe alſo I ſhall firſt ſhew you
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:54884:18"/> the remedie that every Free-man is to uſe for the regaining of his libertie when he is againſt law impriſoned, that ſo upon the legall courſe and forme to be held in uſing that remedie, the Preſidents or Judgements upon it, for all Judgements of Record riſe out of this remedie, may bee eaſily underſtood. There are in law divers remedies for inlarging of a Free-man impriſoned, as the writts of <hi>Odio &amp; Atia,</hi> and of <hi>Homine re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plegiando,</hi> beſides the common or moſt knowne Writs of <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beas Corpus,</hi> or <hi>Corpus cum cauſa,</hi> as it is called alſo.</p>
                  <p>The firſt two Writs are to be directed to the Sherifs of the County, and lie in ſome particular Caſes, with which it would be untimely for me to trouble your Lordſhips, becauſe they concerne not that which is committed to my charge. But that Writ of <hi>Habeas Corpus,</hi> or <hi>Corpus cum cauſa,</hi> is the higheſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie in Law for any man that is impriſoned, and the only remedie for him that is impriſoned by the ſpeciall command of the King, or the Lords of the Privie Counſell, without ſhewing cauſe of the commitment, neither is there in the law any ſuch thing, nor was there ever mention of any ſuch thing in the Lawes of this Land, as a Petition of right to be uſed in ſuch caſes for libertie of the perſon, nor is there any legall courſe for inlargement to be taken in ſuch caſes, howſoever the contrary hath upon no ground or colour of law beene preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. Now my Lords, if any man be ſo impriſoned by any ſuch command, or other wiſe, in any priſon whatſoever through <hi>England,</hi> and deſire by himſelfe, or any other in his behalfe, this Writ of <hi>Habeas Corpus</hi> for the purpoſe in the Court of the Kings Bench, the Writ is to be granted to him, and ought not to be denied him, no otherwiſe then another ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry originall Writ in the Chancery, or other common Proces of law may be denied, which amongſt other things the Houſe reſolved alſo, upon mature deliberation, and I was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to let your Lord ſh. know ſo much. This Writ is dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to the Keeper of the Priſon in whoſe cuſtodie the priſoner remaines, commanding him that after a certaine day he bring in the body of the priſoner, <hi>ad Subiiciend. &amp; recipiend. juxta quod curia conceda verit, &amp;c. una cum cauſa Captionis, &amp; detentionis,</hi> and oftentimes <hi>una cum cauſa detentionis</hi> only, <hi>captionis</hi> being omitted.</p>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:54884:18"/>
                  <p>The Keeper of the priſon therupon returns by what warrant he detaines the priſoner, and with his returne filed to his Writ, brings the priſoner to the Barre at the time appointed; When the returne is thus made, the Court judgeth of the ſufficiency or inſufficiency of it, only out of the body of it, without having reſpect to any other thing whatſoever; that is they to ſuppoſe the returne to be true whatſoever it be, if it bee falſe, the priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner may have his action on the Caſe againſt the Gaoler that brought him. Now my Lords, when the priſoner comes thus to the Barre, if he deſire to be bayled, and that the Court upon the view of the returne thinke him in Law to bee bayleable, then he is alwayes firſt taken from the keeper of the Priſon that brings him, and committed to the Marſhall of the Kings Bench, and afterwards bayled, and the entry perpetually is <hi>Committi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur Mariſcallo &amp; poſtea traditur in Ball',</hi> for the Court never bayles any man, untill he firſt become their owne priſoner, and be in <hi>Cuſtodia Marriſcall'</hi> of that Court. But if upon the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn of the <hi>Habeas Corpus</hi> it appeare to the Court, that the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner ought not to be bayled, nor diſcharged from the priſon whence he is brought, then he is remanded or ſent back againe there to continue, untill by courſe of law he may be delivered, and the entrie in this Caſe is <hi>Remittitur quouſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ſecundum le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem deliberatus fuerit,</hi> or <hi>Remittitur quouſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan>, &amp;c.</hi> which is all one, and the higheſt award or judgement that ever was or can be given upon a <hi>Habeas Corpus.</hi> But if the Judges doubt only whether in Law they ought to take him from the priſon whence he came, or give a day to the Sherife to amend his Writ, as often they doe, then they remaund him only, during the time of their doubte, or untill the Sherife hath amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his returne, and the Entrie upon that is <hi>Remittitur</hi> only, or <hi>Remittitur priſonae praed,</hi> without any more. And ſo <hi>remittitur</hi> generally is of farre leſſe moment in the award upon the <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beas Corpus,</hi> then <hi>remittitur quouſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan>, &amp;c.</hi> howſoever the vulgar opinions raiſed out of the late Judgement be to the contrary. All theſe things are of moſt knowne and conſtant uſe in the Court of Kings Bench, as it cannot be doubted but your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips will eaſily know from the grave and learned my Lords the Judges.</p>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:54884:19"/>
                  <p>Theſe two courſes, the one of the entrie of <hi>Committitus Mareſcall. &amp; poſtea traditur in Ballium,</hi> and the other <hi>remit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titur quouſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan>, &amp;c. &amp; Remittitur</hi> generally, or <hi>Remittitur priſonae pred,</hi> together with the nature of the <hi>Habeas corpus,</hi> thus ſtated, it will bee eaſier for me to open, and your Lordſhips to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, whatſoever ſhall occurre to the purpoſe in the Preſidents of record, to which I ſhall come now in the particular. But before I am come to the Preſidents, I am to let you know the reſolutions of the houſe of Commons touching the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largement of a man committed by the command of the King, or the Privie Counſell, or any other, without cauſe ſhewed of ſuch commitment, it is thus; That if a Freeman be commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted or detained in priſon or otherwiſe reſtrained by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the King, the Privie Counſell, or any other, and no cauſe of ſuch commitment, deteiner, or reſtraint, to be expreſſed for which by law he ought to be committed, detained, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained, and the ſame be returned upon a <hi>Habeas Corpus</hi> gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for the party, then he ought to be delivered and bayled.</p>
                  <p>This reſolution as it is grounded upon the Acts of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment already ſhewen, and the reaſon of the law of the Land, which is committed to the charge of another, and anon alſo to be opened to you, is ſtrengthened alſo by many Preſidents of Record.</p>
                  <p>But the Preſidents of Record that concerne this point are of two kinds, for the Houſe of Commons hath informed it ſelfe of ſuch as concerne it either way. The firſt ſuch as ſhew expreſly that perſons committed by the command of the King or of the Privie Counſell without other cauſe ſhewed have beene inlarged upon bayle when they prayed it, whence it appeareth cleerely, that by the law they are bayleable, and ſo by <hi>Habeas Corpus</hi> to bee ſet at libertie, for though they ought not to have beene committed without a cauſe ſhewed of the commitment, yet it is true that the reverend Judges of this Land did ſuch reſpect to ſuch commitments by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the King or of the Lords of the Counſell (as alſo to the commitment ſometimes of inferiour perſons) that upon the <hi>Habeas Corpus,</hi> they rarely uſed abſolutely to diſcharge the perſons inſtantly, but only to enlarge them upon Bayle, which
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:54884:19"/> ſufficiently ſecures and preſerves the liberty of the Subject ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the lawes that your Lordſhips have already heard, nor in any of the caſes is there any difference made betweene ſuch co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitments by the Lords of the Counſel, that are incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated with him. The ſecond kind of Preſidents of Record are ſuch as have beene pretended to prove the law to bee contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and that perſons ſo committed ought not to be ſet at liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie upon bayle, and are in the nature of Objections out of Record.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall deliver them ſummarily to your Lordſhips with all faith, and alſo true Copies of them, out of which it ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare cleerely to your Lordſhips, that of thoſe of the firſt kind there are no leſſe then 12. moſt full and directly in the point to prove that perſons ſo committed are to be delivered upon bayle, and amongſt thoſe of the other kind, there is not ſo much as one, not one, that proves at all any thing to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary; I ſhall firſt my Lords goe through them of the firſt kind, and ſo obſerve them to your Lordſhips, that ſuch ſcruples as have beene made upon them by ſome that have excepted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them ſhall bee cleered alſo, according as I ſhall open them ſeverally.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Paſc.</hi> 18. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>Bildeſtons Caſe.</hi>
                     </note> The firſt of the firſt kind is of <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. time, it is in <hi>Paſche</hi> 18. <hi>Ed</hi> 3. <hi>Rot.</hi> 33. The Caſe was thus;</p>
                  <p>King <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. had committed by Writ, and that under his great Seale (as moſt of the Kings commands in thoſe times were) one <hi>Iohn de Bildeſton</hi> a Clergie man to the priſon to the Tower without any cauſe ſhewed of the commitment. The Lievtenant of the Tower is commanded to bring him to the Kings Bench, where he is commited to the Marſhall, but the Court askes of the Lievtenant, if there were any cauſe to keep this <hi>Bildeſton</hi> in priſon, beſides that commitment of the King, he anſwered no, whereupon the Roll ſayes, <hi>Quia videtur cur bre. praed. ſufficient. non eſſe cauſam praed. Iohan, de Bildeſton in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſona Dom Regis hic detinend' idem Iohannes admittitur per ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nucaptionem Willielmi de Wakefield,</hi> and ſome others, where the Judgement of the point is fully declared in the very point.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">22. H. 8. <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers Caſe.</hi>
                     </note> The ſecond in the firſt kind of Preſidents of Record is in the time of <hi>H.</hi> 8. one <hi>Iohn Parkers</hi> Caſe, who was committed to
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:54884:20"/> the Sherife of <hi>London, pro ſecuritate pacis,</hi> at the ſuite of one <hi>Brinton, ac pro ſuſpitione feloniae</hi> committed by him in Gloceſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire, <hi>ac per mandatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Dom. Rs.</hi> he is committed to the Marſhall of the Kings Bench, <hi>&amp; poſtea iſto eodem termino traditur in Ball'</hi> here were other cauſes of the commitment, but plainly one was by the command of the King, ſignified to the Sherife of <hi>London,</hi> of which they tooke notice, but ſome have interpreted this, as if the commitment had beene for ſuſpition of felonie by the command of the King, in which caſe it is agreeable of all hands, that the Priſoner is bayleable, but no man can thinke ſo of this preſident that obſerves the context and underſtands the Grammar of it, wherein moſt plainly <hi>ac per mandatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Dom. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis</hi> hath no reference to any other cauſe whatſoever, but is as a ſingle Cauſe enumerated in the returne by it ſelfe, as the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord cleerely ſheweth, it is in 22. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>Rot.</hi> 37.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">35. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>Bincks</hi> Caſe.</note> The third is of the ſame Kings time, it is 35. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>Rot.</hi> 33. <hi>Iohn Bincks</hi> Caſe, he was committed by the Lords of the Counſell <hi>pro ſuſpitioniae feloniae ac pro aliis cauſis illos moventibus qui com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittitur Mariſcallo &amp; immediate ex gratia curiae ſpeciali tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur in Ball'</hi> They committed him for ſuſpition of felonie and other cauſes them thereunto moving, wherein there might be matter of State, or whatſoever elſe can be ſuppoſed, and plainly the cauſe of their commitment is not expreſſed, yet the Court bayled him without having regard to theſe unknowne cauſes that moved the Lords of the Counſell. But it is indeed ſome difference from either of thoſe other 2. that precede, and from the other 9. alſo that follow, for it is agreed, that if a cauſe be expreſſed in the returne, inſomuch that the Court can know why he is committed, that then he may be bayled, but not if they know not the cauſe, now a man is committed for a cauſe expreſſed, <hi>&amp; pro aliis cauſis Dominos de Conſilio moventibus,</hi> certainly the Court can no more know in ſuch a caſe what the cauſe is, then any other.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3. <hi>P &amp; Mar. Overtons</hi> Caſe.</note> The fourth of theſe is in the time of Queene <hi>Mary,</hi> it is <hi>Paſche</hi> 2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3. <hi>P. &amp; Mar. Rot.</hi> 58. <hi>Overtons</hi> Caſe, <hi>Richard O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verton</hi> was returned upon a <hi>Habeas Corpus,</hi> directed to the She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifes of <hi>London,</hi> to have beene committed to them and detey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>per mandatum pranobilium Dominorum honorabilis conſilij
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:54884:20"/> Dominorum Regis &amp; Reginae, Qui committitur Marr. &amp; immediate traditur in Ball'.</hi> In anſwer to this Preſident, or by way of objection to the force of it, It hath beene ſaid that this <hi>Overton</hi> at this time ſtood indicted of high treaſon. It is true, he was ſo indicted, but that appeares in another Roll, that hath no reference to the returne, as the returne hath no reference to that Roll, yet they that object this againſt the force of this Preſident, ſay that becauſe he was Indicted of Treaſon, therefore though he were committed by the Command of the Lords of the Counſell without cauſe ſhewed, yet he was bayleable for the Treaſon, and upon that was here bayled; Then which obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction nothing is more contrary, either to law or common rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. It is moſt contrary to law, for that cleerely every re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne is to be adjudged by the Court out of the body of it ſelfe, and not by any other collaterall or forraigne Record whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, Therefore the matter of Indictment here, cannot in law be cauſe of bayling of the Priſoner, And ſo it is averſe to all common reaſon, that if the objection be admitted, it muſt of neceſſitie follow, that whoſoever ſhall be committed by the King, or the Privie Counſell, without cauſe ſhewed, and bee not indicted of Treaſon or ſome other offence, may not be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged, for by reaſon of ſuppoſition of matter of State, But that whoſoever is ſo committed, and withall ſtands ſo indicted though in another Record may bee inlarged, whatſoever the matter of State be for which he was committed. The abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie of which aſſertion needs not a word for further confuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as if any of the Gent. in the laſt judgement, ought to have beene the ſooner delivered, if hee had beene alſo Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of Treaſon, if ſo, Traitours and Fellons have the higheſt priviledge in perſonall libertie, and that above all other Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of the Kingdome.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">4. <hi>&amp;</hi> 5. <hi>Phil. &amp; Mar. Newports</hi> Caſe.</note> The fifth of this kind is of Queene <hi>Maries</hi> time alſo, it is <hi>Paſch.</hi> 4. <hi>&amp;</hi> 5. <hi>P. &amp; Mar. Rot.</hi> 45. the Caſe of <hi>Edward Newport,</hi> hee was brought into the Kings Bench by <hi>Habeas Corpus</hi> out of the Tower of <hi>London, Cum cauſa, vizt. Quod Commiſſus fuit per mandatum Concilii Dominae Reginae qui committitur Marr. &amp; immediate traditur in Ballium.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:54884:21"/>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Vn objection <abbr>Rnde</abbr>.</note> To this the like anſwer hath beene made, as to that other Caſe of <hi>Overtons</hi> next before cited, they ſay that in another roll of another terme of the ſame yeare, it appeares he was in queſtion for ſuſpition of Coyning, and it is true he was ſo, But the returne and his Commitment mentioned in it have no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to any ſuch offence, nor hath the Baylement of him relation to any thing but to the abſolute commitment by the privie Counſell: So that the anſwer to the like objection made againſt <hi>Overtons</hi> Caſe ſatisfies this alſo.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">9 <hi>El. Lawrences</hi> Caſe.</note> The ſixth of theſe is of Queene <hi>Elizabeths</hi> time, <hi>Mich.</hi> 9. <hi>El. Rot.</hi> 35: the caſe of <hi>Tho. Lawrence;</hi> this <hi>Lawrence</hi> came in by <hi>Habeas Corpus,</hi> returned by the Sheriffs of London to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in priſon <hi>per mandat. Conſilij Dominae Regina qui Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittitue Marr. &amp; ſuper hoc traditur in Ballium.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Objection <abbr>Rend</abbr>.</note> An objection hath beene invented againſt this alſo, it hath beene ſaid that this man was pardoned, and indeed it appeares ſo in the Margin of the roll, where the word <hi>pardonatur</hi> is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, but clearely his in largement by Bayle was upon the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the returne onely, unto which that note of pardon in the Margin of the roll hath no relation at all, and can any man think, that a man pardoned (for what offence ſoever it be) might not as well be committed for ſome <hi>Arcanum,</hi> or matter of State, as one that is not pardoned, or out of his innocencie wants no pardon?</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">9 <hi>El. Constables</hi> Caſe.</note> The ſeaventh of theſe is in the ſame yeare, and of Eaſter Terme following, it is <hi>P.</hi> 9. <hi>El. Rot.</hi> 68 <hi>Ro. Constables</hi> Caſe, he was brought by <hi>Habeas Corpus</hi> out of the Tower, and in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne it appeared he was committed there, <hi>per mandatum pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vati Conſiliidictae Dominae Reginae qui Comittitur Marr. &amp; poſteae iſto eodem ter. traditur in Ball.</hi> The like objection hath beene made to this, as that before of <hi>Lawrence,</hi> but the ſelfe ſame an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer clearely ſatisfies for them both.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">20 <hi>El. Brow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings</hi> Caſe.</note> The 8. is of the ſame Queenes time in <hi>Paſ.</hi> 20 <hi>El Rot.</hi> 72. <hi>Iohn Brownings</hi> Caſe. This <hi>Browning</hi> came by <hi>Habeas Corpus</hi> out of the Tower, whether he had beene committed, and was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to have been committed, <hi>per privat. Conſil. Dominae Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginae qui comittitur Marr. &amp; poſtea iſto codem termino traditur in Ball.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Objection <abbr>Rnde</abbr>.</note> To this it hath beene ſaid, that it was done at the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:54884:21"/> chiefe Juſtice <hi>Wrayes</hi> Chamber, and not in the Court: and thus the authority of the Preſident hath beene leſned or ſleighted. If it had beene done at his Chamber, it would have proved at leaſt this much, that Sir <hi>Chriſtopher Wray</hi> then chiefe Juſtice of the Kings Bench, being a grave learned and upright Judge, knowing the Law to be ſo, did Bayle this <hi>Browning,</hi> and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large him, and even ſo farre the Preſident were of value e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough; but it is plaine, that though the <hi>habeas corpus</hi> were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnable, as indeed it appeares in the Record it ſelf, at his Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber in Serjeants Inn; yet he only committed him to the Kings Bench preſently, and referred the conſideration of inlarging him to the Court, who afterward did it: For the Record ſayes, <hi>Et poſtea iſto eodem termino traditur in Ball.</hi> which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be of an inlargement at the chiefe Juſtice Chamber.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">40 <hi>El. Hare-Courts</hi> Caſe.</note> The ninth of this firſt kind is <hi>Hill.</hi> 40. <hi>El. Rot.</hi> 62. <hi>Edward Hare Courts</hi> Caſe, hee was impriſoned in the Gatehouſe, and that <hi>per Domines de private Conſilio Dominae Reginae pro certis cauſis eos moventibus &amp; ei ignotis,</hi> And upon his <hi>habeas corpus</hi> was returned to be therefore onely detained, <hi>Qui Comittitur Marr. &amp; poſtea iſto eodem termino traditur in Ball.</hi> To this never any colour of anſwer hath beene yet offered.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">43 <hi>El. Cateſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bies</hi> Caſe.</note> The tenth is <hi>Catesbies</hi> Caſe in the vacation after Hill. Term 43. <hi>El. Rot. Robert. Catesbie</hi> was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted to the Fleet <hi>per war rantum diverſor. pro nobilium viroy de privato Conſilio Domine Regina:</hi> He was brought before Iuſtice <hi>Fenner,</hi> one of the then Iuſtices of the Kings Bench by <hi>Habeas Corpus</hi> at Wincheſter houſe Southwark, <hi>Et homiſſ. fuit Marr. per prefat. Edwardum Fenner &amp; ſtatim traditur in Ball.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">12 <hi>Iac. Beck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withs</hi> Caſe.</note> The eleventh is <hi>Rich Beckwiths</hi> Caſe, which was in Hill. 12 of K. <hi>Iames Rot.</hi> 153. He was returned upon his <hi>Habeas corpus</hi> to have beene committed to the Gatehouſe by divers Lords of the privie Counſel, <hi>Qui committitur Marr. &amp; poſtea eſto eodem termino traditur in Ball.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Objection <abbr>Rnde</abbr>.</note> To this it hath bin ſaid by ſome, that <hi>Beckwith</hi> was bayled upon a letter, written by the Lords of the Counſell to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to the Iudges, but it appeares not that there was ever any letter written to them to that purpoſe, which though it had beene, would have proved nothing againſt the authority of the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:54884:22"/> Record: for it was never heard of that Iudges were to be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected in point of law by letters from the Lords of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, although it cannot bee doubted, but that by ſuch letters, ſometimes they have been moved to bayle men that would or did not ask their inlargement without ſuch letters, as in ſome examples I ſhall ſhew your Lordſhips among the preſidents of the ſecond kind.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">14 <hi>Iac.</hi> Sir <hi>Tho. Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> Caſe.</note> The 12 and laſt of theſe, is that of Sir <hi>Tho. Mounſons</hi> Caſe, it is <hi>Mich.</hi> 14. <hi>Jac. Rot.</hi> 147. Hee was committed to the Tower <hi>per warrantum a diverſis Dominis de privato Conſilio Domini Regis locum tenenti directum,</hi> And he was returned by the Liev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant to be therefore detained in priſon, <hi>qui committitur Marr. &amp; ſuper hoc traditur in Ball.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Objection <abbr>Rnde</abbr>.</note> To this it hath beene anſwered, that every body knowes by common fame, that this Gentleman was committed for ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpition of the death of Sir <hi>Tho. Overbury,</hi> and that hee was therefore bayleable; a moſt ſtrange interpretation, as if the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the return, and the warrant of the privie Counſel, ſhould be underſtood, and adjudged out of fame onely; was there not as much a fame why the Gentlemen that were remanded in the laſt judgement were committed, and might not the ſelfe ſame reaſon have ſerved to enlarge them, their offence (if any were) being I think much leſſe then that for which this Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman was ſuſpected?</p>
                  <p>And thus I have faithfully opened the number of 12 Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents moſt expreſſe in the very point in queſtion, and cleared the objections that have beene made againſt them.</p>
                  <p>And of ſuch preſidents of Record as are of the firſt kinde, which prove plainly the practiſe of former ages, and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Court of Kings Bench, in the very point, on the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe the Subject, my Lords hitherto.</p>
                  <p>I am come next to thoſe of the ſecond kind, or ſuch as are pretended that perſons ſo committed are not to be inlarged by the Iudges upon the <hi>habeas corpus</hi> brought, but to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine in priſon ſtill at the command of the King or the privie Counſell.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Preſidents del 2. ſort. vouch ꝑ le Roy.</note> Theſe are of two natures, the firſt of theſe are where ſome aſſent of the King or the privie Counſell appeares upon the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:54884:22"/> inlargement of a priſoner ſo committed, as if that becauſe ſuch aſſent appeares, the inlargement could not have beene without ſuch aſſent.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond of this kind are thoſe which have beene urged as expreſſe teſtimonies of the Iudges denying bayle, and in ſuch caſes, I ſhall open theſe alſo to your ſhips, which being done, it will moſt clearely appeare, that there is nothing at all in any of theſe that makes any thing at all againſt the reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the houſe of Commons touching this point: nay, it is ſo farre from their making any thing againſt it, that ſome of them add good weight alſo to the proofe of that reſolution.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Temps H.</hi> 7 <hi>Brugs</hi> Caſe.</note> For thoſe of the firſt nature of this ſecond kind of Preſidents, they begun in the time of <hi>H.</hi> 7. <hi>Tho. Brugge,</hi> and divers others were impriſoned in the Kings <hi>ad mandatum Dom. Regis,</hi> they never ſought remedy by <hi>habeas corpus,</hi> or otherwiſe, for ought appeares: But the Roll ſayes, that <hi>Dominus Rex relax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avit mandatum,</hi> and ſo they were bayled. But can any man think that this is an Argument either in Law or common rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that therefore they could not have beene bayled without ſuch aſſent? It is common in Caſes of common perſons, that one being in priſon for ſurety of the peace or the like, at the ſuit of another, is bayled upon the releaſe of the party plaintiffe; Can it follow, that therefore he could not have beene bayled without ſuch releaſe? nothing is more plain then the contrary. It were the ſame thing to ſay, that if it appeare, that if a plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiff be non ſuit, therefore unleſſe he had been non ſuit, he could not have been barred in the ſuit. The Caſe laſt cited is, <hi>Mich.</hi> 7. <hi>H.</hi> 7 <hi>rot.</hi> 6.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">7 <hi>H.</hi> 7. <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholomews</hi> Caſe.</note> The very like is in the ſame yeare, <hi>Hill</hi> 7. <hi>H.</hi> 7. <hi>Rot.</hi> 13. The Caſe of <hi>Will. Bartholomew, Will. Chaſe</hi> and divers others, and the ſelfe ſame anſwer that is given to the other cleares this.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">7 <hi>H.</hi> 7. <hi>Beo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds</hi> Caſe.</note> So in the ſame yeare <hi>Paſ.</hi> 7. <hi>H.</hi> 7 <hi>rot.</hi> 18. <hi>Iohn Beomonds</hi> Caſe is the ſame in ſubſtance with thoſe other two, and the ſelf ſame anſwer alſo ſatisfies that cleares them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">12 <hi>H.</hi> 7. <hi>Yews</hi> Caſe.</note> The next Caſe is, <hi>Mich.</hi> 12. <hi>H.</hi> 7. <hi>rot.</hi> 8. <hi>Tho. Yews</hi> Caſe, hee was committed <hi>ad ſec. pacis,</hi> for the ſecurity of the peace, at the ſuit of one <hi>Freeman,</hi> and beſides, <hi>ad mandatum Dom. Regis,</hi> And firſt, <hi>Freeman relaxavit ſec. pacis,</hi> and then Sir <hi>James
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:54884:23"/> Hubbard,</hi> the then Kings Attomey Generall <hi>relaxavit manda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum Dom Regis,</hi> And hereupon he is bayled, the releaſe of the Kings Attomy, no more proves that he could not have bin inlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, without ſuch releaſe or aſſent, then that he could not have bin bayled, without releaſe of ſurety of the peace by <hi>Freeman.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">9 <hi>H.</hi> 7. <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers</hi> Caſe.</note> The very like is in <hi>Hill.</hi> 9. <hi>H.</hi> 7. <hi>rot.</hi> 14. The Caſe of <hi>Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phry Boch,</hi> which proves no more here then the reſt of this kind already cited.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">39 <hi>Eliza. Broomes</hi> caſe</note> Then for this point alſo <hi>Broomes</hi> Caſe of Queene <hi>Elizabeths</hi> time, is <hi>Trim.</hi> 39. <hi>El. rot.</hi> 128. <hi>Lawrence Broome</hi> was committed to the Gatehouſe <hi>per mandatum Dom. Conſilii Dominae Reginae,</hi> And being returned ſo upon the <hi>habeas corpus,</hi> is firſt commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Marſhalſey as the courſe is, and then bayled by the Court, which indeed is an expreſſe preſident, that might per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps well have been added to the number of the firſt 12, which ſo plainly ſhew the practiſe of inlarging priſoners in this Caſe, by judgment of the Court upon the <hi>habeas corpus,</hi> But it is true, that in the ſcrowles of that yeare where the bayles are entred, but not in the Record of the <hi>Habeas Corpus,</hi> there was a note, that this <hi>Broome</hi> was bayled <hi>per mandatum privati Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lii,</hi> but plainly this is not any kind of Argument, that therefore in law he might not have beene other wiſe bayled.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">40 <hi>Wendens</hi> Caſe.</note> The ſelfe ſame is to be ſaid of another of this kind, in <hi>Mich.</hi> 40. <hi>El. rot.</hi> 37. <hi>Wendens</hi> Caſe, <hi>Tho. Wenden</hi> was committed to the Gatehouſe by the Queene and the Lords of the Counſell <hi>procertis cauſis</hi> generally, he is brought by <hi>Habeas corpus</hi> into the Kings Bench, and bayled by the Court. But it is ſaid, that in the Scrowles of that yeare it appeares, that his inlargement was <hi>pro conſenſum Dom. privati Conſilii,</hi> and it is true that the Queenes Attorney did tell the Court, that the Lords of the Counſell did aſſent to it. Followes it therefore that it could not have beene without ſuch aſſent.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">43 <hi>Eliz.</hi>
                     </note> Next is <hi>Hill.</hi> 43. <hi>El. rot.</hi> 89. when divers Gentlemen of ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all quality were impriſoned by the command of the Privie Counſell, the Queen being graciouſly pleaſed to inlarge them, ſends a comandement to the Iudges of the Kings Bench, that they ſhould take ſuch a courſe, for the delivering of them upon bayle as they ſhould think fit, and they did ſo, and inlarged
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:54884:23"/> them upon Writs of <hi>hab. corpus.</hi> Followes it therefore, that this might not have beene done by law, if the parties themſelves had deſired it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iac.</hi> Sir <hi>Io. Brockets</hi> Caſe.</note> So in <hi>Tr.</hi> 1 <hi>Jac. rot.</hi> 30. Sir <hi>Io. Brocket</hi> being committed to the Gatehouſe, is returned to ſtand committed <hi>pro mandatum pravati Conſilii,</hi> and hee is inlarged <hi>virtute warranti. a Conſilio predicti.</hi> But the ſame anſwer that ſatisfie for the reſt before cited, ſerves for this alſo.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">12 <hi>Iac. James Reynar</hi> Caſe</note> The laſt of theſe, is <hi>Reynars</hi> caſe, in <hi>Mich.</hi> 12. <hi>Iac. rot.</hi> 119. hee was committed to the Gatehouſe, by the Lords of the Counſel, and being brought into the Kings Bench by <hi>Habeas Corpus,</hi> is inlarged upon bayl, but this they ſay was upon a letter written from one of the Lords of the Counſell to the Iudges. It is true that ſuch a letter was written, but the anſwer to the former preſidents of this nature, are ſufficient to cleare this alſo.</p>
                  <p>And in all theſe obſerve:</p>
                  <p n="1">1 That it appeares not, that the party ever deſired to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged by the Court, or was denied it.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Letters either from the King or Counſell cannot alter the law in any caſe: So that hitherto, nothing hath beene brought on the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary part, that hath any force or colour of reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in it.</p>
                  <p>Wee come now my Lords to thoſe preſidents of the other nature cited againſt the liberty of the Subject: That is, ſuch as have beene uſed to miſlike, that perſons ſo committed may not be inlarged by the Court.</p>
                  <p>They are in number eight, but there is not one of them that proves any ſuch thing, as your Lordſhips will plainly ſee upon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>opening them.</p>
                  <p>The firſt foure of them are exactly in the ſame words, ſaving that the names of the perſons and the priſons differ, I ſhall therefore recite them all one after another, and then cleare them together.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">7 <hi>H.</hi> 7. <hi>Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rards</hi> Caſe.</note> The firſt is <hi>Richard Everards</hi> caſe, <hi>Hill.</hi> 7. <hi>H.</hi> 7. <hi>rot.</hi> 18. he and others were committed to the Marſhalley of the Houſhold <hi>per mandatum Dom. Regis,</hi> and ſo returned upon a <hi>habeas cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus</hi> into the Kings Bench, whereupon the entry is onely <hi>Qui committitur Marr. &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">8 <hi>H.</hi> 7. <hi>Cher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> Caſe.</note> The ſecond is <hi>Hill.</hi> 8. <hi>H.</hi> 7. <hi>Richard Cherries</hi> caſe he was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:54884:24"/> to the Major of Windſor <hi>per mandatum Dom. Regis,</hi> and ſo returned upon a <hi>habeas corpus,</hi> and the entry is onely <hi>Qui committitur Marr. &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">9 <hi>H.</hi> 7. <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons</hi> Caſe.</note> The third is <hi>Hill.</hi> 9. <hi>H.</hi> 7. <hi>rot.</hi> 14. <hi>Chriſtopher Burtons</hi> caſe, who was committed to the Marſhalſey of the Houſhold, <hi>per man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datum Dom. Regis,</hi> and ſo returned upon his <hi>habeas corpus,</hi> and the entry is likewiſe <hi>Qui committitur Marr. &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">19 <hi>H.</hi> 7. <hi>Vrſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wicks</hi> Caſe.</note> The fourth is <hi>George Vrſwicks</hi> caſe, <hi>Paſ.</hi> 19. <hi>H.</hi> 7 <hi>Rot.</hi> 19. he was committed to the Sheriffs of London <hi>per mandatum Dom. Regis,</hi> and returned ſo upon his <hi>habeas corpus, Qui committitur Marr. &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Theſe foure have beene uſed principally, as expreſſe preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, to prove that a priſoner ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted cannot be inlarged, and perhaps at the firſt ſight, to men that know not, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve not the courſe and entries of the Court of Kings Bench, they may be apprehended to prove as much, but in truth they rather prove the contrary, at leaſt there is no colour in them of any ſuch matter as they have beene uſed for. To which pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe I beſeech your Lordſhips to call to your memories, that which I firſt obſerved to you touching the courſe of that Court. Where a priſoner is brought in by <hi>habeas corpus,</hi> he is (if he be not to be remanded) firſt committed to the Marſhall of the Court, and then bayled as his caſe requires. This is ſo certaine as it can never be otherwiſe. Now theſe men being thus com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted expreſſe command of the King, are firſt you ſee taken from the priſons whither they were firſt committed, wherein you may obſerve my Lords, that if a generall ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of matter of State were of force in ſuch a caſe, it might be as needfull in point of State to have the priſoner remain in the priſon where the King by ſuch an abſolute command commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him, as to have him at all committed; when they have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken them from the priſons where before they were they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit them to the Marſhall of their owne Court, which is but the firſt ſtep to bayling them: now it appeares not indeed that they were bayled, for then <hi>Traditur in Ball.</hi> had followed, but nothing at all appeares that they were denied it, perhaps they never asked it, perhaps they could not finde ſuch as were ſufficient to bayle them. And in truth whenſoever any man
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:54884:24"/> is but removed from any priſon in England (though it be for debt or treſpaſſe onely) into that Court, the entry is but in the ſelfe ſame ſillables as in theſe foure caſes.</p>
                  <p>And in truth if theſe proceedings did prove, that any of the priſoners named in them were not bayleable, or had beene thought by the Court not to have beene bayleable, it will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily follow, that no man living that is ordinarily removed from any priſon into the Kings Bench, or that is there upon any ordinary action of debt, or action of treſpaſſe, could bee bayled, for every man that is brought thither, and not reman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and every man that is areſted but for a debt or treſpaſſe and was returned into that Court, is likewiſe committed to the Marſhall of that Court, and by the ſelfe ſame entry, and not otherwiſe; yet theſe foure havebeen much ſtood on, and have ſtrangely miſled the judgement of ſome that did not, or would not ſeeme to underſtand the courſe of that Court.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">7 <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>Pages</hi> Caſe.</note> The fifth of this nature is, <hi>Edward Pages</hi> caſe, it is <hi>Tr.</hi> 7. <hi>H.</hi> 8. this might have beene well reckoned with the former foure, had not the miſentry of the Clerk only made it vary from them. <hi>Ed. Page</hi> was committed to the Marſhalſea of the Houſhold, and that <hi>per mandatum Dom. Regis,</hi> and returned to be therfore detained, and the entry is <hi>Qui committitur Marr. Hoſpitii Dom. Regis,</hi> This word <hi>Marr.</hi> is written in the Margine of the roll; this hath beene uſed to prove, that the Judges remanded this priſoner, if they had done ſo, the remanding had beene onely while they adviſed, and not any ſuch award which is given when they adjudge him not bayleable; but in truth the word <hi>Committitur</hi> ſhewes, that there was not any remanding of him, nor doth that Court ever commit any man to the Marſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſea of the Houſhold: and beſides the word <hi>Marr.</hi> for <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſcallo</hi> in the Margine, ſhewes plainly that he was committed to the Marſhall of the Kings Bench, and not remanded to the Marſhalſea of the Houſhold, for ſuch entry of that word in the Margine, is perpetually in caſes of that nature, when they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit a man to their owne priſon, and ſo give him the firſt ſtep to baylement, which he may have if he ask it, and can finde bayle; and doubtleſſe theſe words of <hi>Hoſpitii pred.</hi> were added by the error of the Clerk for wnat of diſtinction in his underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:54884:25"/> from the <hi>Marr.</hi> of the Kings Bench to the Marſhall of the Houſhold.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">8 <hi>Iac. Caeſars</hi> Caſe.</note> The ſixth of theſe is <hi>Tho. Caeſars</hi> Caſe, it is 8 <hi>Iac. rot.</hi> 99. This <hi>Caſar</hi> was committed to the Marſhalſea of the Houſhold <hi>per mandatum Dom. Regis,</hi> and returned to be therefore detained, and indeed a <hi>remittitur</hi> is in the roll, but not a <hi>remittitur quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſque,</hi> but onely that kind of <hi>remittitur</hi> which is onely uſed while the Court adviſes. And in truth this is ſo farre from proving any thing againſt the reſolution of the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, That it appeares that the opinion of the reverend Jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of that time was, that the returne was inſufficient, and that if it were not amended, the priſoner ſhould be diſcharged. For in the Book of Rules in the Court of <hi>Mich.</hi> Terme (when <hi>Caeſars</hi> Caſe was in queſtion) they expreſly ordered, that if the Stewards Marſhall did not amend their returne, the priſoner ſhould be abſolutely diſcharged, the words of the Rule are <hi>Niſi Seneſchalus &amp; Maniſcal. Hoſpitii Dom Regis ſufficientur returnaverint brevem de Habeas Corpus Thome Caeſar dier. mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur. prox. per oſt. quindenam ſcilicet Martium. def. exonerabitur.</hi> And this is alſo the force of that Preſident, but yet there hath beene an interpretation upon this rule. It hath beene ſaid that the Judges gave this rule, becauſe the truth was, that the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne was falſe, and that it was well knowne, that the priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner was not committed by the immediate command of the King, but by the command of the Lord Chamberlaine, and thence (as it was ſaid) they made this rule: but this kind of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation is the firſt that ever was ſuppoſed, that Judges ſhould take notice of the truth or falſhood of the return other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, then the body of the returne could informe them. And the rule it ſelfe ſpeakes plainly of them, ſufficiencie onely, and not of the truth or falſhood of it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Emerſons</hi> Caſe.</note> The ſeventh of theſe is the caſe of <hi>Iames Deſmaiſtres, Edward Emerſon,</hi> and ſome others that were brewers, and were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the Marſhalſea of the Houſhold <hi>per mandat. Dom. Regis,</hi> and ſo returned upon <hi>habeas corpus,</hi> and it is true, that the roll ſhewes that they were remanded, but the remanding was onely upon adviſement, and indeed the grave and upright Judges of the time were ſo carefull, leaſt upon the entry of the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:54884:25"/> remanding, any ſuch miſtake might be, as might perhaps miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lead poſterity in ſo great a point, that they would expreſly have this word (immediate) added to the <hi>Remittitur,</hi> that ſo all men that ſhould meet with the roll might ſee, that it was done for the preſent onely, and not upon any debate of the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion. And beſides, that there is no <hi>quouſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan>
                     </hi> to it, which is uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally added; when the higheſt award upon debate or reſolution of this kind is given by them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">12. <hi>Iam</hi> Sir <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel Saltonſtalls</hi> Caſe.</note> The eighth of theſe is the Caſe of <hi>Saltonſtall,</hi> it is <hi>Hill.</hi> 12. <hi>Iac.</hi> Sir. <hi>Samuel Saltonſtall</hi> was committed to the Fleet, <hi>per man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datum Dom. Regis;</hi> and beſides, by the Court of Chauncery, for diſobeying an order of that Court, and is returned upon his <hi>habeas corpus,</hi> to be therefore detained. And it is true that a <hi>Remittitur</hi> is entred in the roll, but it is onely a <hi>remittitur pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner prodict'.</hi> without <hi>quouſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ſecundum legem de liberatus fue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> and in truth it appeares on the Record, that the Court gave the Warden of the Fleet, three ſeverall dayes at ſeverall times, to amend his returne, and in the interim <hi>remittitur perſone pred'.</hi> Certainly if the Court had thought that the returne had beene good, they would not have given ſo many ſeverall dayes to have amended it, for if that <hi>Mandatum Dom. Regis</hi> had beene ſufficient in the Caſe, why need it to have been amended.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">13. <hi>Iac.</hi> Sir <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel Saltonſtalls</hi> Caſe.</note> The ninth and laſt of theſe is, <hi>Tr.</hi> 13. <hi>Iac. Rot.</hi> 71. The Caſe of the ſame Sir <hi>Samuel Saltonſtall,</hi> he is returned by the Warden of the Fleet, and in the Caſe before, and generally <hi>remittitur,</hi> is in the roll which proves nothing at all, that therefore the Court thought he might not by law be inlarged; and beſides in both caſes hee ſtood committed alſo for diſobeying an order in the Chauncery.</p>
                  <p>Theſe are all that have beene pretended to the contrary in this great point, and upon the view of them thus opened to our Lordſhips, it is plaine, that there is not one, not ſo much as one at all; that proveth any ſuch thing, as that perſons com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by the command of the King, or the Lords of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell without cauſe ſhewed, might not be enlarged, but indeed the moſt of them expreſly prove rather the contrary.</p>
                  <p>Now my Lords, having thus gone through the Preſidents of Record, that concerne the point of either ſide, before I come to
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:54884:26"/> the other kind of Preſidents, which are the ſolemne reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Judges in former times, I ſhall (as I am commanded alſo by the Houſe of Commons) repreſent unto your Lordſhips ſomewhat elſe; they have thought very conſiderable; with which they met, whilſt they were in a moſt carefull enquiry of whatſoever concerned them in this great queſtion.</p>
                  <p>It is my Lords a draught of an entry of a judgement in that great caſe lately adjudged in the Court of Kings Bench, when divers Gentlemen impriſoned <hi>per ſpeciale mandatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Dom. Regis,</hi> were by the award and order of the Court, after ſolemne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, ſent back to priſon, becauſe it was expreſly ſaid, they could not in Juſtice deliver them, though they prayed to be bayled. The caſe is famous, and well knowne to your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, therfore I need not further to mention it, as yet indeed there is no judgement entred upon the Roll, but there is room enough for any kind of judgement to be entred. But my Lords, there is a forme of a judgement, a moſt unuſuall one; ſuch a one as never was in any ſuch caſe before (for indeed there was never before any Caſe ſo adjudged) and thus drawne upon by a chiefe Clerk of that Court (by direction of M. Attorney ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall) as the Houſe was informed by the Clerk, in which the reaſon of the judgement, and remanding of thoſe Gent. is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in ſuch ſort, as if it ſhould be declared upon Record for ever, that the Lawes were, that no man could ever be inlarged from impriſonment that ſtood committed by ſuch an abſolute command.</p>
                  <p>The draught is onely in Sir <hi>John Heninghams</hi> Caſe, being one of the Gent. that was remanded, and it was made for a form for all the reſt. The words of it are after the uſuall entry of a <hi>Curia adviſare vult</hi> for a time. That <hi>viſis retur, predict. nec non diverſis antiquis recordis in Curia hic remaveum conſimiles caſus continentibus matura<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> deliberatione, inde prius habita eo quod milla ſpecialis cauſa captionis ſive detentionis pred. Iohanis ex pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitur ſed generalitur quod detentus eſt in priſona pred'. per ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciale mandatum Dom. Regis ideo pred'. Iohanes remittitur prefat. cuſtodi Marr. Hoſpitii pred'. Salvo cuſtodiend. quouſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> &amp;c.</hi> that is, <hi>quouſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> legem deliberatus fuerit.</hi> And if that Court that is the higheſt for ordinary Juſtice, cannot deliver him <hi>ſecundem
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:54884:26"/> legem.</hi> What law is there I beſeech you my Lords, that can be ſought for in any other inferiour Court to deliver him. Now my Lords, becauſe this draught, if it were entred in the Roll, (as it was prepared for no other purpoſe) would be as great a declaration, contrary to the many Acts of Parliament already cited, contrary to all Preſidents of former times, and to all rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Law, to the utter ſubverſion of the higheſt liberty and right belonging to every free man of this Kingdome, and for that eſpecially; alſo it ſuppoſes that divers ancient Records had been looked into by the Court in like caſes, by which Records their judgements were directed, whereas in truth, there is not any one Record at all extant that with any colour (not ſo much indeed as with any colour) warrants the judgement, therefore the Houſe of Commons thought fit alſo, that I ſhould with the reſt that hath beene ſaid ſhew this draught alſo to your Lordſhips, I come now to the other kind of Preſidents, that is, ſolemne reſolutions of Iudges, which being not of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, remaine onely in authentique copies: but of this kinde there is but one in this caſe, that is the reſolution of all the Iudges in the time of Queene <hi>Elizabeth.</hi> It was in the 34 of her raigne, when divers perſons had beene committed by ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute command, and delivered by the Iuſtices of the one Bench or the other, whereupon it was deſired, that the Iudges would declare in what caſes perſons committed by ſuch command were to be inlarged, hath beene variouſly cited, and variouſly apprehended.</p>
                  <p>The Houſe of Commons therefore deſiring with all care, to informe themſelves as fully of the truth of it, as poſſibly they might, got into their hands from a member of their Houſe, a Book of ſelected caſes, collected by a reverend and learned chiefe Iuſtice of the common place, that was one of them that gave the reſolution, which is entred at large in that booke: I meane the Lord chiefe Iuſtice <hi>Anderſon,</hi> it is written in the booke with his own hand, as the reſt of the book is, and how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever it hath beene cited, and was cited in that great judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon the <hi>habeas corpus</hi> in the Kings Bench, as if it had been, that upon ſuch commitments the Iudges might not bayle
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:54884:27"/> the priſoners, yet it is moſt plaine that in the reſolution itſelfe, no ſuch thing is contained, but rather expreſſed the contrary, I ſhall better repreſent it to your Lordſhips by reading it, then by opening it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Then it was read here.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If this reſolution doth reſolve any thing, it doth indeed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Iurie reſolve fully the contrary to that which hath bin pretended, and enough for the maintenance of the ancient and ſundamentall point of liberty of the perſon, to be regained by <hi>habeas corpus</hi> when any is impriſoned. And I the rather thought it fit now to read it to your Lordſhips, that it might be at large heard, becauſe in the great judgement in the Kings Bench, though it were cited at the barre, as againſt this point of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall liberty, as alſo at the Bench, yet though every thing elſe of Record that was uſed, were at large read openly, this was not read either at Barre or Bench; for indeed if it had, every hearer would eaſily have knowne the force of it, to have been indeed contrary to the judgement.</p>
                  <p>My Lords, having thus gone through the Charge commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to me by the Houſe of Commons, and having thus mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to your Lordſhips, and opened the many Preſidents of Records, and that draught of the judgement in this like caſe, as alſo this reſolution, I ſhall now (as I had leave and direction given me, leſt your Lordſhips ſhould be put to much trouble, and expence of time in finding or getting Copies at large of thoſe things which I have cited,) offer alſo to your Lordſhips authentique Copies of them all, and ſo leave them, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever elſe I have ſaid; to your Lordſhips further conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="precedents">
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:54884:27"/>
                  <head>Mr. <hi>Seldens</hi> Preſidents.</head>
                  <head>The true Copie of the Preſidents of Record, in one of the Arguments made at the firſt conference with the Lords tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the libertie of the perſon of every Free-man.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>Inter Record. Dom. Regis Caroli in Theſauro Recept. Scaccarij ſui ſub cuſtodi Dom. Theſaurar &amp; Camerar ibidem Rema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. vizt. Placita coram Domino Rege apud Weſtmonaſteriu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de Ter' Paſche Anno Regis Edwardi 3. poſt conqueſt Ang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liae 18. inter alia ſic continetur ut ſequitur.</p>
                  </argument>
                  <div type="record">
                     <head>Rot. 33. Adhuc de termino Paſche.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>London,</hi> 18. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>Bilde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtons Caſe cite devant, fo.</hi> 33.</note> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Ominus Rex mandavit delicto &amp; fideli ſuo Roberto de Dalton Conſtabullar' Turris ſuae London vel ejus locum tenent' bre. ſuum in haec verba Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vardus Dei gracia Rex Angliae, Franciae, &amp; Dominus Hiberniae delicto &amp; fideli ſuo Roberto de Dalton Conſtabular' Turris ſuae London vel ejus locum teneum ſalutem maudamus quod Johannem Bildeſton ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellan' quem vic. noſtr. London ad mandatum noſtrum apud pred. Turrim vobis liberavit ab eiſdem recipiatis &amp; in priſona noſtra Turris London pred. Salvo Cuſtodiar fac' quouſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ſuper hoc dux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erimus emandand. Teſte meipſo apud Turrim noſtram London 30. die Marcij Anno Regni nostri Angliae 16 Regni vero noſtri Francie 30. Et modo ſclt. in Craſt Aſſen. Dom. anno Rege nuns 8. coram Domino Rege apud Westminſt. venit Iohannes de Wyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wicke locum teneus pred. Conſtabular &amp; adduxit coram Iustici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar' hic in Cur. pred. Iohannem de Bildeſton quem als a prefat. Vicecomit. virtute brevis pred. recepit. &amp;c. Et dicit quod ipſe a Dommo Rege huit mandat. ducend. &amp; liber and corpus
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:54884:28"/> ipſius Iohannis de Bildeſton prefat. Iuſticiar. hic. &amp;c. Et queſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum eſt de pred. Iohannem de Wynwicke ſi quam aliam detentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem prefat Iohannis de Bildeſton habeat Camm. Qui dicit quod non niſi bre. pred. tantum, Et quia videtur cur. bre. pred. ſufficien, non eſſe coram pred. Johannis de Bildeſton priſon. Marr' Regis hic retinen. &amp;c. Idem de Iohannes dimittitur per manus Willielm. de Wakefield rectoris Eccill. de willingham Iohannis de Wynwicke in Com. Kanc. Johanis de Norton in Com. Norff. Nicolai de Blan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defford in Com. Middl. &amp; Rogeri de Bromley in Com. Stafford, qui eum manuceperunt Habend. in eum Coram Domino Rege apud in Octabis Sancti Trin. ubicun<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> &amp;c. vizt. Corpus pro corpore, &amp;c. Ad quos Octabis Sancte Trin. Coram Domino Rege apud Weſtm. ven. pred. per manus pred. Et ſuper hoc mandavit Iuſticiar. ſuis hic quoddam bre. ſuum Clauſ. in hec verba Edwardus Dei gracia Rex Anglia, &amp; Franciae, &amp; dominus Hiberniae, delictis &amp; fid li ſuis Willielmo Scot, &amp; ſocijs ſuis Justiciar' ad placita coram nobis tenend. aſſignat ſaltem cum nuper mandaverimus delicto, &amp; fideli noſtro Roberto de Dalton Constabular' Turris noſtre London vel ejus locum tenen. quod Iohannem de Bildeſton Capellaum Capt. &amp; decent. in priſona turris pred. hoc preceptum noſtrum pro ſuſpitione contra factionis magni Sigilli noſtri cum Attachiat. &amp; aelias Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis capcon. &amp; detentionem pred. cangen. ſalvo &amp; ſecur' duci fac' Coram nobis in Cron Aſcen. Dom, ubicun<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> tunc fuiſſemus in Anglia perſone Marreſcall. noſtre coram nobis liberand. in eadem quouſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> per quendam informatorem eſſemus plenius informat. Cuſtod. &amp; tuta inde informatione pred. ulterius pred' ſuper hoc fieri facerimus quod fore viderimus faciend. ſecundum legem, &amp; conſuetudinem Regni noſtri Anglie nos in caſu quod dictus In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formator non verum, Coram nobis ad informand nos plenius ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per premiſſ. volentes eidem Jahannem ea de cauſa Iusticiar' defer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr' in hac parte vobis mandamus quod ſi pred Informator' in Quenden. Sanct. Trin. prox. futur. vel circa non venit non ſuper hoc plenius informat. tunc advent. ejuſdem informatoris minime expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctat. eidem Iohanni ſuper hoc fieri fac. Iuſtic. complement. prout fort videritis faciend. ſecundum legem &amp; conſuetudinem Regni noſtri Anglie Teſte meipſo apud Weſtminſt. 12. Maij Anno Regni noſtri Anglie 18. Regni vero noſtri Franc' 5<hi rend="sup">to</hi>. Quo quidem bre. reſpect. fact. est proclamaco. quod ſiquis dictum regem ſuper premiſſ. in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formare
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:54884:28"/> vel erga ipſum Iohannem profequi veluerit quod veniat Et ſuper hoc venit pred. W. de wakefield, Nicholas de Wandſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth, Johannes Brynwyn, Iohannes de Longham, Iohannes de Norton, &amp; Rogero de Bromly amnes de Com' Midd' &amp; man' pred. Iohannem de Bildeſton habend Cum Coram Domino Rege de die in diem uſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ad prefat' quinden. Sanct. Trin. ubicun<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan>, &amp;c. Ad quem diem Anno 18. coram Domino Rege apud Weſtminſt. vonit pred. Iohannes de Bildeſton per manus pred. &amp; iterata facta eſt proclam. in forma qua ſuperius, &amp;c. Et nullus venit ad dictum regem informand' &amp;c. per quod conceſſ. eſt quod pred. Johannes de Bildeſton erat inde ſine die ſalva ſemper actione Dom. Regis ſi q<hi rend="sup">ua</hi>, &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="record">
                     <head>De Ter' Sanct. Hillar' Anno 22. H. 8. &amp; per cont. Rot. ejuſdem Retul. 38.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">London. Glouc. 22 <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>Parkers Caſe. cite ante, fo.</hi> 33. b.</note> Iohannes Parker per Ricardum Choppin, &amp; W. Daunſey Vic' London virtute brevis Dom. Regis de lattitat. pro pace verſus ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum Iohannem Parker ad ſect. in Johannis Bruton eis inde direct &amp; coram rege duct. cum cauſa, vizt. quod idem Iohannes Parker capt. ſuit in Civitate pred. pro ſecus pacis pred. &amp; pro ſuſpicione felonie per ipſum apud Croweall in Com. Gloceſt. perpetrat per no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men Iohannis Parker de Thornbury in Com. Glocest. Corſer alias dict. Iohannes Charbs de eodem Com' Surgeon ac per mandatum Dom. Regis nunciat. per Robertum Pecke gen' de Cliffords Inn qui committitur Marh' &amp;c. &amp; poſtea iſteo eodem termino tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur in Ballium Thomae Atkins de Thornebury pred. Weaver, &amp; Willi. No le de eadem ville &amp; Com. uſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> a die Paſche in unum men. Weaver ubicun<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> &amp;c. Et quod idem Iohannes Parker citra eun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem diem perſonaliter comparuit coram Iusticiar' Dom, Regis ad prox. general' Gaol de liberation' in Com. Gloceſt. prox. te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nend. ad ſubijciend. &amp; recipiend. ea omnia, &amp; ſingula quod pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fat. Iuſticiar' de eo tunc ordinari contigerint, &amp;c. vizt. Corpus procorpore &amp;c. Ad quem diem pred. Iohannes Parker licet ipſi 4. placit ſelemniter exact ad comparend. non ven. ideo caperet cum pler' Trin. ad quem diem ex Octab. Trin. poſtea Trin. 24. H. 8. ex noſtro quinden. Paſche. Ad quem diem bre. &amp; vic' return' quoad Auſt tent. apud London die lune prox' poſt feſt. Sancte Scholaſtice Anno Regis H. 8. 25. Johannes Parker, &amp;
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:54884:29"/> W. Nole vel'fuer. prout patet per bre. Regis de Ter' Paſche Anne 25. Rs. pred.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="record">
                     <head>De ter. Sanct. Mich. Anno 35. H. 8. &amp; per cont. ejuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem Rot. 33.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">35. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>Bincks, Caſe cite ante fo.</hi> 33. b.</note> Iohannes Binks per Ro. Baker Ar. Seneſchall. Cur. Marr. &amp; Radum Hapton Mar' ejuſdem Cur. virtute brevis Dom. Regis de Habeas Corpus ad Subiiciend. &amp; recipiend. &amp;c. eis inde Direct. Coram Domino Rege duct' cum cauſa, vizt. quod ante adventum brevis pred. Johannes Bincks captus fuit per mandatum privati Conſilij Dom. Regis pro ſuſpitione feloniae, &amp; pro alijs cauſis illos movent. &amp; duc' ad Gaol. Marr. &amp; ibidem detent. virtute Gaol' pred. qui comittitur Marr, &amp;c. Et imediate ex gra' cur. ſpecial' pred. Iohannes Binckes de Magna Marlow in Com. Buck Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver traditur in Ball; Thomae Bignam de London Gent. &amp; Johan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni Woodward de Marlow, de Marlow pred. Taylor uſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> in Craſt. Sanct. Martin. ubicun<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> &amp;c. ut<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> pleg. corpus pro corpore, &amp;c. Ad quem diem comperuit &amp; Robertus Drury <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>r' &amp; Iohannes Boſſe gen. Domino Juſticiar. Dom. Regis ad pacem in Com. Buck. virtute brevis Dom. Regis eis direct. Domino Regi certificave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt quod nullum Indictiamentum de aliquibus felonis &amp; tranſg. verſus ipſum Johannem Byncks coram eis ad preſons reſident. Et ulterius de fama &amp; Geſtu ipſius Iohannis Byncks per Sacrum pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borum &amp; legalium homini Com. Buck. diligenter inquiri fecerunt, &amp; nihil aliud preter bonum de eo coram eis eſt compertum. Ideo conceſſ. est quod pred. Io. Byncks de premiſſis eat inde ſine die deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beratur per proclamationem &amp; Iur. prout moris eſt.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="record">
                     <head>De Ter. Paſ. Anno 2. &amp; 3, Ph. &amp; Mar. Rot. 58.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3. P. <hi>&amp; Mar Mar. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertons Caſe cite devant, fo.</hi> 33.</note> Ricus Overton nuper de London gen. per Tho. Letgh, &amp; Johan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem Machell vic' London virtute brevis duorum Regis &amp; Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginae de Habeas corpus ad ſtand. rect. &amp;c. eis inde direct. coram Willielmo Portman mil' captal Iuſticiar. &amp;c. duct. cum cauſa, vizt. quod pred Ricardus Overtan 9. die Octobr. ult. preter co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſ. fuit priſon de Newgate, &amp; ibidem in eadem perſona ſub cuſtod. dict. Vic. detent. ad mandatum per nobilium duorum honorabilis conſil. pred Regis &amp; regine quim committet. Marr. &amp;c. Et ime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate traditur in Ball. Willielmo Overton de London gen. &amp; Iohan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:54884:29"/> Taylor de perechia Sanct. Martinum apud Ludgate Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don mero. uſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> Octab. Trin. vizt. uter<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> manucaptor pred. corpus pro corpore &amp; poſtea Tr. 2. El. Regine, corpus Overton &amp; pleg. ſuos Octabis Michael. Ad quem diem ex menſ. Paſch. Ad quem diem vic. ret. quod ad Huſt. ſuum tent. Guild-hall Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitatis London die Lune poſt feſtum Sanct. Gregor. Epi. pred. W. Overton utl' eſt et per bre. Paſ. Anno ſuperd.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="record">
                     <head>De Te Sanct. Mich. Anno 2. &amp; 3. P. &amp; Mar. Rot. 16. Habet Chart. allocat. Trin. 2. &amp; 3. Phil. &amp; Mar.</head>
                     <p>Ricardus Overton nuper de Lond. gen. capt. Octab. Hill. pro quibuſdam altis prodic. unde indictat eſt, Ad quem diem Paſc. ad quem diem ex Cr. Animarum.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="record">
                     <head>De termino Paſche 4. &amp; 5. P. &amp; Mar. &amp; per cont. ejuſdem Rot. 45.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">4. <hi>&amp;</hi> 5 P <hi>&amp; Mar. Newports caſe cite ante</hi> 33</note> Edwardus Newport gen. per Robertum Oxenbridg mil' Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stabular. Turris pred. virtute bre. Dominor. Regis &amp; Regine de Habeas corpus ad Subiiciend. &amp;c. eis inde direct. ad barr. Coram Domino Rege &amp; Regina duct. cum cauſa, vizt. quod ipſe ſibi Commiſſ. fuit per mandat. Concill. Domine Regine qui Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titur Marr. &amp; immediate traditur in Ball. prout. &amp;c. Et poſtea ſine die per proclamationem virtute brevis de geſtis &amp; fama prout. &amp;c. Rot. 17. ejuſdem Anni.</p>
                     <p>De Ter. M. Anno 4. &amp; 5. P. &amp; Mar. per Cont. ejuſdem Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tul. 17. Mem. quod 14. die Octobr. Anno 4. &amp; 5. P. et. M. Edwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus Newport de Hanley in Com. Wigorun. Ac capt. fuit per Vx<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge in Com. pred. pro ſuſpitione contra factionis quarundem pec. Auri vocat French crownes per ipſum &amp; alibi in Com. Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor. fier. ſuppoſit. (&amp; eade cauſa per mandatum concill' Dominor. Regis &amp; Regine ad barr. tunc duct. fuit qui comittitur Marr. &amp;c. Et ſuper hoc idem Edwardus Newport traditur in Ball. Thomae Charge de Latton in Com. Eſſex gener. Edwarde Hales de pero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chia Sancti Ola<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ri London gen. Johanni Baker. Clerico Ordinar. London, Iohanni Gill de perochia Sanct. Tho Apoſtoli London Clothworker, &amp; Ricardo Parkes de Browneſgrave in Com Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorn. yeoman uſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> Octabis Hill. ubicun<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> &amp;c. vizt. qui libt. pleg. proced. ſub pena 100 l' &amp; pred. Edwardus Sub pena 200 l'.
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:54884:30"/> quas, &amp;c. Ad quem diem comperint &amp; committitur Conſtabular. Turris London per mandatum Conſil' Dom. Regis &amp; Regine ibid. ſalvo cuſtodiend quouſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan>, &amp;c. Et poſtea Paſ. 4 &amp; 5. P &amp; M. tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur in Ball. prout. patet per Scrivect. finium iſtius ter. &amp; poſtea M. 5. &amp; 6. P et M. exonerat. per cur. eo quod tam per Sacroru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 12. pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor. &amp; legalium hominum de pred. Com. Midd. coram Dom. Rege, &amp; Domina Regina hic in cur. mea parte Iurat, &amp; onerat. quam per Sacrament. 12. probor. legal. homin. de pred. Com. Wigor. cora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardo Saunders, &amp; Iohanne Whiddon mil. &amp; aliis Iuſticiar' di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor' Dom. Regis &amp; Regine ad pacem ac diverſis felonis tranſgreſſ. &amp; aliis malefact. in eodem com' perpetrat. audiend. &amp; terminand. aſſignat. virtute brevis dictor. Dominor. Regis &amp; Regine eis inde direct. in ea parte Jurat &amp; anerat ad in querendo de geſtu &amp; fama ipſius Edwardi compert. existit quod idem Edwardus eſt de bonis geſtu &amp; fama ideo proclamatio eſt inde fact a prout moris eſt ſecund. legem &amp; conſuetudinem Reg. Anglie, &amp;c. Conceſſ. eſt quod pred. Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardus eat inde ſine die.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="record">
                     <head>De Ter. Paſ. 9. El. Rot. 35.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">9 <hi>El. Laurence Caſe cite de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, fo.</hi> 34. a.</note> Tho. Lawrence per Christopher' Drap. majorem Civitatis Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don Ambroſiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Nicholas, &amp; Ricu' Lambert vic. ejuſdem Civitatis virtute brevis Dom. Regine de Habeas Corpus, &amp;c. ad ſubiiciend. &amp;c. eis inde direct. &amp; coram Domina Regina dict. cum cauſa, vizt. qaod 7. die Novembr. Anno regni Dom. El' nunc Regine Anglie 8. pred. Thomas Lawrence indicto brevinominat captus fuit in Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitate pred. &amp; in priſona dom. Regine, Sub cuſtod. pred. coram vic. detent. per mandatum Conſil' dom, Regine qui committitur Mar. &amp;c. &amp; ſuper hoc tradit. in Ball' prout patet per Scriuect. finum iſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us ter.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="record">
                     <head>De Ter, Paſch. 9. El. Rot. 68.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">9. <hi>El. Conſtables caſe cite devant fo.</hi> 34 a.</note> Robertus Conſtable Ar' per Franciſeum Jobſon mil' locu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tenend. Turris London virtute brevis Dom' Regine de Habeas corpus ei inde direct &amp; coram Domina Regina dict' cum cauſa vizt. quod idem Robertus Constable prefat Franciſco Jobſon commiſſus fuit per mandatum privat. Conſil' Dom. Regine ſalvo cuſtodiend. Qui committitur Marr. &amp;c. Et postea iſto eodem Ter. traditur in Ball. prout patet inter ſcriuect finum istius Ter.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="record">
                     <head>Ter. Paſ. Anno 20. El. &amp; per cont. ejuſdem Rot. 72.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">20 <hi>El. Brow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings Caſe cite devant, fo.</hi> 34 a.</note> Johannes Browning per Owen Hopton mil' locum tenen' Turris
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:54884:30"/> Domine Regine London virtute brevis Habias Corpus ad Subii<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciend. ei inde direct, &amp; coram dilecto &amp; fideli Ch'ro Wray mil. capt. Justiciar. Dom. Regine ad placita coram nobis tenend. aſſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat apud Hoſpitium ſuum in Serjants Inne Fleet-ſtreet London die lune, vizt. 12. die Maij duct. cum cauſa vizt. quod pred. Iohannes browning Comiſſus fuit eidem locum tenend. per mandatum priva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti conſil' Regine ſalvo cuſtodiend. &amp;c. Qui com. Mar. &amp;c. &amp; poſtea iſto eodem Ter. traditur in Ball' prout pat. per ſtruect fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num iſtius Ter.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="record">
                     <head>De Ter. Sanct. Hillar. Anno 40. El. Regine &amp; per cont. ejuſdem Rot. 62.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">40. <hi>El Hare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corts c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ſe cite devant, fo.</hi> 34.</note> Edwardus Harecort per Hugonem Parlour cuſtod. priſone Domine Regine de Gatehouſe infra Civitatem Weſtminſt. in Com. Middl. virtute brevis Domine Regine de Habeas corpus ad Subii<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciena. &amp;c. ei inde direct, &amp; coram Domina Regina apud Weſtminſt. dicta cum cauſa, vizt. quod ante, advent brevis pred. ſcil. 7. die Octobr. An. Regni dom. Regine nunc. 39. corpus Edwardi Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cort per duos privat Conſil. dicte Domine regine ei comiſſ. fuit ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vo &amp; ſecurae cuſtodiend. certis de cauſis ipſos movent, &amp; ei igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis qui committitur Marr. &amp;c. Et poſtea iſto eodem Ter. traditur in Ball. prout patet per Struct finum iſtius termini.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="record">
                     <head>De Vacatione Hillar. Anno 43. El.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Catesbies caſe cite antea fo.</hi> 34.</note> Robertus Cattesbie per Johannem Phillips Guardian' de le Fleete virtute brevis Domine Regine de Habeas Corpus ad Subii<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciend. &amp;c. ei inde direct &amp; coram Edwardo Fenner uno Iuſticiar. Domine Regine ad placita coram ipſa Regina tenend. aſſignat apud Winbheſter houſe in Burgo de Southwarke in Com. Surr. dict. cum cauſa, vizt. quod pred. Robertus comiſſus fuit priſone pred. primo die Marcij Anno 43. El. Warr. diverſorum pre nobilium virorum de privato conſilio Domine Regine in hec verba. <hi>To the Warden of the Fleet or his Deputie; Theſe ſhall bee to will and require you, to receive at the hands of the Keeper of the Compter of Woodſtreet, the perſon of <hi>Robert Catesbie</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſquire, and him to detaine and keepe ſafely in that Priſon un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der your charge, untill you ſhall have other direction to the contrary, whereof this ſhall be your Warrant.</hi> Et praefat Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertus Commiſſus fuit Marr. per prefat Edwardum Fenner, &amp; ſtatim traditur in Ball' prout patet, &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="record">
                     <pb n="58" facs="tcp:54884:31"/>
                     <head>Ter. Hill. Anno 43. Eliz. Regine 12. Iac. Regis.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">12. <hi>Iac Beck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withs</hi> caſe <hi>cite dev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>nt. fo.</hi> 34.</note> Ricardus Beckwith gen' per Aquilam Wykes cuſtod, perſone de Gatehouſe in Com. Midd. virtute libris Dom. Regis de habe as corpus ad Subiiciend. ei inde direct. &amp; coram Domino Rege duct. cum cauſa vizt. quod ante advent. libris predict. ſcilicet 10 die Iulii. Anno Regni Dom. Jac. Regis dei gracia Anglie Franc. &amp; Hibernie fidei defenſor. &amp;c. 11. et Scot. 47. predict. Ricardus Beck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with ſibi Comiſſus fuit priſone predict. ſub cuſtod. ſua virtute cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſdem Warrant ſibi fact. et direct. per Georgium divina provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentia Cant. Archiepiſcopum totius Anglie primat. et. Metropoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane Henric. Com. Northampton Dominum Guardiam. 5. por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuum et un. de privato Conſil. Regis Tho. Com. Suffolk Dom. Camerar' Regie Familie ac ſacr' Conſil. Dom. Regis Edwardum Domini Wooton gubernator Regie familie Johannem Dom. Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoppe <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ice-Camerar' Regie Familie cujus Warrant. tenor. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitur in hec verba To. <hi>
                           <hi>Aquila Wykes</hi> Keeper of the Gatehouſe in Weſtminſter or his Deputy, whereas it is thought meet that <hi>Miles Rayner,</hi> and <hi>Richard Beckwith,</hi> be reſtrained of the 12 liberties, and committed to the priſon of the Gatehouſe, Theſe ſhall be to will and require you to receive the perſons of the ſaid <hi>Reynard</hi> and <hi>Beckwith</hi> into your charge, and ſafe keeping in that priſon, there to remaine untill you ſhall have further order from us in that behalfe, for which this ſhall be your war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, Dated at Whitehall the 10 of July 1613.</hi> Et poſtea iſto eodem termino.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="record">
                     <head>De Ter. Mich. Anno. 14. Jac. per cont. ejuſd. Rot. 14. 7.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Turris London.</hi> 14 <hi>Iac.</hi> Sir <hi>Tho. Mounſons</hi> caſe <hi>cite devant. fo.</hi> 34.</note> Thomas Mounſon miles per Georgium More locum teneum Turris Dom. Regis London virtute libris Dom. Regis de Habeas Corpus ad ſubiiciend. &amp;c. ei inde direct. coram Domino Rege apud Weſtm. duct. cum Cauſa vizt. quod ante adventum libris pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict. predict. Thomas ſibi Commiſſus fuit per warrant. adverſ. Dominis de privato Conſilio Dom. Regis ſibi direct. &amp;c. Qui Committitur Marr. &amp;c. Et ſuper hoc traditur in Ball' prout patet per Scruect. fin. iſtius Terminum.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="record">
                     <head>De Ter. Mich. 7. H 7. &amp; per cont. ejuſdem Rot. 6.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">7. <hi>H.</hi> 7. <hi>Bruggs</hi> caſe <hi>cite de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vunt.</hi> 34.</note> Tho. Brugg junior, nuper de Yanington in Com' Hartford gen'
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:54884:31"/> Iohanes Rawleus &amp; te Com. &amp; in ure de Lemſter in Com. pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict' Yeoman, Robert us Sherman nuper de Lemſter in Com. pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict. Walter Thomas nuper de eadem in Com. predict. Hoſier. Tho. Ballard nuper de eadem in eodem Com. Smith Cadwallader ap Iohn Duy nuper de Kerry in Marchia Wallie in Com. Salop ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jacen. gen. Reignald ap Breignham, alias Sherman, nuper de Leamſter in Com. Herreford Shereman, &amp; Thomas Turner nuper de king ſland in Com. Hereford courſer, ſunt in cuſtod. Marr. ad mandatum Dom. Regis, &amp;c, ac pro aliis certis de cauſis pro ut pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet alibi de record, &amp;c. per record. iſtius Ter. poſtea iſto Termin. Dominus relaxavit mandatum ſuum &amp; pro recuſſ. predict. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peraverint per Attorn. &amp;c. Et quod utlagem verſus praefat. Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam Brugg revocatur iſto termino &amp; predict. Iohannes Rawleus profelon. &amp; murdo predict. traditur in Ball' prout patet alib. &amp;c, ideo hic Marr, de ejus orbus per cur exoneratur. &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="record">
                     <head>Ter. Hillar. 7. H. 7 &amp; per Cont. ejuſdem Rot. 18.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">7. <hi>H</hi> 7. <hi>Bartho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomewes</hi> caſe <hi>cite devant.</hi> 34.</note> W. Bartholomew, Iohanes Bartholomew, Willielmus Chace, Henr. Carr, Tho. Roteſley, Tho. Street, Robertns Feldone, &amp; Henr. Bancks ſunt in cuſtod. Marr, ad cuſt. mandat. Dom. Regis, &amp;c, per recept. iſtius termin, ac predict. Willielmus Chace pro pace Randulpho Joſſelen inveniend &amp;c. Paſche ſequen, pet, poſtea Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min. ſequen, dictus Dominus Rex mandatum ſuum predict. quo ad Willielmus Chace relaxavit per Regis Attornat. &amp; pro pace &amp; pro felon. &amp; murdro traditur in Ball.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="record">
                     <head>De ter. Pas. 7. H. 7. &amp; per Cont. Rot. ejuſdem 18.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">7. <hi>H.</hi> 7. <hi>Beo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds</hi> caſe <hi>cite devant. fo.</hi> 34.</note> Iohannes Beomond de Weddesbury in Com' Staff. Ar' eſt in cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtod. Mar' ad mandatum Dom. Regis, &amp;c. per record. iſtius ter' poſtea ſcilicet Trin' 7. H. 7. ſe quen' predict. Iohannes Beomond de mandato predict. exoneratus exiſtit Ideo Marr' de eo per ean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem Cur' exoneratus exiſt.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="record">
                     <head>De ter' M. Anno 12. H. 7. Rot. 8.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">12. <hi>H</hi> 7. <hi>Yewes</hi> c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſe <hi>cite devant. fo.</hi> 34.</note> Thomas Yew de villa de Staff. in com' Stafford Yeoman, per Iohannem Shawe &amp; Ricardum Haddon vir' London virtute libris Dom. Regis de habeas corpus, ad Sect. ipſius Regis eis inde direct. coram Rege duct. cum cauſa quod id in Thomas Yew attachiatus
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:54884:32"/> fuit per Ricardum Whittington Serjant apud Baynords Caſtle Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitatis predict. &amp; priſona dicti Dom. Regis infra eandem Civita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem ſalvo cuſtodiend. cauſa pro ſuſpitione felone apud Coventrie in Com' Warr' per petrat. ad Suggeſtionem Willielmi King Inholder, Ac in ſuper idem Tho. Yewe detinetur in priſona predict. virtute cujuſdem alterins querel. verſus ipſum ad Sestam Johannis Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Sergeant de eo quod inveniat. ei in ſufficiaend. Secur. pacis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicta cur. coram Johanne Waiger nuper vic. Ac. ulterius idem Tho. Yewe de tent. eſt indicta priſona pro 23 l. debit. &amp; 2 s. 8 d. dampnis &amp; cuſtag. quos Robertus Corbet Mercer. ex cognicione ipſius defend. verſus eum recuperavit. in eadem Cur. coram eodem Johanne Waiger nuper vic. Ac. etiam idem Tho. detinetur in dicta priſona ad mandatum Domini Regis per Iohannem Shawe Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Civitatis London, Qui Comittitur Marr. &amp;c. poſtea ſcilicet ter' Sct. Trin. Anno 19 Regis H. 7. predict. Iohannes Freeman relaxavit ſecur. pacis verſis eundem Tho. Yewe dictuſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> Robertus Corbet cognovit ſe fore ſatisfact. de debito &amp; dampnis predict. Ac. Iacobus Hubberd Attornat. general. Dom. Regis relaxavit mandatum Dom. Regis Ac. pro ſuſpicione felonie predict. traditur in Ball. Symon. Little de London Tayler &amp; Iohanni Aſhe de Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don Skinner uſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> Octabis Mich. ubicun<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> &amp;c. Ad qui diem com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peruuit &amp; Robertus Throgmorton miles unus cuſtod. pacis predict. com' Warr' return' quod mill. Indictiament. de aliquibus felon' ſive tranſgreſſ. verſus prefat. Tho. Yewe coram eo &amp; Sociis ad pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſens reſidet. &amp; ulter. virtute brevis Dom. Regis ſibi &amp; Sociis ſuis direct. per Sacrament. 12 probor. &amp; legal hominum de villa de Co. venutriepredict. de geſtu &amp; fama predict. Thome diligenter inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicionem fecerunt, &amp; nihil de eo preter bonum coram eo &amp; Sociis ſuis eſt compertum ſed de bono geſtu, &amp; fama ideo conceſſ. eſt quod predict. Tho. eat inde ſine die.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="record">
                     <head>Ter. Hillar. Anno 9. H. 7 &amp; per cont. ejuſdem Roth. 14.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">9. <hi>H.</hi> 7 <hi>Broch's caſe cite d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>vant. fo.</hi> 34.</note> Humfridus Broche nuper de Canterbrig in Cantabr. Scholler: per Robertum Willoughbie Dom' Brooke mil. Seneſcall. Hoſpitii Dom. Regis ac Iohannem Digbie mil. Marr' cur' Marr' Hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tii predict' virtute cujuſdem brevis Dom. Regis de habeas corpus ad Sectam ipſius Regis ad ſtand. rect', &amp;c. ad ſect. partis utlag. eis inde direct. coram Rege duct. cum cauſa vizt. quod
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:54884:32"/> idem Humfridus Commiſſus fuit Gaol. Marr' Hoſpitij Dom. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis &amp; hac de cauſa &amp; non alia idem Humfridus in priſonae pred. detinetur qui committitur Marr', &amp;c. poſteo Paſ. ſequen' Rex relinquit mandatum ſuum Capital. Iuſticiar' per Tho. Lovett mil. oſten' &amp; pro utlag. pred. traditur in Ball. prout patet alibi.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="record">
                     <head>De Ter' Scte. Trinit' anno 39 El. &amp; per cont. Rotli. ejuſdem 113.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">39. <hi>El. Broome caſe cite devant. fo.</hi> 35.</note> Lawrence Broome per Hugonem Parlour cuſtod, priſone Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine Regine de le Gatehouſe virtute brevis Domine Regine de ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beas corpus ad ſubiiciend. &amp;c. ei inde direct. &amp; coram Domina Regina apud Weſtminſt' duct. cum cauſa vizt. quod predict. Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence Broome in arcta cuſtod. ſua remanſet per mandatum duo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum de Conſilio dicte Domine Regine pro certis cauſis eos moven' qui committitur Marr' &amp; poſtea iſte eodem termino traditur in Ball. pro ut patet, &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="record">
                     <head>Per Scruect. Fin. Ter' Sct. Trin. anno 39. El. Regine.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Eſſex.</note> Lawrencius Broome de parva Baddow in Com. pred. husband. traditur in B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ll' ad ſubiiciend, &amp;c. ad mandat. privat. Conſil. Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine Regine ſuper habe as corpus.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Vſ<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> octabis Mich.</hi>
                        </note> Verſus Rando. Mayall de Hatfield Beverell in Com' pred' gener.</p>
                     <p>Verſus Henrico Odall de eadem Gent.</p>
                     <p>Verſus Will. Eekaſden de Weſminſt' Bricklayer.</p>
                     <p>Verſus Rica. Morgan de Weſtminst' Labourer.</p>
                     <p>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ter<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ſub pena 40 l. et princeps ſub pena 100 morcarum.</p>
                     <p>Pro ſuſpitione proditionis cum Johanne Smith mil.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="record">
                     <head>De Ter' Sct' Michaelis anno 4 El. &amp; per cont: Rot. ejuſdem Rot. 37.</head>
                     <p>Tho. Wenden per Hugonem Parlour gen' cuſtod. priſone Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine Regine de ie Gatehouſe virtute brevis Domine Regine de Habeas corpus ad Subiiciend. &amp;c. ei inde direct' et coram Domina Regina apud Weſtm' duct. cum cauſa vizt. ad 18 die Junii Anno Regini Domine El. nunc Regine Anglie 38 corpus &amp;c. infra no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minat. Tho. Wenden extra cur' ejuſdem Domine Regine coram ipſa Domina Regina privati Conſilii Dom. Regis civitatis tenor ſequitur in hec verba ſcilicet. <hi>Theſe are to wil &amp; require you to
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:54884:33"/> receive into your charge and cuſtody, the perſon of <hi>Iohn Brocket</hi> Knight, and him to retaine in ſafe keeping under your charge, untill you ſhall have further order for his inlargement, whoſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitment being forſome ſpecial matter concerning the ſervice of our Soveraigne Lord the King, you may not faile to regard this Warrant accordingly. From the Kings Pallace at White-Hall the laſt of March 1605.</hi> Ea<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> fuit cauſa detentionis pred. Johannis in priſona pred. qui committitur Marr. &amp;c. &amp; poſtea traditur in Ball' prout patet, &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="record">
                     <head>Ter' Mic-Anno 12. Jac. Regis Rot. 119.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">12. <hi>Ia. Rayners Caſe cite devent fo.</hi> 35.</note> Milo Reyner per Aquilam Wykes Cuſtod. priſone de le Gate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe, virtute brevis Dom, Regis de Habeas corpus ad Subijci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>end. &amp;c. coram Domino Rege duct. cum cauſa vizt. quod ante ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent brevis pred. ſcilt. 10. Iuly Anno Dom. 1613. pred. Milo Reyner comiſſus fuit priſona pred' &amp; huc uſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> detent. virtute Warr' cujuſdem fact, &amp; direct. per Georgium Archiepiſcopum Cant. Henr. Com. Northampton, Tho. Com. Saffolke. Willielm. Dom. Knolles, Edwardum dom, Wooton, &amp; Edwardum dom, Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hope cuius Warranti tenor ſequitur in hec verba. <hi>To <hi>Aquila Wykes,</hi> Keeper of the Gate-houſe in <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> or his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putie, whereas it is thought meet that <hi>Miles Reyner</hi> and <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Beckwith,</hi> be reſtrained of their libertie, and committed to the priſon of the Gate-houſe. Theſe ſhall bee to will and require you, to receive the perſons of <hi>Rayner &amp; Beckwith</hi> into your charge and keeping, untill you ſhall have further order from us in that behalfe, for which this ſhall be your ſufficient warrant, Dated at <hi>White-Hall</hi> the 10. of July 1613.</hi> Et haec eſt cauſa detentionis ſue in priſona pred. Qui comittitur Marr' &amp;c. Et poſtea iſto eodemter' traditur in Ball' prout patet. &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="record">
                     <head>Ter. Hill 5. H. 7. &amp; per cont' ejuſdem, Rot. 18.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">5. <hi>H</hi> 7. <hi>Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rards Caſe cite devunt, fo.</hi> 35.</note> Ricus Everard imper de Colcheſter in Com. Eſſex clericus, &amp; Robertus Wight nuper de Norwico Smith per Robertum Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loughbie mil' Dom. de Brooke Seneſchall' Hoſpicij Dom. Regis, &amp; Iohannem Turbervile mil. Marr. Hoſpicij pred. virtute bre, de Habeas Corpus ad Sectam ipſius Regis pro quibuſdam prodicio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus, &amp; felon' unde indicto Com. Eſſex indictat ſunt eis inde
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:54884:33"/> Direct. Coram Domine Rege duct cum cauſa, vizt. quod ijdem Ricardus Everard &amp; Robertus Wight Commiſſ. fuer' cuſtod. Marr. Marr. pred. per mandat. Dom. Regis Qui committitur Marr. &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="record">
                     <head>Ter. Hill 8. H. 7. et percont. ejuſdem, Rot. 13.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Berckſſ.</hi> 8. <hi>H.</hi> 7. <hi>Cherries caſe cite devant fo.</hi> 43.</note> Roger Cherrie nuper de nova Windſor in Com pred. Yeoman alias dict. Rogerus Stearries nuper de eadem in eodem Com. Yeom. per lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>han. Baker Majorem villae Dom. Regis de nova Windſor in Com. pred. virtute brevis Dom. Regis de Habeas Corpus ad Sect. ipſius Regis pro quibuſdam felonijs &amp; iranſgr. unde in Com. Midd. in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictatus eſt' ſibi inde direct. coram Domino Rege duct. cum cauſa, vizt. quod idem Roger' commiſſus fuit Gaol. Dom. Regis infra villa. pred. per mandat. Dom. Regis Qui committitur Marr. &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="record">
                     <head>Ter. Hillar. 9. H. 7 &amp; per Cont. ejuſdem Rot. 14.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">9. <hi>H.</hi> 7. <hi>Burtons Caſe cite de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, fo.</hi> 44. <hi>Surr.ſſ.</hi>
                        </note> Chriſtopherus Burton nuper de Rocheſter in Com' Cancij Hack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neyman per Robertum Willoughbie Dom. Brooke mil' Seneſchall' Hoſpitij Dom. Rogis, &amp; Iohannem Digbie mil' Marr. cur. Mar. Hoſpitij pred. per mandatum Dom. Regis. Et hac eſt cauſa &amp; non alia. Qui committitur Marr. &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="record">
                     <head>Ter. Paſ Anno 19. H. 7. &amp; per Cont. ejuſdem. Rot. 23.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">9 <hi>H.</hi> 7. <hi>Vrmſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wicks Caſe cite devant, fo.</hi> 44.</note> Georgius <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rmeſwicke de London Mereer, per Oliverum Wood locum tenen priſonae Dom. Regis de le Fleet virtute brevis Dom. Regis de conſervand. diem, &amp;c. eiinde direct. coram rege duct. cum cauſa vizt. quod idem Georgius 13. Maij Anno 19. Regis com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſus fuit priſonae del Fleet per mandatum ipſius Dom. Regis ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocuſtodiend. Sub pena 40. <hi rend="sup">l,</hi> qui committitur Marr. &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="record">
                     <head>Ter. Trin. Anno 8. H. 8 per cont. ejuſdem, Rot. 23.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">8. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>Pages caſe cite devant, fo.</hi> 45.</note> Edwardus Page nuper de London Gent. per Georgium Com. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lopiae Seneſchall. Hoſpitij Dom. Regis, &amp; Henericum Shamburne, Marr. cur. Mar. Hoſpitij pred. virtute brevis Dom. Regis de Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beas corpus ad Sect. ipſius Regis ad conſervand, diem. &amp;c. eis inde direct. &amp; coram Rege duct. cum cauſa, vizt. quod idem Edwardus Captus &amp; detentus in priſona Regis Marr. pred. per mandatum Dom. Regis ihidem ſalvo Cuſtodiend. &amp;c. Qui committitur Marr. Hoſpitij Dom. Regic.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="record">
                     <pb n="64" facs="tcp:54884:34"/>
                     <head>Ter. Mich. Anno 8. Jac. Et per cont. ejuſdem Rot. 99.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">8 <hi>Iac. Caeſars caſe cite devant fo.</hi> 46.</note> Tho. Caſar per Tho. Vaviſour mil' Marr. Hoſpitij Dom. Regis &amp; Marr. Marr. ejuſdem Hoſpitij Dom. Regis, virtute brevis Domini Regis de Habeas corpus ad ſubijciend. &amp;c. ci inde direct, &amp; coram Rege apud Weſtminſt. duct. cum cauſa, vizt. quod ante adventum brevis pred. ſcil. 18. Julij Anno Regni dicti Dom. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis nunc Angliae, &amp;c. 7. Tho. Caeſar in brevi pred. nominat. Captus fuit apud White-Hall in Com' Middl. per ſpeciale mandatum Dom. Regis ac per eundem Regem ad tunc &amp; ibidem Commiſſ. fuit priſon. Marr. ibidem ſalvo Cuſtodiend. quouſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> &amp;c. Et ea fuit cauſa captionis &amp; detentionis ejuſdem Tho. Caeſar Qui comitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur priſonae Marr. pred.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="record">
                     <head>Ter. Sancti Mich. 8. Jac Regis.</head>
                     <p>Niſi pred. Seneſchall &amp; Marr. Hoſpitii Dom. Regis ſufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter return' bre. de Habeas Corpus Tho. Caeſar die Mercur. per quinden. Sanct. Martini defendens exonerabitur.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="record">
                     <head>Ter Hill. 12. Jac. Rot. 153.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Marr' Hoſpitii Regis</hi> 12. <hi>Iac E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merſons caſe cite devant. fo.</hi> 46.</note> Iacobus Demaiſtres, Edwardus Emerſon, Georgius Brookeſhall &amp; W. Steephens per Tho. Vaviſour mil' Marr. Marr. Hoſpitij Regis virtute bre. Dom. Regis de Habeas corpus ad ſubijciend. &amp;c. ei in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de direct. coram domino Rege apud Woſtminſt. duct. cum cauſa, vizt. quod ante adventum brevis pred. ſcilt. 22. Ianuar. Anno Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis Iacobi Angliae, &amp;c. 12. &amp; Scot. 48. pred. Iacobus Demaiſtres, Edwardus Emerſon, Gregorius Brookeſhall, &amp; W. Steephens in brovi. huic Schedul' annex, nominat, Commiſſ. fuer' Gaol' Marr. Hoſpitij Dom. Regis pro cauſis ipſum Regem &amp; ſervic' ſuum tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen. &amp; concernen. Et hac eſt cauſa Captionis pred. Iacobi, Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardi, Georgij &amp; Willielmi, &amp; postea immediate remittitur prafat. Marr. Hoſpitij pred.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="record">
                     <head>Ter. Hill. 12. Jac. Regis.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Priſon de le Fleet Sir Samu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el Saltonſtalls caſe cite devant fo.</hi> 49.</note> Samuel Saltonſtall miles per Johannem Wilkinſon Ar. guard. de le Fleete virtute brevis Dom. Regis de Habeas Corpus ad ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ijciend. &amp;c. ei inde direct. &amp; coram Domino Rege apud Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſt. duct. cum cauſa vizt. quod pred, Samuel commiſſ. fuit pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonae pred. 11. Martij 1608. per Warrant. a Dominis de privato conſilio Dom. Regis &amp; quod detentus ſuit etiam idem Samuel in priſona pred virtute cujuſdem ordinis in cur. Canc' Dom. Regis fact. cujus ordinis tenor patet per Rot. Record. iſtius Termini ad
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:54884:34"/> quem diem pred. Samuel remittitur priſonae pred. Et ſecundus dies prox. ter' datus eſt guardian. priſonae pred. ad emendand. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn. ſuum ſufficien. ſuper pred. bre. de Habeas Corpus, Et quod tunc intulerit hic in cur. corpus pred. Samuel Saltonstall mil'. Ad quam quidem diem prefat. Guardian. priſonae pred. ſuper pred. bre. de Habeas Corpus retorn. quod pred. Samuel co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſus fuit pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonae pred. 11. die Martii 1608 per Warrant. a Dom. de privat' Concil. dicti Dom. Regis apud Whitehal tunc Seden. &amp; quod poſtea 11. die Febr. 1610. commiſſ. fuit extra cur. Canc. Dom. Regis apud Weſtminſt. pro contemptu ſuo eidem cur. illat. Et quod detent. fuit etiam idem Samuel in priſona pred. per mandat. Dom. Cancellar' Anglia ſuper quo pred. Samuel' iterum remittitur priſonae pred. &amp; ulterius dies dat' eſt prefat. Gardian. ad emendend. return. ſuum ſuper Habeas corpus ver. deftom prout ſtare voluit uſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> diem Iovis prox' Menſ. Paſch. Et tunc ad Habend. Corpus, &amp;c. Ad quam diem prefat. guardian. intulit corpus hic in cur. &amp; retorn' ſuper Habeas corpus quod pred. Samuel' Commiſſ. fuit priſonae pred. 11. die Martii 1608. virtute cujuſdem Warranti a Dominis de privato Concil' Dom. Regis tunc ſeden. apud White-Hall, Et quod etiam idem Sam. Commiſſ. fuit. priſonae 11. Febr. Anno Regis Jac. 8. per cur. Canc. Dom. Regis apud Weſtminſt. tunc exiſten. pro quadam contempt. per eundem Samuel eidem cur. illat. &amp; perpetrat. proinde ſalvo cuſtodiend. qui remittitur priſonae pred.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="record">
                     <head>Ter. Tr. Anno 13. Jac. &amp; per cont. ejuſdem Rot. 17.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">13 <hi>Ia. Sir Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel Saltonſtals caſe cite devant, fo.</hi> 49.</note> Samuel Saltonſtall miles per Iohannem Wilkinſon Guardian. priſonae de le Fleet virtute brevis Dom. Regis de Habeas Corpus ad Subiiciend. et recipiend. &amp;c. eiinde direct. &amp; cora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Domino Rege apud Weſtminſt. duct. cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cauſa vizt. quod pred. Samuel. Saltonſtall commiſſus fuit priſonae pred. 12. die Martii Anno Regis Iacob. Angliae, &amp;c. ſexto virtute cujuſdam Warrant. a dominis de privat. Conſilio Dom Regis tunc ſeden. apud White-Hall commiſſus fuit etiamidem Samuel Saltonſtall miles priſonae pred. 12. die Febr. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no 1610. &amp; Anno Reg. Iac. Angliae, &amp;c. 8. per conſiderat. cur. Cancell' dicti Dom. Regis apud Weſtminſt. pro contempt. eidem cur. ad tunc per pred. Samuel illat, ibidem proinde Salvo cuſtodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>end. Et haec ſunt cauſae captionis &amp; detentionis pred. Sam Salton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtall mil. in priſona pred. cujus tamen corpus ad diem &amp; locum infra content. parat. habeo prout mihi precipitur.</p>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>Finis d' les Preſidents.</trailer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="Cooke" type="part">
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:54884:35"/>
               <head>Sir <hi>Edward Cookes</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument.</head>
               <head>Iovis 3. Apr. 4. Caroli Regis.</head>
               <div type="argument">
                  <p n="1">1. <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Eſolved upon the queſtion, that no Free-man ought to be deteined or kept in priſon, or other wiſe reſtrained by the command of the King, or the Privie Counſell, or any other, unleſſe ſome cauſe of the commitment detey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner or reſtraint bee expreſſed, for which by Law he ought to be committed, deteyned or reſtrained.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That the Writ of Habeas Corpus may not bee denied, but ought to be granted to every man that is committed or deteyned in priſon, or otherwiſe reſtrained, though it be by the command of the King, the Privie Counſell or any other, hee praying the ſame.</p>
                  <p>That if a Free-man be committed or deteyned in priſon or otherwiſe reſtrained by the Command of the King, the Privie Counſell, or any other, no cauſe of ſuch commitment, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyner or reſtraint being expreſſed, for which by Law he ought to be committed, deteyned or reſtrained, and the ſame be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned upon a Habeas Corpus granted for the ſaid party, then he ought to be delivered or bayled. All theſe without one nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, that theſe Acts of Parliament, and theſe Judiciall preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents in affirmance thereof (recited by my Colleagues) are but declarations of the fundamentall lawes of this Kingdome I ſhall prove by manifeſt and legall reaſons which are the grounds and mothers of all lawes,</p>
                  <div n="1" type="reason">
                     <head>The firſt generall reaſon.</head>
                     <p>1. The firſt generall reaſon is drawne <hi>are ipſa,</hi> from impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment, <hi>ex viſceribus cauſae,</hi> be it thoſe or other impriſonments, which is divided into three parts.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. Firſt, no man can be impriſoned at the will and pleaſure of any but he that is bond, and a villaine, for that impriſonment at will is <hi>tailes luy haut, &amp; baſe,</hi> are <hi>propria quarto modo</hi> to vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laines.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. But if Free-men of <hi>England</hi> might be impriſoned at the wil and pleaſure of the King by his commandment, then were they in worſe caſe then bond-men &amp; villaines for the lord of a vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain cannot command another to impriſon his villain without
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:54884:35"/> cauſe, as of diſobedience, or refuſing to ſerve, as it is agreed in our Bookes.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Impriſonment is accounted in law a civil death, <hi>perdit do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum, familiam, vicinos, patriam,</hi> his houſe, is family, his wife, his children his neighbours, his Country, and to live among wretched wicked men.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">39 <hi>H.</hi> 6. <hi>fo.</hi> 50. <hi>&amp;</hi> 41. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. 9.</note> If a man be threatned to be killed, he may avoid a feoffment of lands, gift of goods, &amp;c. So it is, if he be threatned to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned, he ſhall doe the like, for that is a civill death.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="reason">
                     <head>The ſecond generall reaſon.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Bracton</hi> 105. <hi>fo.</hi> 15.</note> The ſecond generall reaſon is a <hi>Minore ad majus; paena corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralis eſt majus qualibet pecuniaria,</hi> but the King himſelfe can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not impoſe a fine upon any man, but it muſt be done juditially by his Judges, <hi>per Iuſticiar' in Cur' non per Regem in Camera,</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">2. <hi>R.</hi> 3. 11.</note> and ſo it hath beene reſolved by all the Judges of England.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="reason">
                     <head>The third generall reaſon.</head>
                     <p>The third generall reaſon is drawne from the number and diverſity of remedies, which the law giveth againſt impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>vizt. brevia de Homine replegiande de odio &amp; Atia de habeas corpus &amp; bre. de manucaptiene.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The two former of theſe are antiquated, but the writ <hi>de odio &amp; Atia</hi> is revived, for that was given by the Sat. of <hi>Magna Car' cap.</hi> 26. and therefore though it were repealed by the Stat. of 28. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3 <hi>ca</hi> 9. yet it is revived by the Stat. of 43. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. by which it is provided, that all Statutes made againſt <hi>Magna Charta</hi> are void, now the law would never have given ſo many remedies, if the Freemen of England might have beene impriſoned at Free will and pleaſure.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="reason">
                     <head>The fourth generall reaſon.</head>
                     <p>The fourth generall reaſon is drawne from the extent &amp; uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſality of the pretended power to impriſon, for it ſhould not extend onely to the Commons of the Realme and their poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity but to the Nobility and their Honourable Progenies, to the Biſhops and Clergie of the Realme and their Succeſſours; to all perſons of what condition, or ſex, or age ſo ever: to all Judges, Officers, &amp;c. whoſe attendance are neceſſary without exception of any perſon.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="reason">
                     <pb n="68" facs="tcp:54884:36"/>
                     <head>The fifth generall reaſon.</head>
                     <p>The fifth generall reaſon is drawne from the indefiniteneſſe of time, the pretended power being limited to no time, it may be perpetuall during life.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="reason">
                     <head>The ſixth generall reaſon.</head>
                     <p>The ſixth generall reaſon is drawne a <hi>dedecore</hi> from the loſſe and diſhonour of the Engliſh nation, in two reſpects. 1. For their valour and power ſo famous through the whole world. 2. For their induſtry; for who will endeavour to imploy him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in any profeſſion, either of Warre, liberall Science, or Merchandize, if he be but tennant at will of his liberty, and no tennant at will, will ſupport or improve any thing, becauſe he hath no certaine eſtate; and thus it ſhould be both <hi>dedecus</hi> and <hi>damnum</hi> to the Engliſh nation, and it ſhould be no honour to the King to be King of a ſlaves.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="reason">
                     <head>The ſeventh generall reaſon.</head>
                     <p>The ſeventh generall reaſon is drawne <hi>ab utili et inutili,</hi> for that appeareth by the Stat. of 36 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. that the execution of the Statute of <hi>Magna Charta</hi> 5. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. 25. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 28. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3: are adjudged in Parliament to be for the common profit of the King, and of his people, and therefore the pretended power being againſt the profit of the King, and of his people, can be no part of his prerogative.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="reason">
                     <head>The eighth generall reaſon.</head>
                     <p>The eighth generall reaſon is drawne a <hi>tuto,</hi> for it is ſafe for the King to expreſſe the Cauſe of the Commitment, and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous for him to omit it, for if any be committed without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing of the Cauſe, though hee eſcape, albeit the truth be, it were for treaſon or felony, yet the eſcape is neither felony nor treaſon; but if the cauſe be expreſſed to be for ſuſpition of trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or felony, then if he eſcape, albeit he be innocent, it is trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or felony.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="reason">
                     <head>The laſt generall reaſon.</head>
                     <p>The laſt generall reaſon is drawne from authorities.</p>
                     <p>16. <hi>H.</hi> 6. <hi>Means de fait</hi> 182. by the whole Court, the King in his preſence cannot command one to be arreſted, but an action of falſe impriſonment lies againſt him that arreſteth.</p>
                     <p>22. <hi>H.</hi> 7. 4. <hi>Newton.</hi> 1 <hi>H.</hi> 7. 4. The opinion of <hi>Markham</hi> chiefe Juſtice to <hi>Ed.</hi> 4. And the reaſon becauſe the party hath
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:54884:36"/> no remedy. <hi>Forteſcue cap.</hi> 8. <hi>Proprio <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>re nullus regum uſus eſt, &amp;c.</hi> to commit any man.</p>
                     <p>4. <hi>El. Plo. Com.</hi> 236. The Common Law hath ſo admeaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Kings Prerogative, as he cannot prejudice any man in his inheritance, and the greateſt inheritance a man hath, is the liberty of his perſon, for all others are acceſſary to it. <hi>Cicere. Major haeredidas venit unicui<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> noſtrum a legibus quam a paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus,</hi> 25. <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. All judgements given againſt <hi>Magna Charta</hi> are void.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="objections">
                  <head>Vpon conference with the Lords, theſe objections were made by the Kings Attorney.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="objection">
                     <head>The firſt objection.</head>
                     <p>
                        <label>1</label> That the reſolutions of the Houſe of Commons were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compatible with a Monarch that muſt governe by rule of State.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <abbr>Rns</abbr>.</note> Whereunto it was anſwered, <hi>Quod nihil tam propr' eſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perii quam legibus vivere.</hi> And againe, <hi>Attribuat Rex legi quod lex attribuat ei vizt. dominationem &amp; imperium quia ſine lege non poteſt eſſe Rex.</hi> It can be no prejudice to the King by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of matter of State: for if it be for ſuſpition of treaſon, miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſion of treaſon, or felony, it may be by generall words ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, <hi>vizt. pro ſuſpitione proditionis,</hi> &amp;c. If it be for any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, or any other thing, the particular cauſe muſt be ſhewed.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="objection">
                     <head>The ſecond objection.</head>
                     <p>
                        <label>2</label> To blinde thoſe that are committed, one cauſe muſt be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, and another intended, eſpecially when it toucheth matter of State.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <abbr>Rns</abbr>.</note> Whereunto it was anſwered, that all diſſimulation, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in a cauſe of Juſtice, was to be avoided, and ſoundneſſe of truth to take place. And therefore <hi>David</hi> that was both a King and a Prophet, prayed unto Almighty God againſt diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation, in theſe words, Lord ſend me a ſound heart in thy Statutes, that I be not aſhamed: where found in the originall ſignifieth upright without diſſimulation, and ſhame followes diſſimulation when the truth is knowne.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="objection">
                     <head>The third objection.</head>
                     <p>
                        <label>3</label> If a Rebell be attainted in Ireland, and his children for
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:54884:37"/> ſafety, and matter of State be kept in the Tower, what ſhall be returned upon the <hi>habeat corpus?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <abbr>Rns</abbr>.</note> Whereunto it was anſwered, that their impriſonment might be juſtified, if they could not find good ſureties for their good behaviour. 2. It was charity to finde them meat, drink, and cloath, that by the Attainder of their Father had nothing.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="objection">
                     <head>The fourth objection.</head>
                     <p>
                        <label>4</label> Though his Majeſtie expreſſeth no cauſe, yet it muſt be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended there was a juſt cauſe.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <abbr>Rns</abbr>.</note>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Bracton</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Fleta</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list> Anſwere <hi>De non apparentibus &amp; non exiſtentibus eadem ratio.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="objection">
                     <head>The fifth objection.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">25. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 13 <hi>Stat.</hi> 4. <hi>H.</hi> 7. 6.</note> 
                        <label>5</label> The King in ſtead of gold or ſilver, may make money cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of any baſe mettall. 2. He may make warres at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. 3. Hee may pardon whom he will. 4. Hee may make Denizens as many as he will, and theſe were ſaid to be greater prerogatives then theſe in queſtion.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <abbr>Rns</abbr>.</note> Anſwer to the firſt. It was denied that the King might make money Currant of baſe money, but it ought to be of gold or ſilver. 2. It was anſwered admitting that the King might do it, his loſſe and charge was more then of his Subjects, both in the Caſe of money, and in the Caſe of warre; the pardon was pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate, out of grace, and no man had danger or loſſe by it; and ſo the making of Denizens the King was onely the looſer, <hi>vizt.</hi> where hee had double Cuſtomes to have ſingle. 3. It was a <hi>non ſequitur,</hi> the King may doe theſe things, <hi>ergo</hi> hee may im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſon at will.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="conclusion">
                  <p>Your Lordſhips are now adviſed by thoſe that cannot be daunted for feare, nor miſled by affected reward, or hope of preferment, that is of the dead.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <label>1</label> By ancient and many Acts of Parliament in the point be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> which hath beene 30 times confirmed, and commanded to be put in execution, whereto the Kings of England have 30 times given their royall aſſent.</item>
                     <item>
                        <label>2</label> Judiciall Preſidents of grave and reverend Judges in <hi>termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis terminantibus,</hi> that long ſince are departed this world.</item>
                     <item>
                        <label>3</label> And laſtly, <hi>per vividas rationes,</hi> manifeſt and apparent rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</item>
                  </list>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:54884:37"/>
                  <p>Wee of the Houſe of Commons have, upon great Studie and ſerious conſideration, made a great <hi>manifeſto</hi> unanimouſly <hi>nullo contradicente,</hi> concerning this great liberty of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, and have vindicated and recovered the body of this fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentall liberty, both of your Lordſhips, and of our ſelves, from ſhadowes, which ſometimes of the day are long, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſhort, and ſometimes long againe, And therefore no Judges are to be led by them: your Lordſhips are involved in the ſame danger, and therefore <hi>ex congruo &amp; condigno,</hi> Wee deſired a conference, to the end your Lordſhips may make the like declaration, as we have done, <hi>Commune periculum</hi> requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth <hi>commune auxilium,</hi> and thereupon take ſuch further courſe as may ſecure both your Lordſhips, and us, and all your and our poſterities in enjoying our ancient undoubted and fundamentall liberties.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="addendum">
            <pb n="72" facs="tcp:54884:38"/>
            <div n="Heath" type="objections">
               <head>The ſubſtance of the obiections made by M. Attorney Generall, before a Committee of both Houſes, to the Argument that was made by the Houſe of Commons, at the firſt conference with the Lords, out of Preſidents of Record, and reſolutions of the ludges in former times, touching the liberty of the perſon of every Freeman, and the anſwers and replies then preſently made by the Houſe of Commons to thoſe objections.</head>
               <head>M. Attor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neyes objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter the firſt conference which was deſired by the Lords, and had by a Committee of both Houſes in the painted Chamber, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the reaſons, lawes, acts of Parliament, and Preſidents concerning the liberty of the perſon of every Freeman, M. Attorney Generall being heard before a Committee of both Houſes, as it was aſſented by the Houſe of Commons that hee might be, before they went up to the conference, after ſome preamble made, wherein hee declared the anſwering of all reaſons of Law, and Acts of Parliament, came onely to the Preſidents uſed in the Arguments before delivered, and ſo en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devoured to weaken the ſtrength of them that had bin brought on the behalfe of the Subject, to ſhew that ſome were directly contrary to the Law comprehended in the reſolutions of the Houſe of Commons touching the bayling of priſoners returned upon the Writ of <hi>Habeas Corpus</hi> to be committed by the ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall command of the King, or of the Counſell, without any cauſe ſhewed for which they ought by Law to be committed.
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:54884:38"/> And the courſe that was taken (which it pleaſed the Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee of both Houſes to allow of) was that M. Attorney ſhould make his objections to every particular Preſident, and that the Gent. appointed and truſted by the Houſe of Commons by ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall replies ſhould ſatisfie the Lords touching the ſeverall objections made by him againſt or upon every particular, as the order of the Preſidents ſhould lead them. He began with the firſt 12 Preſidents that were uſed by the Houſe of Commons, at the conference deſired by them, to prove that priſoners re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to ſtand ſo committed were delivered by bayle by the Court of Kings Bench.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Objection al <hi>Bildeſtons</hi> Caſe <hi>cite devant. fo.</hi> 35. <hi>&amp;</hi> 55.</note> The firſt was, that of <hi>Bildeſtons</hi> Caſe in 18 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>Rot.</hi> 33. To this he objected, 1. That in thereturne of him into the Court it did not appeare that this <hi>Bildeſton</hi> was committed by the Kings Command. And ſecondly, that in the Record it did appeare alſo that he had beene committed for ſuſpition of counterfet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the great Seal, and ſo by conſequence was bayleable in the Law, in regard there appeared a cauſe why hee was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, in which caſe it was granted by him (as indeed it is plaine and agreed of all hands) that the priſoner is bayleable, though committed by the Command of the King. And he ſaid that this part of Record by which it appeared hee had beene committed for this ſuſpition of treaſon was not obſerved to the Lords in their Argument before uſed. And he ſhewed alſo to the Lords, that there were three ſeverall kinds of Records, by which the full truth of every award or bayling upon a <hi>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beat corpus</hi> is knowne. Firſt, by the remembrance roll where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the award is given. Secondly, the file of the Writ, and the returne. Thirdly, The Scruet Roll or Scruet Finn', wherein the Bayle is entred, and that onely the remembrance roll of this caſe was to be found, and that if the other two of it were extant, he doubted not but that it would appeare alſo, that up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the returne it ſelfe the cauſe of the commitment had beene expreſſed, and ſo he concluded that this proved not for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of the Houſe of Commons touching the matter of Baile, where a priſoner was committed by the Kings command without cauſe ſhewed.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <abbr>Rns</abbr> al dit obj.</note> To theſe objections the reply was firſt, that it was plaine,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:54884:39"/> that <hi>Bildeſton</hi> was committed by the Kings expreſſe command, for ſo are the very words of the Writ to the Conſtable of the Tower, <hi>quod cum teneri &amp; cuſtodiri facias, &amp;c.</hi> then which no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can more fully expreſſe a commitment by the Kings command. Secondly, how ever it be true, that in the latter part of the Record it doe appeare, that <hi>Bildeſton</hi> had beene committed for a ſuſpition of treaſon, Yet if the time of the proceeding expreſſed in the Record were obſerved, it would be plaine, that the objection was of no force: for this one ground both of this one caſe, and all the reſt, is infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible, and never to be doubted of in the Law, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Regula.</hi>
                  </note> That the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices of every Court adjudge of the force and ſtrength of a returne out of the body of it ſelfe onely, and according as therein appeares to them. Now in Eaſter Terme 18 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. he was returned and brought before them onely as committed by the Writ, wherein No cauſe is expreſſed, and the Lievte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of the Conſtable of the Tower that brought him into the Court, ſaid, that he had no other warrant to detaine him <hi>niſi bre. predict.</hi> wherein there was no mention of any Cauſe, And the Court thereupon adjudged, that <hi>bre. predict.</hi> or that ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all command was not ſufficient cauſe to detaine him in priſon, and thereupon he is by judgement of the Court in Eaſter Term let to mainpriſe, but that part of the Record, wherein it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares, that he had indeed beene committed for ſuſpition of treaſon, is of Trinity Terme following, when the King, after letting him to mainpriſe, becauſe no man, proſecuted him. And at that time it appeares, but not before, he had been in for ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpition of treaſon, ſo that he was returned to be committed by the Kings ſpeciall command onely, without any cauſe ſhewed in Eaſter Terme, and then by judgement of the Court let to mainpriſe, which to this purpoſe is but the ſame with bayle, though otherwiſe it differ. And in the Terme following, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on another occaſion, the Court knew that he was committed for ſuſpition of treaſon, which hath no relation at all to the letting him to mainpriſe, nor to the judgement of the Court then given, when they did not, nor could not poſſibly know any cauſe for which the King had committed him, and it was ſaid in the behalfe of the Houſe of Commons, that they had
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:54884:39"/> not indeed in their Argument expreſſely uſed the latter part of the Record of <hi>Bildestons</hi> Caſe, becauſe it being only of Trinitie terme following, it could not concerne the reaſons of an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward given by the court in Eaſter terme next before, yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding that they had moſt faithfully at the time of their Argument delivered unto the Lords (as indeed they had) a perfect Copie at large of the whole record of this Caſe, as they had alſo done of all other Preſidents whatſoever cited by them, inſomuch as intruth there was not one preſident of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord of either ſide, the Copie whereof they had not delivered in likewiſe, nor did Maſter Attorney mention any one beſides thoſe that were ſo delivered in by them. And as touching the three kinds of Records, the remembrance Rolle, the returne and the file of the Writ, and the Scruet, it was anſwered by the Gent. imployed by the houſe of Commons, that it was true the Scruet and returne of this caſe of <hi>Bildeſtons</hi> was not to be found, but that did not leſſen the weight of the preſident, becauſe alwayes in the award or Judgement drawne up in the remembrance Rolle, the cauſe whatſoever it be, when any, is ſhewed, appeares clearely by the conſtant Entrees of the Court of Kings Bench; So as if any cauſe had appeared unto the Court it muſt have appeared plainly in that part of the Roll which belongs to Eaſter terme wherein the Judgement was given, but the returne of the commitment by the Kings command without cauſe ſhewed, and the Judgement of the Court, that the priſoner was to be let to mainpriſe appeare therein only. And ſo, notwithſtanding any objection made by Maſter Attor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, the Cauſe was maintained to be cleare proofe among ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others touching that reſolution of the Houſe of Commons.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Objections Hors de Parkers caſe</hi> 22. <hi>H</hi> 8 <hi>cite an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, fo</hi> 35 <hi>et.</hi> 55.</note> To the ſecond of thoſe 12. which is <hi>Parkers</hi> Caſe in 22. H. 8 <hi>rot.</hi> 37. his Objections were two, firſt, that this is true that he was returned that he was committed <hi>per mandatum Dom. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis,</hi> but that it appeared that this command was certified to the Sherifes of London by one <hi>Robert Pecke,</hi> and that in regard the command came no otherwiſe, the returne was held in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficient, and therefore he was bayled. Secondly, that it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares alſo in the record, that he was committed <hi>pro ſuſpitione feloniae ac per mandatum Dom Regis;</hi> So that in regard the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:54884:40"/> of the cauſe of his commitment ſuſpition of felonie precedes the command of the King, therefore it muſt be inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that the Court tooke the cauſe why the King committed him to be of leſſe moment then felonie, and therefore bayled him; For he objected that even the houſe of Commons them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in ſome Arguments uſed by them touching the interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the Statute of <hi>Weſtminſt.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 15. about this point had affirmed, that in enumeration of particulars thoſe of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt nature were firſt mentioned, and that it was ſuppoſed that ſuch as followed were of leſſe nature or moment.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <abbr>Rns</abbr> al dit ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection.</note> But the reply was to the firſt objection, that the addition of certifying of the Kings command by <hi>Robert Pecke</hi> altered not the caſe, firſt, becauſe the Sherifes in their returnes tooke notice of the command, as what they were aſſured of, and then how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it came to them, it was of equall force as if it had beene mentioned without reference to <hi>Pecke.</hi> Secondly, that as di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Pattents paſſe the great Seale by Writ of privie Seale, and are ſubſcribed <hi>per bre. de privato Sigillo,</hi> ſo divers <hi>per ipſum Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem</hi> &amp; are ſo ſubſcribed, and oftentimes in the Rolles of former times to the words <hi>per ipſum Regem</hi> are added <hi>Nuntians</hi> A. B. So that the Kings Command generall, and the Kings command related and certified by ſuch a man, is to this purpoſe of like nature. Thirdly, in the late great Caſe of <hi>Habeas Corpus,</hi> where the returne of the commitment was <hi>per ſpeciale man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datum Dom. Regis mihi ſignificat. per Dominos de privato conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio,</hi> and the Court of the Kings Bench did agree that it was the ſame, and of the like force, as if <hi>mihi ſignificat. &amp;c.</hi> had not followed, and that theſe words were void, according where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto here alſo <hi>per mandat. Dom. Regis nunciat. per Robertu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Pecke</hi> had bin wholly omitted and void likewiſe; in truth in that late Caſe this caſe of <hi>Parker</hi> was cited both at the Bar, and at the Bench, and at the Bench it was interpreted by the Judges no otherwiſe then if it had beene only <hi>per mandatum Dom. Regis</hi> in this place of it. But the objection there was made of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kind, as was delivered in the firſt Argument made out of Preſidents in behalfe of the houſe of Commons. Then for the ſecond objection touching the courſe of enumeration of the cauſes in the returne, it was ſaid, that however in ſome acts
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:54884:40"/> of Parliament, and elſe-where in the ſolemne expreſſion uſed in the Law, things of greater nature precede, and the leſſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, Yet in this caſe the contrary was moſt plaine, for in the return there appeares, that there were three cauſes of deteyning the priſoner, ſurety of the peace, ſuſpition of felonie, and the Kings command, and ſuretie of the peace is firſt mentioned, which is plainly leſſe then felonie, therefore it is as plaine, that (if any force of Argument be here to be taken from this enu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meration) the contrary to that which Maſter Attorney inferred is to be concluded, that is, that as felonie is a greater cauſe then Suretie of the Peace, ſo the matter whereupon the Kings command was grounded, was greater then the felonie. But in truth this kind of Argument holds neither way here. And whatſoever the cauſe were why the King committed him, it was impoſſible for the Court to know it, And might alſo have been of very high moment in matter of State, and yet of farre leſſe nature then felonie, all which ſhewes that this Preſident hath its full force alſo, according as it was firſt uſed in Argument by the houſe of Commons.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">35. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>Bincks caſe cite ante</hi> 36. <hi>&amp;</hi> 56 <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections hors de ceo.</hi>
                  </note> To the third of theſe, which is <hi>Bincks</hi> Caſe in 35. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>Rot.</hi> 35. the Objection was, that there was cauſe expreſſed, <hi>pro ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpitione feloniae,</hi> and though <hi>pro alijs cauſis illos moventibus</hi> were added in the returne, yet becauſe in the courſe of enumeration the generall name of <hi>alia</hi> comming after particulars includes things of leſſe nature then the particular doth, therefore in the Caſe ſuſpition of felonie being the firſt, the other cauſes ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally mentioned muſt be intended of leſſe nature for which the priſoner was bay leable for the greater which was ſuſpiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of felonie.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <abbr>Rns</abbr> al dit ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection.</note> Hereunto it was replied that the Argument of enumerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on in theſe caſes is of no moment, and is next before ſhewed, and that although it were of any moment, yet the <hi>aliae cauſae,</hi> though leſſe then felonie, might be of very great conſequence in matter of State, which is pretended uſually upon generall returnes of command without cauſe ſhewed. And it is moſt plaine that the Court could not poſſibly know the reaſons why the priſoner here was committed, and yet they bay led him without looking further after any unknowne thing under that
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:54884:41"/> tytle of matter of State, which might as well have been in this Caſe, as in any other whatſoever.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3. <hi>P. &amp; M. Overtons</hi> caſe, <hi>Et</hi> 4. <hi>et.</hi> 5. <hi>P. &amp; M. Newports caſe cite ante, fo.</hi> 36. <hi>et</hi> 37. <hi>Et les objections la <abbr>rnde</abbr> le Record de ceux, vide an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te fo.</hi> 37. <hi>et.</hi> 38.</note> To the fourth of theſe, which is <hi>Overtons</hi> Caſe <hi>en Paſ.</hi> 2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3. <hi>P. et Mar. rot.</hi> 58. and to the fifth, which is <hi>Newports</hi> Caſe, <hi>Paſ.</hi> 4. <hi>&amp;</hi> 5. <hi>P. &amp; Mar. rot.</hi> 45. onely theſe obſervations were ſaid over againe by Maſter Attorney, which were moved in the Argument made out of the Preſidents in the behalfe of the houſe of Commons at the firſt conference, and in the ſame Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument were fully and cleerely ſatisfied, as they were now againe in like manner.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">9. <hi>El. Lawrences caſe, et eodem Anno Conſtables caſe cite devant fo.</hi> 38. <hi>et</hi> 56.</note> To the ſixth, which is <hi>Lawrences</hi> Caſe, in 9. <hi>El. rot.</hi> 35. and to the ſeventh, which is <hi>Conſtables</hi> Caſe, <hi>Paſ.</hi> 9. <hi>El. Rot.</hi> 68. the ſame objections were likewiſe ſaid over againe by Maſter At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torney that are moved and clearly and fully anſwered in the Argument made at the laſt Conference out of Preſidents in the behalfe of the houſe of Commons. The force of the Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on being only that it appeared in the margin of the Roll, that the word Pardon was written, but it is plaine that the word there hath no reference at all to the reaſon why they are bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, nor could have reference to the cauſe, why they were committed, is utterly unknowne, and was not ſhewed.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">20. <hi>El. Brown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings caſe cite devant fo.</hi> 38. <hi>et</hi> 56.</note> To the eighth, which is <hi>Brownings</hi> Caſe, in <hi>Paſ.</hi> 20. <hi>El. Rot.</hi> 72. it was ſaid by Maſter Attomey, that he was bayled by a Letter from the Lords of the Counſell directed to the Judges of the Court, but being asked for that Letter, or any teſtimony of it, he could produce none at all, but ſaid he thought the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of it was burnt amongſt many other things of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell table at the burning of the Banquetting houſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">40. <hi>El. Hare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courts caſe cite devant, fo</hi> 39.</note> To the ninth, being <hi>Harecourts</hi> Caſe. <hi>Paſ.</hi> 40. <hi>El' Rot.</hi> 620. the ſelfe-ſame objection was made by him, but no warrant was ſhewed to maintaine his objection.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">43. <hi>El. cite de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, fo.</hi> 39. <hi>Catesbies caſe. Object. a ceo.</hi>
                  </note> To the tenth, which is <hi>Catesbies</hi> Caſe <hi>in vacatione Hill.</hi> 43. <hi>El.</hi> he ſaid that it was by direction of a Privie Seale from the Queene, and to that purpoſe he ſhewed the Privie Seale of 43. <hi>El.</hi> which is at Charge among the tranſcript of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords concerning bayles taken in Caſes when the King or the Lords of the Counſell aſſented.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <abbr>Rns</abbr> a ceo.</note> But it was replied, that the Privie Scale was made only for
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:54884:41"/> ſome particular Gentleman mentioned in it and none other, as indeed appeares in it. And then he ſaid, that it was likely that <hi>Catesby</hi> here had a privie Seale in this behalfe, becauſe thoſe other had ſo, which was all the force of his objection.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">12. <hi>Iac. Back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withs caſe cite devant. fo.</hi> 39. <hi>&amp;</hi> 58. <hi>Objection a ceo.</hi>
                  </note> To the 11 which is <hi>Beckwiths</hi> Caſe, in <hi>Hill.</hi> 12. <hi>Iac. Rot.</hi> 183. He ſaid the Lords of the Counſell ſent a letter to the Court of Kings Bench to bayle him, and indeed hee produced a letter, which could not by any meanes be found when the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments were made at the firſt conference. And this Letter, and a Copie of an obſcure report made by a young Student, that was brought to another purpoſe (as is hereafter ſhewed) were the onely things written of any kinde that M. Attorney pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, beſides the particular ſhewed by the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons at the firſt conference.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <abbr>Rns</abbr> al obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions.</note> To this it was replied, that the letter was of no moment, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing onely a direction to the chiefe Juſtice, and no matter of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, nor any way concernign the reſt of the Judges. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, the priſoner was bayleable by the Law, or not bayle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able; if bayleable by the Law, then was he to be bayled with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any ſuch Letter; if not bayleable by the Law, then plainly the Judges could not have bayled him upon the Letter with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out breach of their oathes, which is, that they are to doe Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice according to the Law, without having reſpect to any command whatſoever; ſo that the Letter in this Caſe, or the like in any other caſe, is for point of Law to no purpoſe, nor hath any weight at all by way of objection, againſt what the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord and judgement of the Court ſhewes us.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">14 <hi>Ia. Sir Tho. Mounſons caſe devant. fo.</hi> 40. <hi>&amp;</hi> 58.</note> The twelfth and laſt of theſe which is Sir <hi>Tho. Mounſons</hi> Caſe, in 14. <hi>Jac. Rot.</hi> 147. the ſame objection onely was ſaid over by him, which was moved and clearely anſwered in the Argument at the firſt conference, and that one ground which is infallible, that the judgement upon a returne is to be made onely out of what appeares in the body of the returne it ſelfe, was againe inſiſted upon in this caſe, as it was alſo in moſt of the reſt. And indeed that alone (which is more cleare Law) fully ſatisfies almoſt all kinde of objections that have beene made to any of theſe Preſidents, which thus righty underſtood, are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ample teſtimonies of the judgement of the Court of Kings
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:54884:42"/> Bench touching this great point, in the ſeverall ages &amp; raignes of the ſeverall Princes under which they fall.</p>
               <p>After his objections to theſe twelve, and the replies and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction given to theſe objections, hee came next to thoſe wherein the aſſent of the King or privie Counſell appeares to have beene upon the inlargement, but hee made not to any of theſe any other kind of objection whatſoever, then ſuch as are moved and clearely anſwered (as they were now againe) in the Argument made at the firſt conference. And for as much as it concernes Letters of Aſſent or direction, the ſame was here ſaid againe by way of reply to him, as is before ſaid touching the Letter in <hi>Beckworths</hi> Caſe, <hi>hoc ſupra.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After theſe were diſputed, hee came to urge the eight Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents which ſeemed to make for the other ſide, againſt the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of the houſe of Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons, which eight were uſed, and copies of them alſo given unto the Lords at the firſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ference.</p>
               <p>Of theſe eight, the firſt foure were urged by him, as being of one kinde, the difference of them being onely ſaid the ſame, onely in the names of priſons, and of perſons, they were but the ſelfe ſame.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vide touts ceux cite devant fo.</hi> 43 44. <hi>&amp;</hi> 62. 63 <hi>objections hors de eux.</hi>
                  </note> The force of theſe foure being objected thus, that <hi>Richard Everard</hi> for the purpoſe in the firſt of them, which is 5. <hi>H.</hi> 7. <hi>Rot.</hi> 18. <hi>Roger Cherry</hi> in the ſecond of them, which is 8. <hi>H.</hi> 7. <hi>Rot.</hi> 12. <hi>Chriſtopher Burton</hi> in the third, which is 9 <hi>H.</hi> 7. <hi>Rot.</hi> 14. and <hi>George Vrmſewick</hi> in the fourth of them, which is 19 <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 7. <hi>Rot.</hi> 13. were returned into the Kings Bench by ſeverall Writs of <hi>Habeas corpus,</hi> to have been committed, and detained in the priſons whence they came, <hi>per mandatum Dom. Regis,</hi> and that upon the returne they were committed to the Marſhalſea of the Kings Bench, and that howſoever it had beene objected againſt thoſe Preſidents, that this kind of commitment was by the courſe of that Court alwayes done before the Bayling of the priſoner, yet that it did not appeare that they were bayled.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <abbr>Rns</abbr> al obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions hors des dits preſidents.</note> The reply to theſe objections was, that the conſtant courſe of the Court of Kings Bench was, whoſoever came in upon a <hi>hab. corp.</hi> or otherwiſe upon any Writ into that Court, cannot be bayled, until he be firſt committed to the Mar. of that Court, &amp; that thence it was that all thoſe 4 were committed to the
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:54884:42"/> Marſhal, as appears by the entry, <hi>Marr'. &amp;c.</hi> which is the uſual entry in ſuch a caſe, and that the Clerks of that Court acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge this courſe &amp; entry to be moſt conſtantiſo that all the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference that can be made out of theſe 4 is, but that 4 priſoners being brought from foure ſeverall priſons by <hi>hab. corp.</hi> into the Kings Bench, and returned to ſtand committed <hi>per mandatum Dom. Regis,</hi> were ſo farre from being to be remanded by the Law, that in all theſe foure caſes, they were firſt taken from their ſeverall priſons wherein they had beene detained by ſuch a generall command, which could not have beene, if they had not beene adjudged in every of the Caſes to have beene bayleable by the Court, and that this Commitment of them to the Marſhall of the Kings Bench was the firſt ſtep towards the bayling of them, as in all other caſes; but that it appeares not, that either they ever demanded to be bayled, or that they were able to finde ſufficient Bayle. And if they did not the one, or could not doe the other, it may follow indeed that they were not bayled; but the commitment to the Kings Bench being the firſt ſtep to bayling, and by conſtant courſe it is, ſhewed moſt plainly, that they were bayleable by the Law, which is the onely thing in queſtion: ſo that although the foure Preſidents were ranked among them that may ſeeme to make againſt the reſolution of the Houſe of Commons, which was done, both becauſe they have this ſmall colour in them for the other ſide, to any man that is not acquainted with the nature and reaſons of the Entries and courſes of the Court of Kings Bench, and alſo becauſe all or ſome of them had beene uſed in the late great caſe in the Kings Bench, as Preſidents that made againſt this liberty claimed by the Subject, yet in truth all ſoure of them doe fully prove their reſolution, that is, they plainly ſhew that the Court of Kings Bench in every of them reſolved, that the priſoners ſo committed were bayle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, otherwiſe they had beene remanded, and not committed to the Marſhall of the Kings Bench. And this was the anſwer to the objection made by M. Attorney upon theſe foure Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, being all of them in the time of <hi>H.</hi> 7.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">7 H. 8. Pages caſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>cite devant. fo.</hi> 43. <hi>&amp;</hi> 63.</note> To the fifth of theſe being <hi>Ed Pages</hi> Caſe in 7. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>Rot.</hi> 23. M. Attorney objected thus, he ſaid, that <hi>Edward Page</hi> was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:54884:43"/> to the Marſhalſea of the Houſhold <hi>per mandatum Dom. Regis ibid. ſalvo cuſtodiend. &amp;c. Qui committitur Marr. Hoſpitii Dom. Regis, &amp;c.</hi> by which it appeares as he ſaid, that the Court remanded him to the priſon of the Marſhalſea of the houſhold, and hee ſaid, whereas it had beene objected at the firſt confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, that here was ſome miſtaking in the Entry, he ſaid he conceived indeed there was a miſtaking, but the miſtaking was, that the Clerk had entred <hi>committitur</hi> for <hi>remittitur,</hi> and that it ſhould have beene <hi>Qui remittitur Hoſpitii Dom. Regis,</hi> for when ever they remand a priſoner <hi>remittitur</hi> and not <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittitur</hi> ſhould be entred, and that miſtaking being ſo rectified and underſtood, he conceived it was a direct Preſident againſt the reſolution of the Houſe of Commons.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <abbr>Rns</abbr> al dit ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection.</note> To this it was anſwered by the Gent. of the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, that there was no doubt indeed but that a miſtaking was by the entry of the Clerk, but that the miſtaking was quite of another nature. The addition of theſe words <hi>Hoſpitii Dom. Regis</hi> was the miſtaking, and the entry ſhould have bin <hi>qui committitur Marr. &amp;c.</hi> onely, that is, that he is committed to the Marſhall of the Kings Bench, and ſo indeed the force of the Preſident ſhould be juſt the ſame with the firſt foure, but the ignorance of the Clerk that entred it, knowing not how to diſtinguiſh betweene the Marſhall of the Houſhold, and the Marſhall of the Kings Bench, was the cauſe of the Addition of theſe words, and to confirme fully this kinde of interpretation of that Preſident, and of the miſtaking in it, 'twas obſerved by the Gent. of the Houſe of Commons, that there is in the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine of the Roll an infallible Character that juſtifies ſo much, for by the courſe of that Court whenſoever a priſoner is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the Marſhal of the Kings Bench, and not remanded, the word <hi>Marr'.</hi> &amp;c. is written in the Margin ſhort, by <hi>Marr' &amp;c.</hi> turned up, and that is never written, but when the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſence of the Entry is, that the priſoner is committed to the priſon of the ſame Court, now in this Caſe in the Margin <hi>Marr'.</hi> is likewiſe written, which moſt plainely ſhewes the truth of the Caſe was, that this <hi>Page</hi> was committed to the Marſhall of the Kings Bench, and not remanded, which if hee had beene, neither could the Entry have beene <hi>committitur,</hi> nor
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:54884:43"/> ſhould the Margine of the Rolle have had <hi>Marr'</hi> written in it. And thus they anſwered Maſter Attorneys Objection touching this Preſident, and concluded that now beſides the firſt foure of the eight, they had another, and ſo five, more to prove that a priſoner committed <hi>per mandatum Dom. Regis</hi> ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally was bayled by the Judgement of the Court. Howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it appeares not in theſe particulars that they were bayled, which perhaps they were not, either becauſe they prayed it not, or becauſe they could not find ſufficient Bayle.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">8. <hi>Iac. Caeſars caſe cite devant fo.</hi> 46. <hi>&amp;</hi> 64. <hi>Objections hors de ceo.</hi>
                  </note> To the ſixth of theſe eight Preſidents, being the Caſe of <hi>Tho. Caeſar in</hi> 8. <hi>Iac. Rot.</hi> 99. Maſter Attorney objected it thus, That <hi>Caeſar</hi> being committed <hi>per mandatum Dom. Regis</hi> to the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhalſea of the Houſhold was returned upon <hi>Habeas Corpus</hi> to be ſo committed, and therefore deteyned in Priſon, and that the entrie is <hi>qui remittitur priſonae pred.</hi> by which it appeares cleerely, that he was remanded to the ſame priſon from whence he came.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <abbr>Rns</abbr> al dits obiections.</note> To which the Gentlemen of the houſe of Commons gave this anſwer, they ſaid that the uſuall entrie of a <hi>remittitur,</hi> when it is to ſhew that the Court by way of Judgement or award upon a reſolution or debate remand the priſoner, is <hi>quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſecundum legem deliberatus fuerit,</hi> but when they adviſe, or give day to the Keeper of the priſon to amend his returne, or the like, then the entrie is only <hi>remittitur</hi> generally, or <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittitur priſonae pred.</hi> But it was indeed affirmed by Maſter <hi>Keeling,</hi> a Clerke of experience in that Court, that the entrie of <hi>Remittitur</hi> generally, or <hi>Remittitur priſonae pred.</hi> was indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferently uſed for the ſame that <hi>Remittitur quouſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> &amp;c.</hi> yet it was expreſly ſhewed by the Gent. of the houſe of Commons that there was ſometimes a difference, and that ſo it might, well be in this caſe, for in the laſt of theſe eight preſidents, which is <hi>Saltonſtals</hi> Caſe, they obſerved that <hi>Remittitur priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae pred.</hi> is often uſed, only for a remanding during the time that the Court gave leave for the Warden of the Fleet to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend the returne, which ſhewes plainly, though ſometimes <hi>Remittitur</hi> generally, and <hi>Remittitur quouſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>
                  </hi> may meane but the ſame, yet ſometimes alſo it doth not meane the ſame. And that in this Caſe of <hi>Caeſar</hi> it meant only but ſo much as it doth
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:54884:44"/> twice in that of <hi>Saltonſtalls</hi> Caſe, which was proved alſo by a rule of the Court, which was cited out of the Rule Booke of the Court of Kings Bench, by which rule the Court expreſly ordered, that unleſſe the Steward and Marſhall of the houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold did ſufficiently return the Writ of <hi>Habeas Corpus</hi> for <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar,</hi> that he ſhould be diſcharged, the words of the Rule are <hi>Niſi pred. Seneſchall' &amp; Marr' Hoſpitii Dom. Regis ſufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter returnabit bre. de Habeas Corpus Thomae Caeſar die Mercur. prox' poſt feſtum Sanct. Martin. defendens exonerabitur.</hi> And this was the opinion of the Court, which ſhewes that the Court was ſo farre from remaunding him upon the re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urne, that they reſolved, that unleſſe ſome better returne was made, the priſoner ſhould be diſcharged of his firſt impriſonment, though it appeare to them out of the body of the returne upon which they are to judge, that he was committed <hi>per manda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum Dom. Regis</hi> only. And the Rule not only ſhewes the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the Court then to be agreeable with the reſolution of the houſe of Commons, but alſo proves that <hi>Remittitur</hi> gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, and <hi>Remittitur priſonae predict.</hi> doth not alwayes implie a remanding upon Judgement or debate. And this anſwer was given to this of <hi>Caeſars</hi> Caſe, and that is the ſixth of this number.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">12. <hi>Iac. Deme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strius</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers caſe <hi>cite devant, fo.</hi> 46. <hi>&amp;</hi> 64. Obiections hors de ceo.</note> The ſeventh, is the Caſe of <hi>James Demeſtrius,</hi> it was 12. <hi>Iac. Rot.</hi> 153. Maſter Attorney objected, that this <hi>Demeſtrius</hi> and divers others being Brewers, were committed <hi>per Conſilium Dom. Regis</hi> to the Marſhalſea of the houſhold, and that upon the commitment being ſo generally returned they were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, and that the entrie was <hi>immediate remittitur praefat. Marr' hoſpitij praed.</hi> where obſerves that <hi>immediate</hi> ſhewes that the Judges of that time were ſo reſolved of this queſtion, that they remaunded them preſently, as men that well knew what the Law was herein.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <abbr>Rns</abbr> al dit obiections.</note> Hereunto the Gent. of the Houſe of Commons gave this anſwer; Firſt, that the <hi>remittitur</hi> in this Caſe is but as the other in <hi>Caeſars,</hi> and ſo proves nothing againſt them. Secondly, that <hi>immediate</hi> being added to it ſhewes plainly, that it was done without debate, or any Argument or conſideration had of it, which makes the Authoritie of the Preſident to be of no force
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:54884:44"/> in point of Law. For Judgements and awards given upon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberation and debate only are proofes and Arguments of weight, and not any ſudden act of the Court without debate or deliberation. And the entrie of <hi>immediate</hi> being propoſed to Maſter <hi>Keeling,</hi> it was confirmed by him, that by the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie it appeared by their courſe, that the remaunding of him was the ſelfe-ſame day he was brought, which as it was ſaid by the Gent. of the houſe of Commons might be upon the riſing of the Court, or upon adviſement, or the like; and this anſwer was given to this Preſident of the Brewers.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">12. <hi>Iac. Salton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtalls caſe cite devant, fo.</hi> 49. &amp; 65 Obiections hors de ceo.</note> To the laſt of theſe eight which Maſter Attorney objected is <hi>Saltonſtalls</hi> Caſe 12. <hi>Jac.</hi> he was committed <hi>per mandatum à Dom. de privato Conſilio,</hi> and being returned by the Warden of the Fleet to be ſo, <hi>Remittitur priſonae pred.</hi> and in 13. <hi>Iac.</hi> in the ſame Caſe there is <hi>remittitur</hi> generally in the Roll, and theſe two make but one Caſe, and are one Preſident.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <abbr>Rns</abbr> al dits obiections.</note> To this the Gent. of the houſe of Commons anſwered, that it is true the Rolles have ſuch entries of <hi>remittitur</hi> in them ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally, But that proves nothing upon the reaſon before uſed by them in <hi>Caeſars</hi> Caſe. But alſo <hi>Saltonſtall</hi> was committed for another cauſe, beſides <hi>per mandatum Dom. Regis,</hi> for a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt againſt an Order in the Chancery, and that was in the returne alſo. And beſides the Court, as it appeares in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, gave ſeverall dayes to the Warden of the Fleet to amend his returne, which they would not have done, if they had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived it ſufficient, for that which is ſufficient needs not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment.</p>
               <p>To this Maſter Attorney replied, that they gave him day to amend his returne, in reſpect of that part of it which concerns the Order in Chancery, and not in reſpect of that which was <hi>per mandatum Dom. Regis.</hi> But the Gent. of the Houſe of Commons anſwered, that that appeared not any where, nor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed is it likely at all, nor can be reaſonably ſo underſtood, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe if the other returne <hi>per mandatum Dom. Regis</hi> had beene ſufficient by it ſelfe, then doubtleſſe they would have reman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him upon that alone, for then they needed not at all to have ſtood upon the other part of the returne in this Caſe. So that out of the Record it ſelfe it appeares fully, that the Court
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:54884:45"/> conceived the returne to be inſufficient. So the Gent. of the houſe of Commons concluded, that they had a great number of Preſidents, beſides divers Acts of Parliament, and reaſons of Common law, agreeable to their reſolution, and that there was not one Preſident at all that made againſt them, but indeed, that almoſt all that were brought as well againſt them as for them, if rightly underſtood, made fully for the maintenance of their concluſion, and that there was not one Example or Preſident of a <hi>Remittitur</hi> in any kind upon the point before that of <hi>Caeſars</hi> Caſe, which is before cleered with the reſt, and is but of late time, and of no moment againſt the reſolution of the Houſe of Commons.</p>
               <p>And thus, for ſo much as concerned the preſidents of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, the firſt day of the Conference deſired by the Lords ended.</p>
               <p>The next day they deſired another Conference with the Houſe of Commons, at which it pleaſed the Committee of both Houſes to heare Maſter Attorney againe make what Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections he could againſt other parts of the Argument formerly delivered from the Houſe of Commons, he objected againſt the Acts of Parliament, and againſt the reaſons of the Law, and his objections to thoſe parts were anſwered, as it appeares by the Anſwers by order given into the Houſe of Commons by the Gent. that made them. He objected alſo upon the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond day againſt the ſecond kind of Preſidents, which are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions of Judges in former times, and not of Record, and brought alſo ſome other teſtimonies of the opinions of Jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges in former times touching this point.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Reſolution de touts les Iudges,</hi> 34. <hi>El. Objections hors de ceo per l' At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torney.</hi>
                  </note> Firſt, for that Reſolution of all the Judges of <hi>England</hi> in 34. <hi>El.</hi> mentioned and read in the Arguments read at the firſt Conference, he ſaid, That it was directly againſt the reſolution of the Houſe of Commons, and obſerved the words of it in one place to be, that perſons ſo committed by the King, or by the Counſell, may not be delivered by any of the Courts <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And in another, that if the cauſe were expreſſed, either in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall or in ſpecialtie, it was ſufficient, and he ſaid that the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing of a Cauſe in generaltie, was to ſhew the King and the Counſels co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand, and to this purpoſe he read the whole words
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:54884:45"/> of that reſolution of the Judges. Then he objected alſo, that in a report of one <hi>Roſwels</hi> Caſe in the Kings Bench in 13 <hi>Jac.</hi> he found that the opinion of the Judges of that Court (Sir <hi>Edward Cooke</hi> being then chiefe Juſtice and one of them) was that a priſoner being committed <hi>per mandatum Dom. Regis,</hi> or <hi>privati Conſilii,</hi> without cauſe ſhewed, and ſo returned, could not be bayled, becauſe it might be matter of State, or <hi>Arc anum nuperii,</hi> for which he ſtood committed. And this al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo he added, an opinion he found in a Journall in the Houſe of Commons of 18. <hi>Iac.</hi> wherein Sir <hi>Edward Cooke</hi> ſpeaking to a bill preferred for the explanation of <hi>Magna Charta</hi> touching impriſonment, ſaid in the ſame Houſe, that one ſo committed could not be inlarged by the Law, becauſe it might be matter of State for which he was committed, and amongſt theſe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections, as his objections of the other nature, alſo he ſpake of the confidence that was ſhewed in the behalfe of the Houſe of Commons: and he ſaid, it was not confidence on either part could adde any thing to the determination of the queſtion; but if he would, that he had as much reaſon of Confidence for the other ſide againſt the reſolution of the Houſe of Commons, grounding himſelfe upon the force of his objections, which as he conceived had ſo weakned the Arguments of the Houſe of Commons.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <abbr>Rns</abbr> al dits ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections.</note> To this a reply was made, and firſt it was ſaid to the Lords on the behalfe of the Houſe of Commons, that notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any thing yet objected, they were upon cleare reaſon ſtill confident of the truth of their firſt reſolution, grounded upon ſo juſt examination, and deliberation taken by them. And it was obſerved to the Lords alſo, that their confidence herein was of another nature, and of greater waight, then any confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence that could be expreſſed by M. Attorney, or whomſoever elſe being of his Majeſties Counſell learned.</p>
               <p>To which purpoſe the Lords were deſired to take into their preſent memories the difference between the preſent qualities of the Gent. that ſpake in the behalf of the Houſe of Commons, &amp; of the Kings learned Counſel in their ſpeaking there howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever accidently they were both men of the ſame profeſſion: For the Kings Counſell ſpake as Counſell perpetually retained
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:54884:46"/> by Fee, and if they made gloſſes or advantagious interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons whatſoever for their own part, they did but what belonged unto them; but the Gent. that ſpake in behalfe of the Houſe of Commons, came there, bound on the one ſide by the truſt repo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in them by their Country that ſent them, and on the other ſide by an oath taken by every of them before hee ſit in the Houſe, to maintaine and defend the rights and prerogatives of the Crown, for even in the point of Confidence alone thoſe of them that ſpeake as retained Counſell by perpetuall Fee, and thoſe that by their place being admitted to ſpeake, are bound to utter nothing but truth, both by ſuch a truſt and ſuch an oath, were no way to be ſo compared or counterpoiſed, as if the one were of no more waight then the other.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Reſolution de</hi> 34. El. <hi>explaine &amp; expound.</hi>
                  </note> For that of the reſolution of all the Judges in England in 34. <hi>El.</hi> It was ſhewed that plainly it agreed with the reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of the Houſe of Commons, for although indeed it might have beene expreſſed with more perſpicuity, yet the words of it as they are, ſufficiently ſhew that to them. To that purpoſe, beſides the words of the whole frame of this reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Judges, as it is in the Copie tranſcribed out of the Lord chiefe Juſtice <hi>Anderſons</hi> Book, written with his owne hand, which book was here offered to be ſhewed in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe of the Houſe of Commons, it was obſerved, that the words of the firſt part of it ſhew plainly, that all the Judges of England then reſolved, that the priſoners ſpoken of in that firſt part of their reſolution, were onely priſoners committed with cauſe ſhewed; for they onely ſay they might not be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vered by any of the Courts without due triall, by law and judgement of the acquittall they muſt be delivered; but it is cleare that no triall or acquittall can be had, where there is not ſome cauſe laid to their charge, for which they ought to ſtand committed. Therefore in that part of the reſolution ſuch priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners are onely meant as are committed with cauſe ſhewed, as which alſo the Judges expreſly in that reſolution expreſly thought neceſſary, as appeares in the ſecond part of their reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, wherein they have theſe words, If upon the returne of their <hi>Habeas Corpus,</hi> the cauſe of their commitment be certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied to the Judges, as it ought to be, &amp;c. By which words they
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:54884:46"/> ſhew plainly, that every returne of a commitment is inſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, that hath not a cauſe ſhewed of it. And to that which M. Attorney ſaid, as if the Cauſe were ſufficiently expreſſed in generality, if the Kings command or the Counſels were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in it, as if that were meant in the reſolution for a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient generall cauſe, It was anſwered, that it was never heard of in Law, that the power or perſon that committed the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner was underſtood, for the <hi>cauſa captionis</hi> or <hi>cauſa detentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis,</hi> but onely the reaſon why that power or perſon commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the priſoner, as alſo in common ſpeech if any man aske why or for what cauſe a man ſtands committed, the anſwere is not, that ſuch a one committed him, but his offence or ſome other cauſe is underſtood in the queſtion, and is to be ſhewed in the Anſwer, but to ſay that ſuch a one commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the priſoner, is an anſwer onely to the queſtion, who committed him? and not why or for what canſe hee ſtands ſo committed.</p>
               <p>That for that of the Copie of the report in 13 <hi>Iac.</hi> ſhewed forth by M. Attorney, it was anſwered by the Gent. of the Houſe of Commons, that the report it ſelfe which had beene before ſeene, and peruſed among many other things at a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee made by the Houſe, was of ſleight or no authority, for that it was taken by one who was at that time a young Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, and as a reporter in the Kings Bench, and there was not any other report to be found to agree with it. Secondly, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the reports of young Students, when they take the words of Judges as they fall from their mouthes at the Bench, and in the ſame perſon and forme as they have ſpoken, may be of good credit, yet in this Caſe there was not one word ſo reported, but in truth there being three caſes of a time in the Kings Bench, one <hi>Roſewells</hi> Caſe, <hi>Allens,</hi> and one <hi>Saltonſtalls</hi> caſe, every of which had ſomething of like nature in it, the Student having beene preſent in the Court, made up the frame of one report or caſe out of all three in his owne words, and ſo put it into his Book: ſo that there is not a word in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, but it is framed according to the Students fancie, as it is written, and nothing is expreſſed in it, as it came from the mouth of the Judges, otherwiſe then as his fancy directed him.</p>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:54884:47"/>
               <p>Thirdly, there are in the report plaine falſhoods of matter of fact, which are to be attributed either to the Judges, or to the reporter. It is moſt likely by all reaſon that they procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from the reporters faults, and howſoever, theſe matters of falſhood ſhew ſufficiently that the credit of the reſt is of light value. It it ſaid in the report that <hi>Harecourt</hi> being committed by the Counſell, was bayled in 40. <hi>El.</hi> upon a Privie Seale or a Letter, whereas in truth there is no ſuch thing. And it is ſaid here, that kind of Letters are filed in the Crowne Office, whereas in truth there was any ſuch kind of Letters filed there in any caſe whatſoever, that reſolution of the Judges in 34. <hi>El.</hi> is miſ-cited there, and made in 36. <hi>El.</hi> And it is ſaid there, that by that reſolution a Priſoner returned to be committed by the Command of the King might not at all be delivered by the Court, whereas no ſuch thing is comprehended in that reſolution.</p>
               <p>But that which is of moſt moment is, that howſoever the truth of the report were, yet the opinion of the Judges being ſudden, and without any debate had of the Caſe, is of light moment, for in difficult points eſpecially the moſt grave and learned men living may on the ſudden let fall (and that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any diſparagement to them) ſuch opinions as they may will, and ought to change upon further inquirie, examination, and full debate had before them, and mature deliberation ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by them. Now plainly in that of 13. <hi>Jac.</hi> there is not ſo much as a pretence of any debate at the Barre or Bench. All that is reported to have beene, is reported as ſpoken of the ſudden. And can any man take ſuch a ſudden opinion to be of value againſt ſuch debates and mature deliberations ſince had of the point? And indeed this great point, and all circumſtances belonging to it, hath within this halfe yeare beene ſo fully ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined and ſearched into, that it may well be affirmed, that the moſt learned man whoſoever that hath now conſidered of it, hath within that time, or might have learned more reaſon of ſatisfaction in it then ever before he met with. Therefore the ſudden opinion of the Judges to the contrary is of no va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue here, which alſo is to be ſaid by that opinion obliviouſly delivered in the Commons houſe in 18. <hi>Iac.</hi> as Maſter Attor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:54884:47"/> objected out of the Journall of the Houſe. But beſides, neither was the truth of that report of that opinion of the Journall any way acknowledged, for it was ſaid on the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe of the houſe of Commons, that their Journals were for matters of Orders and reſolutions of the Houſe of ſuch Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, as that they were as their Records. But for any parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular mans opinion noted in any of them, it was ſo farre from being of any authority there with them, that in truth no par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular opinion is at all to be entred in them, and that their Clerke offends whenever bee doth to the contrary. And to conclude, no ſuch opinion whatſoever can be ſufficient to wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the cleare Law comprehended in theſe reſolutions of the Houſe of Commons grounded upon ſo many Acts of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſo much reaſon of the Common law, and ſo many Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidents of Record, and the reſolution of all the Judges of <hi>England,</hi> and againſt which not one Law written or unwrit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, not one Preſident, not one reaſon hath beene brought that make any thing to the contrary.</p>
               <p>And thus to this purpoſe ended the next day of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference deſired by the Lords, and had by a Committee of both Houſes.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
